<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main"/><author/></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date/></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p><date when="2015-07-24"/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><date>$LastChangedDate: 2015-07-24T10:53:10Z$</date><name/></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div><head rend="Normal" meTypesetSize="100" meTypesetHeadingID="0"><hi meTypesetSize="100" rend="">Part 1: Away</hi></head><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Tucked away somewhere in the twisting innards of Mulago Hospital,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Kampala, Uganda, there lies the pink, neatly stapled medical file of a man</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">who is doomed to die. I know this because I saw him on Thursday night.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">"There's an interesting case you should see if you have time," said the attending doctor</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">cheerfully, "you should look up his condition in your book and take a history. It might </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">be good for a case write-up when you get home."</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">We had just stepped into the casualty department, hoping to catch some of the </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">evening's action. It seemed as though it had found us. Puzzled, one of us asked </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">what the patient in question had.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">"Rabies. He's a classic case." She paused. "But I'm not sure what to do about it."</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Having had her say, she closed the door to the treatment room behind her, leaving</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">us alone in the crowded hallway.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">We had only been in Kampala for two weeks but already we had seen our fair share </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">of 'interesting cases'-- that is to say, we had seen dozens of people whose disease had</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">progressed to the point where their clinical findings were evident even to our clumsy hands.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Young diabetics with histories of multiple DKAs because they could not afford insulin, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">children with spleens swollen from chronic malaria, and wasted people of all ages exhibiting </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">the innumerable and tragic complications HIV infection were all daily sites for us in Mulago Hospital.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">At home in Canada, patients would rarely if ever present at such advanced stages. They </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">would be considered exceptional. Here, they were the rule.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">To see these patients --cases-- day after day was of course absoultely heart-wrenching. Earlier in our </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">training, before we had become comfortable in a clinical setting, any one of the patients </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">we now saw hourly would have been recognized only as the individual tragedy it was,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">a unique piece of human suffering.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Now, on our first major clinical elective, we had already developed a student's enthusiasm for learning</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">to accompany our empathetic urges. Foucault would have referred to this as the development of the "medical gaze." </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">For us, though, it was not a philosophical construct but the learned, pragmatic response to one of the most real and</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">tearing realities of medical education: our learning depends on the willingness of patients to share their suffering with us </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">and our ability to occasionally look beyond that suffering and see the scientific principles that lay behind it.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">We stepped into the treatment room like four scared, shocked kittens comically dolled up in white coats. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The consultant strode in with confident ease and without pause began to take a history from the patient</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">and his family, trying to piece together their story. None of us foreigners spoke the local Lugandan language, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">so we had no choice but to wait until the consultant could translate for us. As we watched meekly, the patient, in evident discomfort,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">lay supine, knees bent, head thrown back, with the freshly healed stigmata of a dog's bite on his distal forearm.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Soon satisfied with the history, the consultant gave us a quick summary.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The man had received the bite while defending his daughter from the attack of a wild dog. Thinking </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">nothing of the minor wound on his arm and daunted by the experience and cost of coming to Mulago hospital, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">he had dismissed the injury until he began to develop his current symptoms of extreme terror, laryngeal spasm, and hydrophobia.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">A classic case.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p></div><div><head rend="Normal" meTypesetSize="100" meTypesetHeadingID="1"><hi meTypesetSize="100" rend="">	Rabies</hi></head><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	A uniformly fatal infection, still common in many parts of the tropics, that is caused </hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	by the rabies virus... once clinical symptoms have appeared, the patient will die. However,</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	if the infection is caught soon after transmission and before the onset of clinical symptoms, </hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	rabies can be prevented by post-exposure vaccination.</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote/></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	There is currently no effective treatment for a person who is showing signs and symptoms</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	of rabies infection. In this situation, management is symptomatic with sufficient sedation</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	and analgesia to relieve pain and terror.</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote/></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	Vaccination within days of exposure is 100% effective in preventing the progression of the </hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	infection to encephalitis. However, the cheap Semple vaccine that is used most widely in</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	the developing world is itself capable of initiating encephalitis... the vaccine can produce</hi></p></quote></cit><cit><quote><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">	severe CNS disease with a 3% mortality.</hi></p></quote></cit><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">							The Oxford Handbook of Tropical Medicine, second edition</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">							pp. 410-413</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The medical plan for the man was continued observation, accompanied by any</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">palliation the hospital resources could afford. We never found out whether or not he was told of his prognosis,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">or whether any effort would be made to find the daughter and initiate the post-exposure rabies vaccine protocol</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">before it was too late. Such follow-up was not always possible in the chaos of the hospital.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The consultant volunteered to give us a lift so we wouldn't have to walk home in the dark.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">For four white mzungus it was probably a risk not worth taking. Not even the jostling</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">of his car over the deep potholes of Wandegeya road could shake the image of the bitten man or his story from my head.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Places like Kampala are, for me at least, the places where all of the most enraging injustices </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">of the world are presented, bare, raw, and worn to the bone. Seeing people succumb to diseases </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">and injuries which in my native Canada would be dealt with quickly as minor inconveniences,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">turns each death and disability into a tragedy all the more powerful because it is </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">so obviously preventable and unnecessary. While such tragedies may be the visible vestiges of </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">huge economic and political systems bearing their full weight down on the most remote </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">and oppressed members of society, to see them first-hand fills one with a sense of personal grief and urgency to act.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">There is also often a sense of guilt. Walking through the hospital, armed with gloves, gowns, and masks,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">chowing down daily on malaria prophylaxis while the doctors and patients struggle to scrape together</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">the few dollars it takes to get an needed x-ray, I am acutely aware of my privileged place in those systems which </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">keeps the local people under such unjust conditions. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Part of me wants to not settle for anything more than what the people here, who have taken us into their homes, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">fed us, and taught us, could possibly get themselves. Another part of me knows that like it </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">or not, my position in the world is somehow different from that of the others in the hospital.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p></div><div><head rend="Normal" meTypesetSize="100" meTypesetHeadingID="2"><hi meTypesetSize="100" rend="">Part 2: Home</hi></head><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">I woke from my sleep that Saturday evening in sheets soaked with sweat,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">as Sarah and I listened to the shrill squeals of bats overhead.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">We were sleeping in a small cabin at Murchison Falls National Park in</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">north-western Uganda, having just completed a successful two days of safari in and about the Nile river. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">After two weeks spent mostly in the cramped quarters of Mulago hospital, and the smoggy, congested streets of Kampala,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">taking a leisurely, planned tour of the park to see some wildlife was a welcome diversion.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">All of that came to a sudden end with the flap of a pair of leathery wings in the air around our beds. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Having just two nights earlier seen a man in the early throes of rabies, neither Sarah or I were too </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">thrilled at the possibility of meeting that same fate ourselves. We spent a frantic night in the pitch-dark room, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">terrified that maybe we had been bitten. Bat bites, I had learned, were often invisible and painless, only revealing</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">themselves once it was too late.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">In some ways, the role of the physician in health and disease is simple.  </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">The explicit teaching is this: </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Patients arrive with a chief complaint, which sometimes clearly identifies the disease but is sometimes misleading. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">It is the job of the physician to illicit the important symptoms and signs and evaluate their importance in order to </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">determine the most likely diagnoses and the patient's likely prognosis. This information should be clearly and empathetically</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">communicated to the patient. Then, together, the patient and the doctor have to evaluate the risks and benefits </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">of various treatments, and assist the patient in selecting one which will meet their own personal needs and goals.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">The implicit teaching is this:</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">As physicians, we are equipped with knowledge and skills which suffering individuals are not</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">and by which we may be of assistance. Although the patient's perspective is vital in determining the</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">goals of treatment, medical professionals should retain a sense of objectivity in order to more accurately</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">determine diagnoses and the relative merits of various treatments. There is an "us" and a "them." The "other" persists.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">"Doctor, heal thyself!"</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Of course, all the above notions of objective risk assessment tend to go out the window whenever we apply them</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">to ourselves. 'Medical Student Syndrome,' technically referred to 'hypochondriasis of medical students,' is a particularly</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">acute example of this. It is not uncommon for a student during the course of their studies to diagnose themselves</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">with, for instance, an aortic dissection, gallstones, peptic ulcer disease, or any one of a number of metabolic</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">or endocrine derangements, depending on which disease they happen to be studying at the time.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">When it comes to ourselves, we seem unable to stick to the objectivity and rules we so cooly apply to others.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">So it may be, too, with our ideals of health and justice. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The ride home the next morning took us on sunny winding road through the Rwenzori mountains and their lush</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">fields of tea and tobacco. Sarah was quiet for the entire ride, likely due in part to the gravol, but certainly also due to </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">her worries about what might happen after the 9-20 day rabies incubation period we had so recently learned about, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">and the risks of the local Ugandan rabies post-exposure protocols.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">When we arrived back at our hostel in Kampala that night, I called my mother back home in Hamilton</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">and asked for her advice as to what we should do about the possible rabies exposure. She made a few calls </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">to travel doctors in the area and quickly found out that there was another local option, a private clinic called "The Surgery," </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">the longest continually-held practice in Kampala. Started in the 1940s by ex-pat British GPs while Uganda was still under colonial rule, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">the clinic has been used by international travellers to Kampala for whom nothing less than the 'western standard' would suffice. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">After speaking to a nurse at the clinic, we soon found that although The Surgery did not use the Semple post-exposure vaccine,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">the protocol they followed was substantially different from the one we used in Canada, in particular because it did not include</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">the immunoglobin injection during the initial treatment phase.  The nurse told us that despite that, they'd never had any </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">reports of the protocol's failure in all their many years of practice.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">If it is a tragedy each time a Ugandan dies from a preventable, treatable illness, then what is it called</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">when a visiting medical student witnesses that tragedy and then promptly visits a clinic which costs </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">ten times as much for a much more minor condition? Reasonable precaution? Irony? </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">To me it felt like hypocrisy. Most Canadians point to the ideals of Medicare as one of Canada's greatest </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">civil achievements: a system of care based on need rather than the ability to pay. As a society, we pool </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">risk, share benefits, and sacrifice autonomy for the sake of others in society, usually complete strangers. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">What makes us do so for the sake of strangers within our country but not elsewhere in the world? </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Economics? Geography? Futility?</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">"You need that immunoglobin. All of the doctors here at home agree." </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Despite my protests, consults with the local Mulago doctors, and personal research, I knew that the</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">doctors at home were probably right. If I had been bitten by the bat, and if it had carried rabies, the </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">only rational thing to do would be to minimize the chances that the disease would spread throughout my system. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">The severe consequences of infection were too great to avoid taking all necessary precautions.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">Unfortunately, even if I managed to procure local immunoglobin, there were still complications. The concentration</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">of IG in human blood is so low that to create the substantial dose necessary for a rabies protocol requires extracts </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">of blood from multiple donors. In Uganda, with rates of HIV infection in urban areas reported to be as high as 30%, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">receiving such a concentrate of blood products was a risky prospect in itself.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">"Look, health care is practiced differently in Uganda than it is in Canada... and since you can't get the immunoglobin there, </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">your best bet really is to come home. So quit stalling in Kampala and start making arrangements to fly back as soon as possible."</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">I hung up the phone, paused, and started to formulate my plans.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Many of the doctors we worked alongside at Mulago had actually spent a portion of their</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">training in Hamilton. There was a clear sense of camaraderie and shared experience between us</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">as we traded back and forth our hilarious fish-out-of-water stories. It was not uncommon for the docs to discuss</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">a patient's assessment and plan with finality, and then direct some additional comments towards us: </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">"Of course, back in Canada you would likely deal with the problem using... since you'd have the resources for it. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Here we can't do that so we have to make do."</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">Watching the skilled hands and minds of the doctors as they waded through the crowded wards was a unique experience.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">I can't really imagine what it was like for them, having to come up with ad-hoc, 'good-enough' solutions for complicated</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">problems after having studied and practiced in Canada where we investigate every symptom to the nth degree with extensive</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">follow-up. Were they driven crazy knowing all too well what they were missing? Did they think it unfair that in Canada we </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">as students wielded resources even the top doctors in Mulago would envy?</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">None of the doctors or nurses or other professionals I met working at the hospital, or even any of the patients,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">indicated that sentiment even once. Rather, there seemed to be an understanding and resignation to our unequal</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">relationships: 'Even if we don't have the resources you do at home, come, learn from us and let us learn from you too; </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">we understand why you look after yourselves with such caution.'</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16">The inequalities that separate us may be huge, but they do not have to be barriers to meaningful relationships. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">~~~~</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">A few days later, as my plane smoothly glided off the runway at Entebbe International Airport,</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">my thoughts swarmed with all of the people, places, and events I had witnessed during the past few weeks. </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">After two airplane meals I started to think about how I was going to organize the 28 days </hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">of rabies vaccinations around my remaining clinical electives.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">By the time I arrived home 23 hours later, I had comfortably slipped back into my daily routines.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">I almost felt as though nothing had changed, that maybe I had never left home at all.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">But Mulago is still there. The doctors are there. And the bitten man might still be there.</hi></p><p rend="Normal"><hi meTypesetSize="16" rend="italic">I'll never know.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>