<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">The Journal Title</journal-id>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0000-000X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>The Publisher Name</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1000/123456</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group>
          <subject>Sample Articles</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>A Sample Article Title</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Eve</surname>
            <given-names>Martin Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="lincoln"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="lincoln">
          <institution>University of Lincoln</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>1</fpage>
      <lpage>2</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2014, Martin Paul Eve</copyright-statement>
        <license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The citation of this article must include: the name(s) of the authors, the name of the journal, the full URL of the article (in a hyperlinked format if distributed online) and the DOI number of the article.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri>https://www.martineve.com/</self-uri>
      <abstract>
        <p>This is a sample abstract that forms part of the metadataSample.xml file in meTypeset.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title/>
      <p>Variation in Rates of Uptake of Preventive Options in BRCA1 and BRCA2 Mutation Carriers Across Canada</p>
      <p>Kelly A. Metcalfe1, 2, Parviz Ghadirian3, Barry Rosen4, William Foulkes5, Charmaine Kim-Sing6, Andrea Eisen7, Peter Ainsworth8, Doug Horsman6, Christine Maugard9, Diane Provencher9, Andre Robidoux3, Dawna Gilchrist10, Albert Chudley11, Edmond G. Lemire12, Susan Armel4, Amy Finch1,4, Ping Sun1, &amp; Steven A. Narod1</p>
      <p>1 Centre for Research in Women&#8217;s Health, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada </p>
      <list list-type="order">
        <list-item>
          <p>2Faculty of Nursing, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada   3 Epidemiology Research Unit, Centre Hospitalier de l&#8217;Universit&#233; de Montr&#233;al (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa8a0c642-aa77-4b3d-a009-be93b3d8ac0a">CHUM</xref>), H&#244;tel-Dieu, University of Montr&#233;al , QC, Canada  4 Division of Gynecologic Oncology, Princess Margaret Hospital and University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada  5 Program in Cancer Genetics, Department of Oncology and Human Genetics, McGill University, Montr&#233;al, QC, Canada  6 BC Cancer Agency, Vancouver, BC, Canada  7 Toronto Sunnybrook Regional Cancer Centre, Toronto, ON, Canada  8 London Health Sciences Centre, The University of Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada  9 Hospital Notre Dame, Montr&#233;al, QC, Canada   10  Departments of Medicine and Medical Genetics, University of Alberta, Edmonton, AB, Canada   11 Children&#8217;s Hospital, The University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada  12 Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, SK, Canada  2Faculty of Nursing, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada  3 Epidemiology Research Unit, Centre Hospitalier de l&#8217;Universit&#233; de Montr&#233;al (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb2ed204a-fe99-4bf2-b30a-d28858e1e598">CHUM</xref>), H&#244;tel-Dieu, University of Montr&#233;al , QC, Canada 4 Division of Gynecologic Oncology, Princess Margaret Hospital and University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada 5 Program in Cancer Genetics, Department of Oncology and Human Genetics, McGill University, Montr&#233;al, QC, Canada 6 BC Cancer Agency, Vancouver, BC, Canada 7 Toronto Sunnybrook Regional Cancer Centre, Toronto, ON, Canada 8 London Health Sciences Centre, The University of Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada 9 Hospital Notre Dame, Montr&#233;al, QC, Canada  10 Departments of Medicine and Medical Genetics, University of Alberta, Edmonton, AB, Canada  11 Children&#8217;s Hospital, The University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, MB, Canada 12 Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics, University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon, SK, Canada </p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>Abstract:</p>
      <p>Background: Women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation have several options available for cancer prevention, including prophylactic surgery, chemoprevention, and screening.  In this study, we report on actual preventive practices in women with and without breast cancer, and we examine differences according to geographic area within Canada and ethnicity.  </p>
      <p>Methods:  Canadian women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation were followed after genetic testing and questioned regarding preventive practices.  Women reported on uptake of prophylactic mastectomy, prophylactic oophorectomy, tamoxifen/raloxifene usage, and screening practices.  Analyses of uptake were done for all of the options.  A sub-analysis was done according to geographic area within Canada where genetic testing was provided.  </p>
      <p>Results: 675 women were included in the study. Follow-up questionnaires were completed after a mean of 4.0 years (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID80b62808-006a-4d66-ad8b-4f6775a5b48f">range 1.6 &#8211; 8.9 years</xref>). Of the 344 women without breast cancer, 72 (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID41e585d8-7ddf-48a1-9b02-ee2c671c0438">21%</xref>) had a prophylactic bilateral mastectomy. 365 women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID570766dd-c864-4a23-81b1-60f6a9fe5ff4">54%</xref>) had a bilateral prophylactic oophorectomy. Seventeen women (6%) took tamoxifen and twelve women (4%) reported taking raloxifene. For the women without breast cancer, 46% of the women had not undertaken any cancer prevention option (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDbf1f207d-c3aa-4774-a7c3-e65beb51a1d5">mastectomy, oophorectomy, or tamoxifen/raloxifene</xref>). Thirty-nine percent of women from Ontario and 34% of women from Western Canada had not elected for any preventive option. Sixty-two percent of women from Quebec had not undertaken any preventive procedure. Conclusion: Significant differences in uptake of preventive options by women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation were observed within Canada.  Future research should be help to explain why these differences exist. </p>
      <p>Introduction</p>
      <p>Women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation have a lifetime risk of developing breast cancer between <xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID8358345d-06bc-4f75-842f-09a92fdb59ef">4</xref>
            <xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID9b903717-cc03-48f9-ad90-02bd49767f4c">5</xref>% and 87% (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID49f8d4d8-be0b-422b-8f25-6048c3786a51">1, 2</xref>)).  By identifying women at high-risk of developing cancer and adopting appropriate intervention strategies, it is anticipated that cases of cancer will be prevented.  Ultimately, the value of genetic testing for BRCA1 and BRCA2 depends on the uptake of effective cancer prevention options.  There are several preventive options available, with varying levels of effectiveness.  Prophylactic mastectomy offers the greatest reduction in breast cancer risk (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDd17696e7-a1f8-4222-8cc7-00c55b311891">approximately 95%</xref>) (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb2199928-a03c-41e3-9b23-33ee921363e7">3</xref>) .  Prophylactic oophorectomy prior to the age of <xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID766cc89e-dac4-42e5-bc24-6857a48e23eb">4</xref>0 in women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation is associated with a <xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa14c313d-401f-424e-b959-e465b644e390">5</xref>0% risk reduction of breast cancer (4).  Tamoxifen has been shown to reduce breast cancer risk by 50% in women at high-risk of developing breast cancer (5).  The evidence in favor of tamoxifen for primary prevention in BRCA1/2 carriers is based on the prevention of contralateral breast cancer (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDe9630966-fbf2-401b-965c-aa5fcd54a3f0">6</xref>).  </p>
      <p>	Previous research that has examined uptake rates of various preventive options among BRCA1 and BRCA2 carriers is limited.  However there are suggestions that the uptake of preventive procedures differs significantly according to country (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb5c4864d-4559-4dde-843d-8de1326de750">7-11</xref>).   Differences in uptake rates are likely due to many factors, including patient preferences, physician preferences, and access to care.  In this study, we present data on a Canadian cohort of BRCA1 and BRCA2 carriers who were followed systematically from the time of genetic testing.  We report on preventive practices in women with and without breast cancer, and examine differences in uptake rates according to geographic area within Canada and/or ethnicity of the population studied.  </p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Study Population</title>
        <p>Eligible subjects were drawn from a database of carriers of deleterious mutations in either the BRCA1 or the BRCA2 gene. These women have been assessed for genetic risk at twelve centers across Canada and were found to carry a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation. All study subjects provided written informed consent for genetic testing. The study has been approved by the ethics committees of all participating centres. In most cases, testing was offered initially to women who were affected either by breast or ovarian cancer. When a mutation in either the BRCA1 or BRCA2 gene was found in a proband or in her relative, testing was offered to other at-risk women in her family. However, in some cases (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID96d0a998-1aa3-4ac2-9c2e-0db1738df541">fewer than 10% of total</xref>) an affected woman in the family was not available for study and an unaffected woman was the first member of the family to be tested. Mutation detection was performed using a range of techniques, but in all nucleotide sequences were confirmed with direct sequencing of genomic DNA. A woman was eligible for the study when the molecular analysis established that she was a mutation carrier. We studied both unaffected and affected women with breast cancer.</p>
        <p>Subjects were eligible for this study if they were a resident of Canada and received genetic testing at a Canadian genetics center, were known to be a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation carrier, were between 25 and 80 years old, and had no previous history of cancer, other than breast cancer. Subjects who were diagnosed with breast cancer during the follow-up period were excluded. Subjects had at least 18 months of follow-up after genetic testing and were alive at the date of follow-up.</p>
        <p>Women were grouped according to geographic area.  Women who received genetic testing at the BC Cancer Agency (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID3505459a-aaf9-4221-9bb4-85f41db1b331">Vancouver</xref>) (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDbb3a12a8-ce2f-49ec-8c4e-870ab1a89c67">n=67</xref>), in Edmonton (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID60493d35-c878-43e5-8143-8013c4e2c231">n=20</xref>), in Saskatoon (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID9cc6af40-4d45-406b-bf03-ecd69804d0e2">n=8</xref>), and in Winnipeg (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDf1ac05fa-7d44-4e9b-8cbd-ff4ebd9ab5fa">n=15</xref>) were classified as from Western Canada.  Women from Ontario received genetic testing and counseling either at Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID5a756e52-3e6b-427f-bb51-d2db473b60d8">n=40</xref>), Women&#8217;s College Hospital (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDc3712b98-0d3a-43a5-af1e-06c2a206c85d">Toronto</xref>) (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID4cf6dc69-56d6-443d-8436-0bbfc06c0b47">n=139</xref>), the Toronto General Hospital (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID23d4c247-2988-4c65-aee9-f68a7901e397">n=50</xref>), the London Regional Cancer Centre (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID598601ed-8ee8-46e5-bfa4-ed4813ff88c3">n=56</xref>), or the Hamilton Regional Cancer Centre (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDfe6e5244-ddaf-47bf-b265-525d30c76ec6">n=30</xref>).  Women from Quebec received genetic testing and counseling at Hotel-Dieu Hospital (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID10395271-7dd6-4d97-95e8-ee5fb8b3d107">Montreal</xref>) (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID85fcafe4-bf6a-4fe7-a4fd-762aead3c2e5">n=165</xref>), or the <xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDcacade43-07c0-444b-8a93-27e2fe5d1490">Montreal</xref> General Hospital (Montreal) (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDf0f8a97a-da99-4582-8076-2fe6e3689ec5">n=82</xref>).  Three women from Halifax were included in the overall analysis, but were not included in the geographic sub-analysis (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa6ca835a-06cd-4526-8e6b-d27004aed9aa">due to the small number</xref>).  Subjects were divided by ethnicity into Jewish, French Canadian, and other.  </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <p>All subjects completed a baseline questionnaire at the time of genetic testing, which assessed cancer history, and past use of cancer prevention options and screening tests.  Follow-up questionnaires were administered by telephone or by mail.  Questions assessed uptake of cancer preventive options, including prophylactic surgery (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDf2649f2b-b062-4ed3-81ee-f16b67c0eb12">mastectomy or oophorectomy</xref>), chemoprevention (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDd490718d-4b72-4ea8-af53-616942bf2c4f">tamoxifen/raloxifene</xref>), and/or breast MRI.  </p>
        <p>
          <underline>Statistical Analysis</underline>
        </p>
        <p>Chi-square test was used to compare frequencies of categorical variables, such as different preventive options among regions, and ANOVA was used to compare the mean values of continuous variables among different regions. All Statistical tests were done by statistical software SAS version 9.1.3, SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, NC, USA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Results</title>
        <p>1054 women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation were identified for this study. Of these, 328 women were ineligible (12 women were less than 25 years, 10 women were greater than 80 years, 105 women were deceased at follow-up, 111 women had ovarian cancer, 15 women were followed for less than 18 months, 52 women were diagnosed with breast cancer during the follow-up period, and 23 women resided outside of Canada); 29 women refused to complete the follow-up questionnaire; and 22 women were lost to follow-up. 675 women were included in the study. Follow-up questionnaires were completed a mean of 4.0 years after genetic testing (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID268d1411-08e7-444e-a492-948cfdb533f8">range 1.6 &#8211; 8.9 years</xref>). 110 women received genetic testing and counseling in Western Canada (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDe482387e-8f49-4043-bd5a-0588553d2773">from four centres</xref>), 315 women in Ontario (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID8d3bf403-ed88-48b7-9df6-e1e94f6c65fb">from five centres</xref>), 247 women in Quebec (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID4c9de2fd-750e-4445-b4e8-904ddee87116">from two centres</xref>) and three from Halifax. 331 women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa2eec1d4-f366-4a3a-96a9-c335ed824670">49%</xref>) had a previous diagnosis of breast cancer and 334 (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID187960cd-c89c-46fe-9709-f71e2ed06067">51%</xref>) women had no previous breast cancer. Characteristics of the subjects are presented in <xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb37aac37-5dc4-4390-be30-1630c823c7dd">Table 1</xref>. The mean age of the subjects at time of genetic testing was 47 years (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDeca38c84-dd49-46ec-8d26-abfd6f0483e2">range 25 to 79 years</xref>) and the mean age at follow-up was 51 years (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID85a8176e-9952-44f8-b0a3-bc7a9c6605f5">range 28-82 years</xref>). There were no statistical differences in mean ages at time of genetic testing according to geographic area (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID73676571-e2f8-4e5e-9a67-1103997dbc9d">p=0.39</xref>), but there were differences in ethnicity (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID35895514-8f6a-46c1-9b22-40053240161f">p&lt;10-4</xref>) (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDebf245d6-8ae9-4b22-b1c3-e15f0a919ddf">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Prophylactic Mastectomy</title>
        <p>Of the 344 women without breast cancer, 72 (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID0dee586c-9518-4175-bfb6-052e4791cea3">21%</xref>) had a prophylactic bilateral mastectomy (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDaa8f95e8-1b41-42f5-bcf2-571e8000eaac">Table 2</xref>).  The majority of these women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDe2666279-3ef2-458a-9e08-9a134de58ddf">74%</xref>) had their surgery after receiving their genetic test result.  The other nineteen women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDe8785574-e3ed-4e04-bb39-4f32a844ec8b">26%</xref>) had prophylactic mastectomy prior to genetic testing, based on their family history alone.  All 72 prophylactic mastectomies were performed before the age of 60 (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDc5e5ed1d-fabb-44f5-96cb-418644a877d8">range 26-58</xref>).  Women from western Canada had the highest rate of prophylactic mastectomy (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID57b658df-a6d8-4236-9ed4-d912ebaae264">46%</xref>) compared to 22% of women from Ontario, and 8.4% of women from Quebec (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDc2fa2841-1863-4c4a-97a5-bf1ae5fba9b3">Table 5</xref>).  Across Canada, 8.7% of French Canadians had prophylactic mastectomy compared to 24.6% of Ashkenazi Jewish women and 26.9% of women of other ethnicities (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID9751e98a-4802-40f1-9f3b-1de576ca9bb8">Table 7</xref>). </p>
        <sec>
          <title>Prophylactic Oophorectomy</title>
          <p>365 women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID639538c0-991e-47a5-a555-a4bff6877e62">54%</xref>) had a bilateral prophylactic oophorectomy.  217 of these women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb1554b20-6135-423a-9c80-0b3e4b670088">59%</xref>) had the surgery after receiving genetic test result (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID6be1d6e0-9523-4a8e-b861-d29effd7ba40">Table 3</xref>).  We were not able to distinguish between oophorectomies that were done for cancer prophylaxis or for other reasons.  More women with a history of breast cancer had a prophylactic oophorectomy (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID124a786e-b4e2-4177-82cd-754584658d9d">60%</xref>) than women without breast cancer (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID617277d4-0029-4d83-9f14-6a58695236d9">48%</xref>)(<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID5166acbf-b341-4f19-88b0-b2ae1c79c491">p=0.002</xref>).  Women from western Canada were the most likely to have prophylactic oophorectomy (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID8056989b-7a2f-451d-90a5-1449c0192f82">67%</xref>) followed by women from Ontario (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID31815602-5944-4116-aad9-129394aa9d2e">61%</xref>) (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID219a0dd8-0da1-420f-a5c2-12fc651164fa">Table 5</xref>).  Women from Quebec were the least likely to have prophylactic oophorectomy (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDb13106fa-2942-4728-8304-697ff699c237">39%</xref>).  Across Canada, 34% of French Canadians had prophylactic oophorectomy compared to 66% of Ashkenazi Jewish women and 63% of women of other ethnicities (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID62f582e6-e2ec-4d96-9a4b-760dac37c61c">Table 7</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Tamoxifen/Raloxifene</title>
        <p>Tamoxifen and raloxifene usage was examined for women without breast cancer but with both breasts intact (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID4e59f188-87fc-4205-9b74-0c2d6e7f1f5b">ie. no prophylactic mastectomy</xref>). Seventeen women (6%) took tamoxifen and twelve women (4%) reported having taken raloxifene (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa70a3b23-5de6-4cb2-9cf0-143d5f2eb7fc">Table 4</xref>). Women from Ontario were the most likely to take one of the two chemopreventive drugs (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID68dd795f-d992-42ab-85ac-0b0cd3c53a47">16%</xref>). Four percent of women from Quebec and 13% of women from Western Canada took one of the two drugs (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID1c3be1d8-91e3-4a3f-aa1f-8286a26e2347">Table 5</xref>). Across Canada, 3.2% of French Canadians took tamoxifen or raloxifene, compared to 16.3% of Ashkenazi Jewish women and 14.1% of women of other ethnicities (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID275f981a-8df1-4846-bb58-4d643b630b0f">Table 7</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>No Preventive Option</title>
        <p>	For the women without breast cancer, 46% of the women had chosen no cancer prevention option (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDc2753ac7-b9b0-473d-a0a3-eafd10bf17df">mastectomy, oophorectomy, or tamoxifen/raloxifene</xref>). Thirty-nine percent of women from Ontario and 34% of women from Western Canada had not elected for any preventive option. Sixty-two percent of women from Quebec had not undertaken any preventive procedure.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>MRI and Mammography</title>
        <p>	Of the 272 women without breast cancer and without prophylactic bilateral mastectomy, data were available on 241 women regarding MRI usage. One hundred and four women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDda50a429-2314-41f0-a760-133c8030de20">43%</xref>) had had an MRI for screening for breast cancer. The majority of these women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID92abe4e0-abde-4066-a131-60c7f9b8248e">96%</xref>) were below the age of 60. There were differences in uptake according to geographic region; 62% of women from Ontario (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID6f5c4e90-45ee-41be-aa93-18800cc6ee56">81 of 131 women</xref>) had had an MRI, compared to 14% of women from Quebec (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="IDa2d393e9-56e7-4109-8c06-fabcefd5c423">15 of 109 women</xref>) and 27% of women from Western Canada (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID89cc04a0-fb90-442d-bbbb-c302b06ec783">8 of 30 women</xref>) (<xref rid="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f" ref-type="bibr" id="ID9e191fcb-75d6-4cb4-b3d5-802cc99137f9">Table 5</xref>). Within Quebec, there was a significant difference in uptake of MRI by ethnicity. In Quebec, French Canadian women were less likely to have had an MRI compared to women of other ethnicities (<xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="IDf3a9ee24-0cf3-4c87-94df-1ca340e879e6">5.4% vs. 50.0%</xref>; <xref rid="TO_LINK" ref-type="bibr" id="ID226c6e10-31ec-4d12-99d5-27f0918361de">p &lt;10-4</xref>).</p>
        <p>	In contrast, the majority of women without breast cancer had mammography (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID5f2efd9a-9808-43aa-b1e8-c49d35ce53e1">96%</xref>). Most of these women (<xref rid="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d" ref-type="bibr" id="ID96bd808b-187d-4f64-b57a-883b572b8d65">86%</xref>) began mammography screening prior to genetic testing, however, 14% of the women had their first mammogram after receiving the genetic test result. Uptake rates were similar according to geographic area. 99% of women from Ontario, 93% of women from western Canada, and 93% of women from Quebec reported undergoing mammography.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ID01d5458a-1d4f-4c6b-93ad-fefdfc99c63d">
        <mixed-citation>	This is the first study to report on the rates of uptake of various cancer preventive options among Canadian women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation.  Overall, the uptake rates of various preventive modalities were similar to those reported in other countries, however, there were dramatic differences across the country.  Approximately two-thirds of women from Quebec had elected no preventive option, compared to approximately one-third of women from Western Canada and Ontario.  The greatest differences in uptake rates were observed with prophylactic mastectomy. Women from Western Canada had the highest uptake of prophylactic mastectomy (46%), followed by women from Ontario (22%), and Quebec (8%). These rates are comparable to those that have previously been reported(8) (9) (11) (12).  Uptake of prophylactic mastectomy has ranged from 3% in the United States to 54% (11) in the Netherlands (9).  We expect to see these numbers rise in with the increasing acceptance of subcutaneous mastectomy for prophylaxis (13).We also observed pronounced differences in rates of uptake of prophylactic oophorectomy. Sixty-seven percent of women from Western Canada and 61% of women from Ontario had preventive oophorectomy. Again, fewer women from Quebec elected to have this preventive surgery (39%). Previous international research has also suggested that there are differences in uptake of prophylactic oophorectomy(8, 11, 14).  Uptake of prophylactic oophorectomy in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers has ranged from 13% in the United States (11) to 64% in the Netherlands (14).   The effectiveness of tamoxifen for primary prevention of breast cancer in BRCA1 carriers is not yet proven.  However, tamoxifen has been shown to reduce the risk of contralateral breast cancer by 50% (6, 15).  We previously surveyed women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation regarding tamoxifen usage (16).  Only 12% of this sample had taken tamoxifen for breast cancer prevention, with the main reason for not taking the drug being fear of side-effects.  Patient reluctance to take tamoxifen has also been documented in three major trials of tamoxifen as a chemopreventive agent (these women were on average at a much lower risk of developing breast caner than <italic>BRCA </italic>carriers). Each of these trials demonstrated a significant rate of attrition (5, 17, 18), which was, in part, attributable to patient reluctance to take tamoxifen.  After the release of the NSABP1 Trial results (5) which demonstrated a significant breast cancer risk reduction associated with tamoxifen, high-risk women were offered tamoxifen for breast cancer prevention on a clinical basis.  Port et al. described that there was still a reluctance to take tamoxifen for breast cancer prevention, despite the proven effectiveness of the drug (19). Recent data from the STAR trial also suggests that raloxifene is effective in preventing breast cancer in high-risk post-menopausal women and is associated with fewer side-effects. These new findings may lead to an increase in the uptake of chemoprevention in BRCA1 and BRCA2 carriersThe superiority of MRI over mammography in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers in detecting small breast cancers is becoming evident (20-22). For many women, screening is more acceptable than either preventive surgery or chemoprevention. We anticipated that if women were not having prophylactic mastectomy that the rates of MRI usage would be high. In Ontario this was the case, with 72% of women without prophylactic mastectomy having MRI for screening. This rate was lower in Western Canada (27%), and in Quebec (16%). The women in Quebec had the lowest uptake of all of the preventive options, and also had the lowest uptake of MRI screening. Our results, and those of others, suggest that there are wide variations in uptake of preventive options in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers.  It is not clear why, but differences may be due to various factors, including; 1) cultural differences influencing patient preferences; 2) health care professionals&#8217; acceptance and recommendation of the procedures; and/or 3) access (including cost and availability).  This question will be the subject of future research.  </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="IDc7f4387b-e8ba-46fd-a142-22eb2763e10f">
        <mixed-citation>Our study subjects were women who have been found to carry a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation at one of 12 specialized genetic counseling centers across Canada between 1995 and 2003. Although ours is a relatively large sample (675 women), it may not be representative of all women who have received a positive genetic test result in Canada. Canadian women may have undergone genetic testing in centers other than the ones included here and we do not have any information on their cancer prevention. Furthermore, the patients were tested on average, seven years ago, and patterns of practice have evolved since 1999. We believe that genetic services are now better integrated with surgical care and that physician attitudes may have changed with regards to specific preventive measures. It is our intention to repeat this survey in five years time in order to evaluate trends in clinical practice.Health care professionals&#8217; acceptance and recommendations clearly influence uptake.  There is evidence that physicians have differing opinions on the various preventive options available to women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation.  In Maryland, USA, surgeons were surveyed about prophylactic mastectomy.  A greater proportion of plastic surgeons (84.6%) than general surgeons (47.0%) or gynecologists (38.3%) agreed that bilateral prophylactic mastectomy has a role in the care of high-risk women (23).   In France, only 11% of French physicians found it acceptable to propose prophylactic mastectomy to women with a <italic>BRCA</italic> mutation (24).  Peshkin et al. (25) surveyed physicians regarding recommendations for tamoxifen for primary breast cancer prevention.  The physicians were more likely to recommend tamoxifen to BRCA2 carriers (73%) than to BRCA1 carriers (57%) (p&lt;0.0001).  The authors concluded that physicians were not convinced of the benefits of tamoxifen in BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers.  Although this research did not examine the uptake of the preventive options by women based on their physicians preference, it is expected that the physicians would influence patient choices.   Other authors have examined the differences in uptake of preventive options in various countries (26).  Women from Canada (Quebec), France and Great Britain were surveyed about their medical decisions related to BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation testing.  Bouchard et al. found differences in the uptake of preventive procedures in three countries.  They attributed these to cultural differences and to differences in the information that was provided during the counseling session.  Differences in provider information may explain the differences that we observed across Canada.  When we compared uptake of preventive options among French Canadians in different centres, we observed that uptake was associated more with centre where genetic testing was provided, and not on French ethnicity alone (Table 6).  Access to services may also contribute to the observed differences.  This is a likely contributor for the difference in uptake of MRI across Canada.  To date, screening MRI is offered on a research basis, and is not widely available as a clinical service.  Women with access to the research studies are more likely to have MRI for screening.  The differences in tamoxifen uptake may also be due to access issues, including cost.  Currently, tamoxifen costs approximately twenty-five dollars per month. Some women may not have drug coverage and therefore may not be able to afford this drug.  The differences in surgical uptake are probably not due to differences in access issues across the country.  Canadian women have coverage for prophylactic surgeries, including breast reconstruction, without cost.  This would not be the case in the United States, and differences in uptake of preventive procedures have been attributed to financial constraints.  Schwartz et al (27) attributed the low rate of prophylactic oophorectomy to constrained financial resources of the women in the study.  This research study is the first to describe the significant differences in uptake of preventive options by women with a BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation who have received genetic testing in different areas of one country.  The differences cannot be explained by differing health care systems because all of the women in this study have similar access to health care (with the exception of MRI) and therefore no woman would be denied any of the preventive procedures because of lack of health insurance (Canada has universal health care).  We have speculated that the differences exist because of various reasons, including 1) cultural differences across Canada; 2) health care professionals&#8217; acceptance and recommendation of the procedures; and/or 3) access (including cost and availability).  In this study we could not ascertain the specific reason for the discrepancies across Canada, but future research will address this important question.  <!--meTypeset:br-->Table 1. Subject Characteristics by Geographic Regiona ANOVA for differences in mean values between the three regions; chi-square test for the differences in frequency distributions of the three regions Table 2. Prophylactic Mastectomy For Women Without Breast CancerTable 3. Prophylactic Oophorectomy by Breast Cancer StatusTable 4. Tamoxifen and RaloxifeneTable 5. Preventive Option by Geographic Area1: For subjects without breast cancer;2: For all subjects in the 3 regions; 3: For subjects with no prophylactic mastectomy and no breast cancer ;*: missing data not included in the test;  Table 6. Preventive Option by ethnicity1: For subjects without breast cancer;2: For all subjects;3: For subjects with no prophylactic mastectomy and no breast cancer;*: Missing data not included in the test;Table 7. Preventive Option by ethnicity1: For subjects without breast cancer;2: For all subjects;3: For subjects with no prophylactic mastectomy and no breast cancer;*: Missing data not included in the test;References:</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
