<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20101291</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2801911</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-01-e49-51</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Peer review in open access scientific journals</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>Matthew E</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>MSc</degrees><degrees>DSc</degrees><bio><p>Matthew E. Falagas, MD, MSc, DSc, is Director of the Alfa Institute of Biomedical Sciences (AIBS), Athens, Greece, and Adjunct Associate Professor, Department of Medicine, Tufts University School of Medicine, Boston, Mass.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Matthew E. Falagas, MD, MSc, DSc, Alfa Institute of Biomedical Sciences (AIBS), http://www.e-meducation.org, 9 Neapoleos Street, 151 23 Marousi, Greece, <email>m.falagas@aibs.gr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e49</fpage><lpage>e51</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/index.php/om/article/view/35"/></article-meta></front><body><p>The introduction of open access scientific journals has revolutionized scientific publishing. Open access to medical publications has the potential to boost the timely and widespread dissemination of new research findings and, ultimately, to have a more immediate impact on clinical practice than traditional publishing methods. However, several aspects of open access publishing remain to be discussed and clarified by the scientific community; among these is the value and process of open peer review.</p><p>The value of peer review to editors and authors is well established in the traditional biomedical publication model. Most authors and editors would agree that a fair and thoughtful manuscript review by experts with considerable knowledge in a given research area is helpful to editors in judging the importance of the research question studied and the appropriateness of the methodology used. Moreover, experienced peer reviewers usually make instructive comments as to whether the authors&#x02019; conclusions are supported by their data and whether their findings have been put in the wider context of what is already known about their research question.</p><p>However, editors of several influential biomedical journals have expressed concern regarding various aspects of the peer review of submitted manuscripts, including whether generally accepted review processes are adequate to ensure appropriate and fair evaluation, and have called for more quantitative and qualitative studies on the issue.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Editors sometimes make decisions about submitted manuscripts irrespective of the peer reviewers&#x02019; comments; this occurs for a variety of reasons, including the fact that some peer reviews are not particularly helpful.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> Nevertheless, traditional peer review has been considered an indispensable part of the editorial evaluation process &#x02014;until such time as a more effective and fair system is developed and successfully applied in scientific publishing.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></p><p>Although the value of a strong peer review process is felt to extend to the open access publication model,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> at least one study has raised the concern that some new open access journals may have a less rigorous manuscript evaluation process than traditional subscription journals.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> If this is so, it may reflect an expectation that post-publication review through open, published discourse will be swift and effective. However, while all manner of electronic journals are experimenting with reader input on published material, little is known about the scientific value of post-publication review in the modern era of open access publishing. Several questions arise. Can new capacities for open comment really assume the responsibilities, thoroughness and overall judgement of formal peer review? Are they being set up and structured in this way? It is noteworthy that the multidisciplinary journal <italic>Nature</italic> closed its recent open peer review experiment, although it should be noted that this &#x0201c;open&#x0201d; movement has differences regarding type of publisher as well access to the data and peer review process compared to that of other publishers such as the Public Library of Science (PLoS) for instance.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></p><p>In second-generation open access journals such as <italic>PLoS ONE</italic> there is a more intense emphasis on open post-publication review (after an initial technical review of the paper&#x02019;s scientific quality) as a means of enabling early publication. This approach makes a greater proportion of submissions available to readers to assess for themselves. Discourse can begin immediately regarding the methodological aspects of a study and the significance and implications of its findings, as compared with traditional journals, where reaction to an article usually takes the form of letters to the editor published at a later date. It should be mentioned that in some first-generation open access journals there has been the opportunity to quickly react to a publication using the &#x0201c;rapid response&#x0201d; electronic system.</p><p>In-depth peer review is essential to open access journals no less than to traditional subscription journals both to ensure that the submitted work is within the journal&#x02019;s scope but also to carefully critique the work before publication. We should not forget that published biomedical information influences clinical practice and thus affects the health of patients. An analogy may be found in the potential dangers for patients if physicians were to make clinical decisions based on results reported in conference abstracts,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> given that major differences often exist between data presented in abstracts and subsequent corresponding full text articles published after peer review, revision and editing.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> The scientific community should have an unconditional, clear and strong interest in preventing false or over-interpreted scientific information from being disseminated, and this commitment requires a rigorous peer review process.</p><p>Open access publications should be at the forefront in experimenting with strategies to foster what might be called an increasingly <italic>open science</italic>. As the open access movement blossoms, its supporters should continue to critically evaluate the parallel development of openness and transparency in the peer review process. We need to ensure that a commitment to high-quality peer review is maintained. At the same time, it has become clear that some aspects of conventional review processes are ineffective. For example, masking the identity of authors to peer reviewers (blind evaluation) was hypothesized as a way of avoiding conflicts of interest on the part of reviewers, but it has been shown that blinding cannot be always be maintained in either journal manuscripts or conference abstracts.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Open access journals are in an ideal position to test the merits of open, unblinded, peer review.</p><p>Other aspect of openness in peer review also merit exploration. Most manuscripts are rejected on at least their initial submission for publication (especially at the leading biomedical journals). A considerable proportion of these manuscripts are submitted for publication in other journals, usually with lower rejection rates. Of 350 manuscripts rejected by the <italic>Annals of Internal Medicine</italic> during 1993 and 1994, 69% were subsequently published in other journals with an average time from rejection of the initial submission to its publication in another journal of 18 months.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Similar findings are evidenced by law review journals, which permit and encourage multiple submissions and have shorter manuscript handling times than economics, finance, mathematics and psychology journals, which do not allow multiple submissions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Such publication delays have led to suggestions that simultaneous submission of an article to two or more journals might reduce the time from initial submission to publication.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> In addition to reducing delays caused by the requirement for sequential submission, simultaneous submissions may increase healthy competition between journals to reduce their editorial response time.</p><p>A natural extension of this &#x0201c;open&#x0201d; submission process would be to make peer reviews of rejected manuscripts available for consideration during subsequent submissions to other journals.  Although this practice is recommended by some journals in their instructions to authors, authors rarely adhere to it &#x02014; for obvious reasons. However, this practice would expedite editorial decisions; for example, it would show whether the authors had addressed previous critiques and thus inform a decision as to whether their work warrants further external peer review. Authors might be more motivated under this system to improve a manuscript after its rejection by paying attention to the suggestions of peer reviewers before submission to another journal, and editors would be able to see where significant improvements to the manuscript have been made.</p><p>In conclusion, we know that the peer review process is not without flaws. The birth of the open access publication model and the rise of a more open science presents an ideal opportunity to re-evaluate the transparency of editorial and peer review practices. I believe that when, and if, the scientific community fully adopts policies leading to open access to journal content and the open peer evaluation of manuscripts (e.g., by signing peer reviews and publishing reviews online), the level of transparency and quality in scientific publishing of research data will be further boosted. This will substantially contribute to the advancement of science and to the international community that scientists serve.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderson</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name><name><surname>Wager</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of editorial peer review: a systematic review</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2002</year><month>6</month><day>5</day><volume>287</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>2784</fpage><lpage>2786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.287.21.2784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12038911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hidden research paper</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2002</year><month>6</month><day>5</day><volume>287</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>2775</fpage><lpage>2778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.287.21.2775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12038909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>Drummond</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fourth International Congress on Peer Review in Biomedical Publication</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2002</year><month>6</month><day>5</day><volume>287</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>2759</fpage><lpage>2760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.287.21.2759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12038904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in manuscripts and quality: The contribution of peer review [abstract]</article-title><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Jan 7</date-in-citation><conf-name>Fourth International Congress On Peer Review In Biomedical Publication</conf-name><conf-date>2001 Sept 14&#x02013;16</conf-date><conf-loc>Barcelona</conf-loc><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ama-assn.org/public/peer/prc_program2001.htm#purcell">http://www.ama-assn.org/public/peer/prc_program2001.htm#purcell</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>Georgii A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The purpose of peer review in the case of an open-access publication</article-title><source>Carbon Balance Manag</source><year>2006</year><month>9</month><day>15</day><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Jan 7</date-in-citation><volume>1</volume><fpage>10</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbmjournal.com/content/1/1/10">http://www.cbmjournal.com/content/1/1/10</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-0680-1-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="authors">Kaufman-Wills Group</collab><source>The facts about open access: a study of the financial and non-financial effects of alternative business models for scholarly journals</source><year>2005</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Jan 7</date-in-citation><volume>1</volume><publisher-loc>Worthing, West Sussex (UK)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of Learned and Professional Society Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>10</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alpsp.org/publications/FAOAcompleteREV.pdf">http://www.alpsp.org/publications/FAOAcompleteREV.pdf</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-0680-1-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Nature&#x02019;s peer review trial [online editorial]</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><month>12</month><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Jan 7</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/nature/peerreview/debate/nature05535.html">http://www.nature.com/nature/peerreview/debate/nature05535.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>Matthew E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosmarakis</surname><given-names>Evangelos S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical decision-making based on findings presented in conference abstracts: is it safe for our patients?</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2006</year><month>9</month><volume>27</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2038</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehl175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16864607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosmarakis</surname><given-names>Evangelos S</given-names></name><name><surname>Soteriades</surname><given-names>Elpidoforos S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergidis</surname><given-names>Paschalis I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasiakou</surname><given-names>Sofia K</given-names></name><name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>Matthew E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From conference abstract to full paper: differences between data presented in conferences and journals</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2005</year><month>5</month><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.04-3140lfe</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15857882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>Matthew E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zouglakis</surname><given-names>George M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavvadia</surname><given-names>Panorea K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How masked is the "masked peer review" of abstracts submitted to international medical conferences?</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>2006</year><month>5</month><volume>81</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16706269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yankauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How blind is blind review?</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>1991</year><month>7</month><volume>81</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><comment>Erratum in: Am J Public Health 1991;81(12):1570.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2053657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkwits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fate of manuscripts rejected by a general medical journal</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2000</year><month>8</month><day>1</day><volume>109</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9343(00)00450-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>David J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>Joy</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockayne</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumville</surname><given-names>Jo</given-names></name><name><surname>Petherick</surname><given-names>Emily</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Submission to multiple journals: a method of reducing time to publication?</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2005</year><month>2</month><day>5</day><volume>330</volume><issue>7486</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.330.7486.305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15695280</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>