<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22046226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3205827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-05-e134</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Frank words about breast screening</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>Cornelia J</given-names></name><bio><p>
              <bold>Cornelia J. Baines</bold>, MD, MSc, Fellow of the American College of Epidemiology, is Professor Emerita at the Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON Canada.
            </p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: <email>cornelia.baines@utoronto.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e134</fpage><lpage>e136</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/461/416">http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/461/416</self-uri><abstract><sec><title/><p>A growing body of evidence suggests that the benefits achieved by screening for breast cancer are small, that the harm from the over-diagnosis of breast cancer arising from screening is substantial, and that, where screening is available, the observed reductions in breast cancer mortality arise largely from increased awareness and improved chemo- and hormone therapyIt is reasonable for women to choose to be screened, but only if they are completely informed about the probability of benefit versus the probability of harm. For 2000 women aged 40&#x02013;49 who undergo screening for 10 years, the benefit is much smaller in terms of avoiding death from breast cancer than is the harm arising from over-diagnosis and unnecessary treatment for breast cancer, to say nothing of the increased rates of mastectomy associated with screening.These issues are not widely known to the general public.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>A growing body of evidence suggests that the benefits achieved by screening for breast cancer are small, that the harm from the over-diagnosis of breast cancer arising from screening is substantial, and that, where screening is available, the observed reductions in breast cancer mortality arise largely from increased awareness and improved chemo- and hormone therapy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> In spite of these new insights, screening advocacy continues in full crescendo. For example, in 2010 the Canadian Breast Cancer Foundation Ontario (CBCFO) released a report on its recent consensus conference, &#x0201c;It&#x02019;s About Time,&#x0201d; focusing on the earlier detection and diagnosis of breast cancer. The CBCFO is a not-for-profit organization; its conference scientific advisory committee consisted of five members, of whom three are active in breast imaging and a fourth is the director of cancer screening at the American Cancer Society. The breast cancer screening recommendations for women at average risk that emerged from the conference are that screening should be done within an organized program and should begin at &#x0201c;approximately&#x0201d; age 40. (&#x0201c;Approximately&#x0201d; may leave wiggle room for women in their 30s to participate.) The &#x0201c;preferred&#x0201d; modality described is annual digital mammography, and if it is not available, film mammography is the alternative.</p><p>The CBCFO&#x02019;s campaign for women in their 40s to be included in the Ontario Breast Screening Program is less than convincing given the current evidence. Furthermore, vested interests from the imaging industry are a major factor associated with screening advocacy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Despite the lack of compelling evidence, the recently released 2011 budget for the Government of Ontario has earmarked $10 million to screen high-risk women aged 30&#x02013;49 for breast cancer. Such an initiative is compatible with the generally held <italic>belief</italic> that the earlier detection achieved by screening makes cure more likely. It is not compatible with current evidence.</p><p>Commitment and funding for breast screening for women aged 40&#x02013;49 without compelling evidence of benefit is not unique to Canada. An uproar among screening advocates was unleashed in November 2009 with the publication of the United States Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) Guidelines for Breast Screening.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> The task force concluded that 1904 women aged 39 to 49 needed to be invited for annual screening for 10 years to prevent one breast cancer death (leaving 1903 women at substantial risk of over-diagnosis). Corresponding figures for women aged 50&#x02013;59 and 60&#x02013;69 were 1339 and 377 respectively. The guidelines are outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="textbox1">Textbox 1</xref>. The USPSTF also recognized over-diagnosis as one of the harms of screening.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>The recommendations &#x0201c;were widely and loudly denounced by radiologists, breast cancer survivors, media doctors, gynecologists and politicians. Medical experts called the task force &#x02018;idiots&#x02019; and conservatives lined up to denounce the report as an Obama administration plot.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> The American College of Radiology (ACR) declared that &#x0201c;two decades of decline in breast cancer mortality could be reversed and countless American women may die needlessly from breast cancer each year&#x0201d; and that the recommendations were &#x0201c;flawed,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;shocking&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;unconscionable.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> These protestations conveniently ignored evidence from Italy, Denmark, Norway and the World Health Organization that, primarily as a result of increased breast cancer awareness and improved therapy, breast cancer mortality has in fact declined in the absence of screening in screening-eligible women and also in women too young to be screened.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>It is of interest that the ACR received donations of at least $1 million each from GE Healthcare and Siemens AG, both companies that make mammography equipment and MRI scanners. The lobbyists leading the charge against the USPSTF 2009 guidelines in Washington included GE, Siemens and the ACR.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> A US radiologist and screening advocate not only assailed the 2009 USPSTF Guidelines but also wrote that those disagreeing with him were wrong: &#x0201c;They distort data, rely on weak science, but refuse to defend when challenged.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> The claim was also made that &#x0201c;Many European countries as well as Canada do not support, or at any rate do not encourage, screening before the age of 50 and have lied to their populations.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></p><p>Over-diagnosis is now recognized as a major harm of screening.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> Over-diagnosis, according to the US National Cancer Institute website, is the diagnosis of &#x0201c;a neoplasm that would never become clinically apparent prior to a patient&#x02019;s death without screening. An example is a tumor that is found by mammographic screening that would never be evident otherwise.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref> It has been estimated that 25% or more of screen-detected breast cancers are over-diagnosed.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> How is this puzzling conclusion reached? When screening trials were being planned, it was predicted that screening would initially result in an increased incidence of early cancer. With screening bringing forward the date of diagnosis compared to later clinical detection (lead time), the numbers of early breast cancers diagnosed were increased. This led to the assumption that later there would be a corresponding decline in the incidence of invasive cancer in the screened population. In fact, US SEER data reveal that the expected correlation between an initial increase in early cancers and a later decline in invasive cancers did not occur in the period 1983&#x02013;2005. The early increase occurred, but there was no subsequent decline in advanced cancers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> Similar observations have been made in Europe,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> leading to the conclusion that there is a substantial risk of over-diagnosis arising from screening programs. In contrast to the transitory disadvantages of false-positive screens, the downside of over-diagnosis is that its consequences are life-long.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Not only is treatment unpleasant, but its long-term consequences (pain, deformity, and increased risk of cardiac complications) are significant.</p><p>After many years of follow-up, combining data from screening trials demonstrates a significant 15%&#x02013;16% reduction in overall breast cancer mortality.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> However, looking specifically at screening benefit for women aged 40&#x02013;49, the Swedish Overview revealed a 9%,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> the UK Age trial a 17%<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> and the USPSTF a 15% reduction,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref> none of which were statistically significant. When that &#x0201c;benefit&#x0201d; is balanced against the 25% or more increased risk of screen-detected cancers that are over-diagnosed,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref> in addition to the recognized efficacy of current therapy,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> mammography screening benefits are diminished.</p><p>Perhaps even more compelling are the data relating breast cancer mortality to the presence or absence of screening programs. A 2010 Danish study compared breast cancer death rates over the period 1971 to 2005 in 20% of the Danish population living in counties where breast screening was offered for about 17 years, to death rates in the 80% of the population in counties where no screening occurred. Surprisingly, breast cancer deaths decreased as much in screened as unscreened populations up to the age of 74. Even more surprising was the finding that breast cancer deaths declined even in younger women who were ineligible for screening and thus did not undergo routine screening to detect their cancers. No decline was observed in women over age 74, another group ineligible for screening in Denmark.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></p><p>In addition, a recent overview of 30 European countries using WHO data has shown that breast cancer mortality dropped 37% in women under 50 years, who are generally ineligible for screening, while the drop was only 21% in women aged 50&#x02013;69 years, who were most commonly screened.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> Improvement in therapy (such as chemo- and hormone therapy) since the 1980s, when many screening trials were conducted, have undoubtedly contributed to the breast cancer mortality reduction observed in both screened and unscreened women.</p><p>It&#x02019;s time to recognize that screening benefits in younger women are small in relation to the risks of over-diagnosis. Screening advocates have used ad hominem attacks that, although inappropriate, have been very successful in dominating the screening controversy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> Survivors&#x02019; testimony in support of mammography screening has been powerful, even though it is incompatible with the reality that most women with breast cancer do not die of breast cancer. Their testimony is also incompatible with the reality that women who have been over-diagnosed never will die of their &#x0201c;cancer.&#x0201d; In addition, what the early breast cancer survivors may not be aware of is the sad fact that breast cancer can kill 20 years after diagnosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></p><p>As recently observed in the <italic>New England Journal of Medicine</italic>, we should &#x0201c;work to prevent vested interests from being granted the loudest voices in health care.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> The vested interests in what has been termed &#x0201c;the mammography wars&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> are clearly those in the imaging industry, those involved directly in screening programs, and even those in the not-for-profit sector, whose fundraising capacity is enhanced by a public committed to fighting breast cancer.</p><p>It is reasonable for women to choose to be screened, but only if they are completely informed about the probability of benefit versus the probability of harm. For 2000 women aged 40&#x02013;49 who undergo screening for 10 years, the benefit is much smaller in terms of avoiding death from breast cancer than is the harm arising from over-diagnosis and unnecessary treatment for breast cancer, to say nothing of the increased rates of mastectomy associated with screening.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref> These issues are not widely known to the general public. After over 20 years of involvement in the screening controversy I can only conclude that this is information few want to hear and many want to suppress.</p><fig id="textbox1" position="float"><label>Textbox 1</label><caption><p>Summary of United States Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) recommendations on screening for breast cancer</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-05-e134-g001"/></fig></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakdawalle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Philipson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The contributions of improved therapy and earlier detection to cancer survival gains, 1988&#x02013;2000</article-title><source>Forum Health Econ Policy</source><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><comment>Article 1<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bepress.com/fhep/13/2/1">http://www.bepress.com/fhep/13/2/1</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quanstrum</surname><given-names>Kerianne H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>Rodney A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons from the mammography wars</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>363</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1076</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsb1002538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20825322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>US Preventive Services Task Force</collab><article-title>Screening for breast cancer: U.S. Preventive Services Task Force recommendation statement</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1059/0003-4819-151-10-200911170-00008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelblatt</surname><given-names>Jeanne S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>Kathleen A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>Stephanie</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>Donald A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>Harry J</given-names></name><name><surname>Draisma</surname><given-names>Gerrit</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sandra J</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsell</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><name><surname>Plevritis</surname><given-names>Sylvia K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravdin</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>Clyde B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>Bronislava</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoto</surname><given-names>Michael A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>Natasha K</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>Nicolien T</given-names></name><name><surname>Venier</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelen</surname><given-names>Marvin</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>Eric J</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Breast Cancer Working Group of the Cancer Intervention and Surveillance Modeling Network</collab><article-title>Effects of mammography screening under different screening schedules: model estimates of potential benefits and harms</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1059/0003-4819-151-10-200911170-00010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamerow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yankee doodling: mammograms, poor communication, and politics</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2009</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>b5275</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>Leonard</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Ferris M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>More mammography muddle: emotions, politics, science, costs, and polarization</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>255</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.10100056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>Karsten Juhl</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahl</surname><given-names>Per-Henrik</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname><given-names>Peter C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer mortality in organised mammography screening in Denmark: comparative study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2010</year><month>3</month><day>23</day><volume>340</volume><fpage>c1241</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20332505">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20332505</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>Fabio</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosetti</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucchini</surname><given-names>Franca</given-names></name><name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>Carlo</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring the decrease in breast cancer mortality in Europe</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Autier</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><name><surname>Boniol</surname><given-names>Mathieu</given-names></name><name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>Carlo</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatten</surname><given-names>Lars</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e9;ry</surname><given-names>Clarisse</given-names></name><name><surname>Heanue</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in breast cancer mortality trends between 30 European countries: retrospective trend analysis of WHO mortality database</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2010</year><month>8</month><day>11</day><volume>341</volume><fpage>c3620</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20702548">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20702548</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20702548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalager</surname><given-names>Mette</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelen</surname><given-names>Marvin</given-names></name><name><surname>Langmark</surname><given-names>Fr&#x000f8;ydis</given-names></name><name><surname>Adami</surname><given-names>Hans-Olov</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of screening mammography on breast-cancer mortality in Norway</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>363</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>1210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1000727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20860502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopans</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why the critics of screening mammography are wrong: They distort data, rely on weak science, but refuse to defend when challenged</article-title><source>Diagn Imaging</source><year>2009</year><volume>31</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>H Gilbert</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>William C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overdiagnosis in cancer</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2010</year><month>4</month><day>22</day><volume>102</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jnci.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=20413742">http://jnci.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=20413742</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djq099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20413742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croswell</surname><given-names>Jennifer M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ransohoff</surname><given-names>David F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>Barnett S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles of cancer screening: lessons from history and study design issues</article-title><source>Semin Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20709205">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20709205</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.seminoncol.2010.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20709205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>Karsten Juhl</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname><given-names>Peter C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overdiagnosis in publicly organised mammography screening programmes: systematic review of incidence trends</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2009</year><month>7</month><day>09</day><volume>339</volume><fpage>b2587</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/19589821">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/19589821</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19589821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Cancer Institute</collab><source>Breast cancer screening (PDQ): Harms of screening</source><date-in-citation>accessed 15 July 2011</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/screening/breast/healthprofessional/page6">http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/screening/breast/healthprofessional/page6</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>Linda L</given-names></name><name><surname>Helfand</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Benjamin K S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolf</surname><given-names>Steven H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer screening: a summary of the evidence for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>137</volume><issue>5 Part 1</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://symptomresearch.nih.gov/tablecontents.htm">http://symptomresearch.nih.gov/tablecontents.htm</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12204020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for breast cancer with mammography</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2009</year><month>10</month><day>7</day><issue>4</issue><fpage>CD001877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19821284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nystr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>Lennarth</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>Ingvar</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjurstam</surname><given-names>Nils</given-names></name><name><surname>Frisell</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordenskj&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutqvist</surname><given-names>Lars Erik</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term effects of mammography screening: updated overview of the Swedish randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><issue>9310</issue><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08020-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11918907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>Sue M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuckle</surname><given-names>Howard</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Andy</given-names></name><name><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobrow</surname><given-names>Lynda</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Trial Management Group</collab><article-title>Effect of mammographic screening from age 40 years on breast cancer mortality at 10 years' follow-up: a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2060</year><volume>368</volume><issue>9552</issue><fpage>2053</fpage><lpage>2060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)69834-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17161727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rational and irrational issues in breast cancer screening</article-title><source>Cancers</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/3/1/252/pdf">http://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/3/1/252/pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adair</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>G F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term followup of breast cancer patients: the 30-year report</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>1974</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1145</fpage><lpage>1150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4819216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>J Michael</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast screening has increased the number of mastectomies</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><month>12</month><day>18</day><volume>11</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S19</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20030870">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20030870</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/bcr2438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20030870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname><given-names>Peter C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>Margrethe</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening for breast cancer with mammography</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2011</year><month>1</month><day>19</day><issue>1</issue><fpage>CD001877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001877.pub4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21249649</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>