<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21687332</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3090101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-04-e134-138</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Institutional financial conflicts of interest policies at Canadian academic health science centres: a national survey</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rochon</surname><given-names>Paula A</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Paula A Rochon</bold>, MD, MPH, is senior scientist at Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute at Women&#x02019;s College Hospital, Toronto, and professor at the Department of Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sekeres</surname><given-names>Melanie</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Melanie Sekeres</bold>, MSc, is a graduate student at the Department of Physiology, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lexchin</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Joel Lexchin</bold>, MSc, MD, is professor at the School of Health Policy and Management, York University, Toronto, emergency physician at the Emergency Department, University Health Network, Toronto, and associate professor at the Department of Family and Community Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>David Moher</bold>, PhD, is senior scientist at the Ottawa Methods Centre, Clinical Epidemiology Program, Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, and an associate professor at the Department of Epidemiology &#x00026; Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Ont.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Wei Wu</bold>, MSc, is statistical analyst at Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute, Women&#x02019;s College Hospital, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalkar</surname><given-names>Sunila R</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Sunila R Kalkar</bold>, MBBS, MD, MEd, is research coordinator at Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute and Women&#x02019;s College Hospital, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Laethem</surname><given-names>Marleen</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Marleen Van Laethem</bold>, MHSc, is research ethicist at the Toronto Rehabilitation Institute, Toronto, and member at the Joint Centre for Bioethics, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoey</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>John Hoey</bold>, MD, is adjunct professor at Queen&#x02019;s University, Kingston, Ont.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib9" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>An-Wen</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>An-Wen Chan</bold>, MD, DPhil, is a Phelan scientist at Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute, Women&#x02019;s College Hospital, Toronto, and assistant professor at the Department of Medicine, University of Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib10" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gruneir</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Andrea Gruneir</bold>, PhD, is a scientist at Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute, Women&#x02019;s College Hospital, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib11" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Jennifer Gold</bold>, LLB, MPH, is legal counsel, Ontario Medical Association, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib12" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maskalyk</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>James Maskalyk</bold>, MD, is assistant professor at the Division of Emergency Medicine, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib13" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Streiner</surname><given-names>David L</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>David L Streiner</bold>, PhD, CPsych, is professor at the Department of Psychiatry, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib14" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taback</surname><given-names>Nathan</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Nathan Taback</bold>, PhD, is assistant professor at Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib15" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>Lorraine E</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Lorraine E Ferris</bold>, PhD, LLM, is professor at Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Toronto.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Dr. Paula A. Rochon, Women&#x02019;s College Research Institute, 790 Bay Street, Toronto  ON; M5G 1N8  tel: 416-351-3732 x2711; fax: 416-351-3746; <email>paula.rochon@utoronto.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e134</fpage><lpage>e138</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/340/341">http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/340/341</self-uri></article-meta></front><body><p>Financial conflicts of interest (fCOI) are of particular concern in the conduct of human subject research, whether they occur at the level of individual investigators or at the level of the institution.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> Institutional fCOI can occur when an institution that hosts the research, or a senior institutional official acting on behalf of the institution, has a financial interest in the study outcome.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Such conflicts can be detrimental to research subjects,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> lead to an inappropriate degree of control over what should be an independent research agenda,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> and have serious implications, even in the absence of research misconducts.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Moreover, undisclosed fCOI undermine the public&#x02019;s confidence in science. </p><p>For example, senior National Institutes of Health (NIH) officials were allowed to receive income as consultants to drug companies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> The concern that this income might inappropriately influence their work resulted in the formation of a national Blue Ribbon committee to examine NIH conflict-of-interest policies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> The committee&#x02019;s 2004 report recommended that senior management should not consult with companies whose interests could influence the outcomes of their research<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> ultimately led to a moratorium on industry-paid consultancies held by any NIH employee. Despite increased scrutiny of this issue on the part of government,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> the media,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> and the public,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> academic institutions have been slow to develop policies related to institutional fCOI.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> We conducted a content analysis of the institutional fCOI policies in use at Canadian academic health science centres (AHSCs) to identify gaps in policy coverage and to guide policy improvement. </p><p>Our research methods are more fully described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>. In brief, we collected institution-level fCOI policies from all 16 AHSCs (16 medical schools and 47 teaching hospitals as well as their 16 partner universities) from August 2005 to February 2006. These centres are the major sites of academic research involving humans in Canada. We contacted the vice president (VP) of research (or equivalent) at each site and asked him or her to identify 3 key institutional fCOI policies at their institution. To evaluate policy comprehensiveness, we compared each unique policy to our &#x0201c;standard&#x0201d; of 16 core items relevant to institutional fCOI derived from the key COI documents.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></p><p>All 16 universities (100%), their 16 medical schools (100%), and 42 (89%) of the teaching hospitals responded to our request for policies. Nine (56%) universities, 9 (56%) medical schools, and 15 (36%) teaching hospitals responded that they had no policies on institutional fCOI. </p><p>Of the 72 policies identified, 34 were shared within AHSCs. Approximately a quarter (26%) of universities, medical schools, and teaching hospitals identified more than one institutional fCOI policy. Only 6 (16%) included &#x0201c;institutional conflicts of interest&#x0201d; in the policy title. Five (13%) policies were cross-referenced to other relevant policies from their institution. Of the 2 teaching hospitals that used internal and partner-university policies, neither cross-referenced the other&#x02019;s policies. The ability of some leaders within an AHSC to identify a fCOI policy, while others based in the same AHSC could not, suggested that communication within AHSCs about fCOI policies was limited. For example, one teaching hospital said that its submitted fCOI policy was also used by its parent university; however, the parent university reported having no relevant policy. </p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> describes a content analysis of the 38 unique policies. Definitions that informed our content analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="box2">Box 2</xref>. Of the policies analyzed, 2 contained no items of relevance to institutional fCOI. On average, individual policies contained 20% of the 16 core &#x0201c;standard&#x0201d; items: no individual policy contained more than 65% of the core fCOI items. Even when the content of up to 3 policies per site was combined, less than half of the core items were addressed. Less than a quarter of policies addressed royalties, equity interest, or ownership interests. </p><fig id="box1" position="float"><label>Box 1</label><caption><p>Description of methods</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-04-e134-g001"/></fig><fig id="box2" position="float"><label>Box 2</label><caption><p>Glossary of terms</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-04-e134-g002"/></fig><fig id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comprehensiveness of institutional fCOI policies at Canadian academic health sciences centres (universities, medical schools and teaching hospitals)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-04-e134-g003"/></fig><p>Our results demonstrate that more than half of Canadian universities, half of medical schools, and more than a third of teaching hospitals had no institutional fCOI policy at the time of our survey. This is consistent with a 2006 survey of 86 deans of US medical schools (response rate 86/125), which found that fewer than half (38%) reported adopting an institutional fCOI policy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> Further, policies were inadequately comprehensive and often difficult to locate.</p><p>Like all studies, our work has limitations. First, we requested a maximum of 3 policies from each site; some may speculate that this truncated our results if sites had more than 3 policies relating to the core fCOI items. (For example, the Pennsylvania School of Medicine reports having more than 90 policies regarding conflicts of interest.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> However, given that 33 of 74 (45%) sites reported no relevant policies and only 10 (13%) sites identified 3, we think this is unlikely. </p><p>Second, we used a stringent definition of &#x0201c;policy&#x0201d; and recognize that this would have excluded other terms used to label policies (e.g., &#x0201c;protocols,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;statements&#x0201d; or &#x0201d;standards&#x0201d;). Moreover, a strategic position taken by the institution or mechanisms to deal with institutional fCOI could have been in place without being articulated in a policy and thus would have been missed by our research method. </p><p>Third, our research focused on the adoption of policies and gave particular attention to their comprehensiveness. This does not capture the measures established at each institution to manage fCOI. Some AHSCs may have very detailed policies that are ineffective because they are not implemented or enforced, while others may have a poorly developed formal policy while still having effective mechanisms to address and manage institutional fCOI. Even detailed policies may not be sufficient to anticipate all issues related to institutional fCOI that could arise within an academic institution.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref> While simply having a comprehensive policy is not sufficient, it is a usual means of communicating expected standards in academic institutions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></p><p>Fourth, the list of the 16 items we used to evaluate the comprehensiveness of a policy was based on information from the AAMC<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> and the AAU <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> that was available at the time of our survey. The 2008 AAMC template policy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> contains the 16 core items we identified as being central to an institutional fCOI policy and adds further clarification. We expect that relevant policy items will continue to evolve. Further, we evaluated only whether the policy mentioned the core fCOI items. An evaluation of the quality of information provided about each core item may reveal further deficiencies. </p><p>Finally, this study was conducted on policies in place in 2006. Given the requirement for Canadian institutions holding federal funds to put conflict-of-interest policies in place by January 2009,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>we expect that many Canadian AHSCs are actively developing and implementing their institutional fCOI policies. Attention will need to be paid to having university-wide fCOI policies that are sensitive enough to capture issues specific to medical schools, or allowances will need to be made for medical schools to have a supplemental fCOI policy. </p><p>In summary, over half of the Canadian AHSCs lacked institutional fCOI policies at the time of our survey. Where policies existed, they were not comprehensive and were frequently difficult to access. The 2008 Report of the AAMC-AAU Advisory Committee on Financial Conflicts of Interest in Human Subjects Research<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> offers a thoughtful discussion on the complex institutional fCOI issues and provides a useful template for institutional policy. Other hospitals and universities that are not affiliated with AHSCs will also need to develop fCOI policies if they receive Canadian Tri-Council federal funds. Professional societies and those involved in clinical practice guideline development may also wish to develop these policies.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref> We trust that our results related to core policy items will support appropriate policy development in this area.</p></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Susan Ehringhaus for reviewing an earlier version of this manuscript and her helpful comments. We also thank Lori Lyons for her editorial comments, Peter Anderson for technical assistance, and Marie-Eve Couture, who conducted the data abstraction of all French language policies.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: Joel Lexchin was retained by a law firm representing Apotex to provide expert testimony about the effects of promotion on the sales of medications. He has also been retained as an expert witness by the Canadian federal government in its defence of a lawsuit launched challenging the ban on direct-to-consumer advertising of prescription drugs in Canada. John Hoey and James Maskalyk are associate editors, David Moher is a contributing editor, and Paula Rochon is on the editorial board of Open Medicine; none of them was involved in reviewing the article or deciding on its acceptance for publication. No conflicts are reported for the rest of the authors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Funding source: This project was funded by the Canadian Institutes for Health Research through Evaluation of the Integrity of Clinical Research in Canada grant EIC-77338. The sponsor had no role in the design, analysis, or publication of this study.</p><p><bold>Role of the sponsor:</bold> The funding organization did not participate in the design or conduct of the study, in the collection, analysis, or interpretation of the data, or in the preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript. Dr. Rochon had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Contributors: Paula A Rochon conceived and designed the project, drafted the manuscript and approved it for publication. Melanie Sekeres contributed to the conception and design of the survey, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Joel Lexchin contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. David Moher contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Wei Wu contributed to the analysis and interpretation of data, revised the manuscript for important intellectual content, and gave final approval of the version to be published. Sunila R Kalkar participated in conducting literature reviews, analyzing and interpret&#x000ad;ing the data and revising the manuscript for important intellectual content, and approved it for publication. Marleen Van Laethem contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. John Hoey contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. An-Wen Chan contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Andrea Gruneir participated in analyzing and interpret&#x000ad;ing the data and revising the manuscript for important intellectual content, and approved it for publication. Jennifer Gold was involved in the conception of the project, conducted some of the literature reviews, helped develop and analyze the survey instrument, read through the final manuscript and approved it for pub&#x000ad;lication. James Maskalyk contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. David L Streiner contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Nathan Taback contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Lorraine E Ferris contributed to the conception and design of the project, participated in analyzing the research, and contributed to the writing of the final paper and approved it for publication. Paula Rochon is the study guarantor.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AAMC-AAU Advisory Committee on Financial Conflicts of Interest in Human Subjects Research</collab><source>Protecting patients, preserving integrity, advancing health: accelerating the implementation of COI policies in human subjects research</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of American Medical Colleges</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.aamc.org/publications/index.cfm?fuseaction=Product.displayForm&#x00026;prd_id=220">https://services.aamc.org/publications/index.cfm?fuseaction=Product.displayForm&#x00026;prd_id=220</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AAMC Task Force on Financial Conflicts of Interest in Clinical Research</collab><source>Protecting subjects, preserving trust, promoting progress II: principles and recommendations for oversight of an institution&#x02019;s financial interests in human subjects research</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of Americal Medical Colleges</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aamc.org/research/coi/2002coireport.pdf">http://www.aamc.org/research/coi/2002coireport.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><name><surname>Florencio</surname><given-names>Patrik S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Financial conflicts of interest in human subjects research: the problem of institutional conflicts</article-title><source>J Law Med Ethics</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12497699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>David J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Academic medical centers and financial conflicts of interest</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2008</year><volume>299</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.299.6.695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudy</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Konefal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Eyck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Universities in the age of corporate science: The UC Berkeley&#x02013;Novartis controversy</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia (PA)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>NIH in the spotlight over conflicts of interest</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>633</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(04)00887-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Institutes of Health</collab><source>Report of the National Institutes of Health Blue Ribbon Panel on Conflict of Interest Policies. A Working Group of the Advisory Committee to the Director</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Bethesda (MD)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Institutes of Health</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brockway</surname><given-names>Laura M</given-names></name><name><surname>Furcht</surname><given-names>Leo T</given-names></name></person-group><collab>FASEB</collab><article-title>Conflicts of interest in biomedical research&#x02014;the FASEB guidelines</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2435</fpage><lpage>2438</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fasebj.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=17142792">http://www.fasebj.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=17142792</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.06-6723LSF</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S Y H</given-names></name><name><surname>Millard</surname><given-names>R W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisbet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caine</surname><given-names>E D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential research participants&#x02019; views regarding researcher and institutional financial conflicts of interest</article-title><source>J Med Ethics</source><year>2004</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jme.bmj.com/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=14872080">http://jme.bmj.com/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=14872080</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14872080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AAU Task Force on Research Accountability</collab><source>Report on individual and institutional financial conflict of interest</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of American Universities</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aau.edu/research/COI.01.pdf">http://www.aau.edu/research/COI.01.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehringhaus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>U.S. medical school policies on individual financial conflicts of interest: results of an AAMC survey</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Association of Medical Colleges</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aamc.org/research/coi/coiresults2003.pdf">http://www.aamc.org/research/coi/coiresults2003.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promoting integrity in industry-sponsored clinical drug trials: conflict of interest for Canadian academic health sciences centers</article-title><source>Law and ethics in biomedical research: regulation, conflict of interest, and liability</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding financial conflicts of interest</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1993</year><volume>329</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgenson</surname><given-names>Gretchen</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>Campbell R</given-names></name></person-group><source>The New York Times dictionary of money and investing: the essential a-to-z guide to the language of the new market</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Times Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charitable conflicts of interest</article-title><source>J Bus Ethics</source><year>2002</year><volume>39</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Academic-industrial relationships in the life sciences</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>349</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>2452</fpage><lpage>2459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMhpr035460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Global Development Research Centre</collab><source>Notes on technology transfer</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gdrc.org/uem/techtran.html">http://www.gdrc.org/uem/techtran.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehringhaus</surname><given-names>Susan H</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>Joel S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>Jacqueline L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goold</surname><given-names>Susan Dorr</given-names></name><name><surname>Feibelmann</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Eric G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of medical schools to institutional conflicts of interest</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2008</year><volume>299</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=18270355">http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=18270355</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.299.6.665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18270355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasserstein</surname><given-names>Alan G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>Patrick J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>Arthur H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Institutional leadership and faculty response: fostering professionalism at the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>82</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ACM.0b013e31815763d2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17971690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>Maryann P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Scott L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>U.S. research universities&#x02019; institutional conflict of interest policies</article-title><source>J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/jer.2009.4.3.3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19754230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</collab><source>Schedule 14: Conflicts of interest in research. Memorandum of understanding (MOU) on the roles and responsibilities in the management of federal grants and awards</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nserc.gc.ca/institution/mou_e.htm">http://www.nserc.gc.ca/institution/mou_e.htm</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Conflict of interest in medical research, education, and practice</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12598">http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12598</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>