<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">OpenMed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009685</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4085086</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-8-e54-e66</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title xml:lang="en">Decision-making about complementary and alternative medicine by cancer patients: integrative literature review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><aff>Laura Weeks, PhD, is a Senior Research Fellow at the Ottawa Integrative Cancer Centre, Ottawa, Ontario.</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>Lynda G</given-names></name><aff>Lynda G. Balneaves, RN, PhD, is an Associate Professor in the School of Nursing, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia.</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>Charlotte</given-names></name><aff>Charlotte Paterson, MSc, PhD, MBChB, MRCGP, is a Research Fellow in the School of Social and Community Medicine at the University of Bristol, Bristol, England.</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>Marja</given-names></name><aff>Marja Verhoef, PhD, is a Professor and Canada Research Chair in Complementary Medicine in the Department of Community Health, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta.</aff><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">Dr. Marja Verhoef, Department of Community Health Sciences, University of Calgary, 3280 Hospital Dr. NW, Calgary AB T2N 4Z6; <email xlink:href="mverhoef@ucalgary.ca">mverhoef@ucalgary.ca</email></corresp><fn id="AFN1" fn-type="con"><p>Lynda Balneaves, Charlotte Paterson and Marja Verhoef conceived the project and, collectively with Laura Weeks, finalized the study methodology. Laura Weeks conducted the database search, and all authors helped to screen studies for inclusion in the review. Laura Weeks collected the data and led the data analysis, with regular input through team meetings with Lynda Balneaves, Charlotte Paterson and Marja Verhoef. Laura Weeks wrote the first draft of this manuscript, and Lynda Balneaves, Charlotte Paterson and Marja Verhoef reviewed and edited a series of manuscript drafts. Marja Verhoef is the guarantor and maintains responsibility for the integrity of the work. All of the authors approved the final version of this manuscript</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e54</fpage><lpage>e66</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Copyright by Societ&#x000e0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country. For more information, please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="sa"><title>Background:</title><p>Patients with cancer consistently report conflict and anxiety when making decisions about complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) treatment. To design evidence-informed decision-support strategies, a better understanding is needed of how the decision-making process unfolds for these patients during their experience with cancer. We undertook this study to review the research literature regarding CAM-related decisionmaking by patients with cancer within the context of treatment, survivorship, and palliation. We also aimed to summarize emergent concepts within a preliminary conceptual framework.</p></sec><sec id="sb"><title>Methods:</title><p>We conducted an integrative literature review, searching 12 electronic databases for articles published in English that described studies of the process, context, or outcomes of CAM-related decision-making. We summarized descriptive data using frequencies and used a descriptive constant comparative method to analyze statements about original qualitative results, with the goal of identifying distinct concepts pertaining to CAM-related decision-making by patients with cancer and the relationships among these concepts.</p></sec><sec id="sc"><title>Results:</title><p>Of 425 articles initially identified, 35 met our inclusion criteria. Seven unique concepts related to CAM and cancer decision-making emerged: decision-making phases, information-seeking and evaluation, decision-making roles, beliefs, contextual factors, decision-making outcomes, and the relationship between CAM and conventional medical decision-making. CAM decision-making begins with the diagnosis of cancer and encompasses 3 distinct phases (early, mid, and late), each marked by unique aims for CAM treatment and distinct patterns of informationseeking and evaluation. Phase transitions correspond to changes in health status or other milestones within the cancer trajectory. An emergent conceptual framework illustrating relationships among the 7 central concepts is presented.</p></sec><sec id="sd"><title>Interpretation:</title><p>CAM-related decision-making by patients with cancer occurs as a nonlinear, complex, dynamic process. The conceptual framework presented here identifies influential factors within that process, as well as patients' unique needs during different phases. The framework can guide the development and evaluation of theorybased decision-support programs that are responsive to patients' beliefs and preferences.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>It is well established that at least half of all patients with cancer use some form of complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) , such as acupuncture, massage, and natural health products, as part of their cancer care.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Many factors contribute to the high prevalence of CAM use, including an increasing amount of high-quality research evidence, increased regulation and availability of natural health products, improved regulation of qualified practitioners, and cultural trends that privilege more "natural" therapies and individual involvement in self-care.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Although CAM use has become common within cancer care, it remains controversial. Many CAM practices originate within philosophical traditions that deviate from Western medicine, leading some individuals to view them skeptically.<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Furthermore, the body of research evidence for most CAM therapies tends to be smaller and often of lower quality than the evidence for conventional medical therapies.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Existing CAM research evidence is also often difficult to find, synthesize, and share with appropriate knowledge users.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Finally, the potential for interactions with conventional cancer therapies is another common concern.<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p><p>The controversies surrounding CAM use contribute to increased levels of conflict and anxiety for patients who contemplate using these therapies as part of their cancer care.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> For this reason, researchers have begun to explore how and in what context patients with cancer make decisions about CAM use, primarily in an effort to design supportive interventions. Many different perspectives have been explored, including those of people with a range of cancer types,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> those who have declined standard care,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> and those who identify with a specific ethnic group.<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> It has become clear that CAM-related decision-making by patients with cancer (hereafter referred to as "CAM and cancer decision-making") is a complex, dynamic, nonlinear, and highly individualized process. To design evidenceinformed decision-support strategies, a better understanding is needed not only of how the decisionmaking process related to use of CAM unfolds during the cancer trajectory but also of the relevant concepts and relationships.</p><p>The purpose of this study was to review the research literature regarding CAM-related decision-making by patients with cancer within the context of treatment, survivorship, and palliation. Specifically, we were interested in the process, context, and outcomes of CAM decision-making and how this decision-making process relates to that associated with conventional medical treatments. We aimed to summarize the literature, to synthesize its critical elements into a preliminary conceptual framework, and to make recommendations for future research.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="S1"><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted an integrative literature review<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> of English- language research articles published since 1998 that describe CAM decision-making related to cancer treatment, survivorship, or palliation. Integrative literature reviews follow many of the same methods as systematic reviews, but their scope is broader. The intent is to synthesize a broad range of literature on an emerging topic with the goal of developing an initial or preliminary model or framework.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Through this review, we intended to propose a more comprehensive, holistic understanding of CAM and cancer decision-making than has been possible through any primary research study.</p><p>Our search strategy was developed with the assistance of a health librarian and included both subject headings and keywords related to cancer, decision-making, and CAM or integrative medicine (online Appendix A). We searched the following electronic databases through September 2011: Academic OneFile, Alt HealthWatch, Allied and Complementary Medicine Database, CINAHL, EBSCO, Embase, MEDLINE, OmniFile, PsycINFO, PubMed, SocINDEX, and Sociological Abstracts. We included articles that described either or both of (1) the process or context of CAM decision-making relevant to cancer treatment, survivorship, or palliation; and (2) the outcomes of the decision-making process. We defined a "process" as a series of actions, changes, or reactions that happen over time as an individual contemplates CAM treatment options. We defined "context" as the set of circumstances within which decision-making takes place. We defined "outcomes" as the results of the decision-making process (and not of the cancer). Pertinent articles were included whether CAM decision-making was considered as a separate issue or as an issue alongside conventional medical decision-making. We excluded articles that described decision-making related to cancer prevention and those that focused exclusively on CAM use or the context of CAM use, although (as stated above) we included articles that described the context of CAM decision-making. All of the authors participated in the screening process, with various pairs of authors independently screening each article title and abstract for eligibility. For articles where it was difficult to determine eligibility on the basis of title and abstract alone, the full text of the article was retrieved and examined before eligibility was determined. Screening decisions were recorded in an Excel database and were compared by one reviewer (L.W.) for consistency. Discrepancies were discussed and resolved during a team teleconference during which all reviewers had access to all abstracts and/or full-text articles as required. Once a preliminary list of included articles had been developed, we reviewed the reference list of each article for other potentially eligible articles missed in the initial search.</p><p>Descriptive data and results of the included studies were extracted from each article by one reviewer (L.W.). Descriptive data included such items as first author, article title, research purpose, sample size, and study design. In addition, the reviewer extracted verbatim result statements from each of the included studies. A quality assessment was not conducted, as such an assessment is outside the scope of an integrative literature review. Descriptive data were analyzed by calculating frequencies for relevant categories within each variable. Result statements were analyzed through an iterative process, with the goal of identifying distinct concepts relevant to CAM decision-making. The reviewer began by reading each article to ensure a comprehensive understanding of the content. Next, the reviewer extracted individual result statements and grouped them within Altas.ti qualitative software according to unique concepts within CAM decisionmaking that the statements represented. As each result statement was extracted, it was compared with all previously extracted statements, so that it could be grouped with similar statements or placed into a new category. Each category was labelled with a term to describe a concept within CAM decision-making that the statements in the category represented. Labels were emergent, based on careful reading of the data and regular team discussions, and were not necessarily borrowed from the reviewed articles, to avoid privileging any particular perspective from the existing literature. In the course of this analysis, a set of 7 unique analytic categories emerged. The final step was to synthesize the result statements within each category and propose a preliminary conceptual framework. One reviewer conducted the majority of the analysis; however, regular teleconferences and email discussions with the research team helped to confer authenticity within the emerging analytic categories.</p><p>The predefined review protocol is available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="S2"><title>Results</title><p>We identified 425 articles by searching the electronic databases and scanning reference lists. Of these, 35 articles<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> met our criteria and were included in the review (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Results of search strategy and process of identifying articles related to complementary and alternative medicine and decision-making by patients with cancer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-08-54-g001"/></fig><sec id="S2a"><title>Descriptive analysis</title><p>Over half of the included articles (19 [54%]) described studies that had been conducted in Canada. The majority (31 [89%]) included participants with any stage of cancer, and over half (19 [54%]) described studies that focused on all cancer types. One-third (12 [34%]) of the included articles described studies that explored CAM and cancer decision-making from the perspective of one or more special populations: various ethnic groups (6 [17%]), those who declined some form of conventional treatment (5 [14%]), significant others (1 [3%]), and participants in phase I clinical trials (1 [3%]). The majority of these articles (25 [71%]) described qualitative research studies, whereas the others reported on cross-sectional surveys (5 [14%]), mixed-methods studies (3 [9%]), or synthesis research (2 [6%]). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> summarizes the descriptive results.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive information about 35 articles describing decision-making by patients with cancer</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purpose</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of theory</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer type, special population</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Method or type of analysis</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balneaves et al.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the personal and social processes engaged in by women with early-stage breast cancer when making decisions about CAM during the period from diagnosis to survivorship</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergent, developed by authors ("Bridging the Gap")</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast (stage I and II)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grounded theory</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balneaves et al.<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To provide a preliminary description of use of complementary therapies by women living with breast cancer and the predisposing factors associated with the decision to use complementary therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bishop and Yardley<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the positioning of people within accounts of treatment decisions and thereby to explicate strategies used to manage ideological conflict within the context of orthodox and complementary medicine in cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positioning theory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Discourse analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate the question, "Are users of CAM more autonomous than non-users with respect to problem-solving and decision-making preferences?"</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deber&#x02013;Kraestchmer problem-solving decision-making scale</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">489</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore prostate cancer patients' perceptions, feelings, ideas, and experiences regarding making decisions to use or not use CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Push&#x02013;pull factors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine breast cancer patients' perceptions of, approaches to, and experiences with CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Push&#x02013;pull factors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazier et al.<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To evaluate the impact of participating in an integrative cancer care program at the Centre for Integrated Healing in Vancouver, British Columbia, on patients' lifestyle, quality of life, and overall well-being</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretive description</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To understand how individuals with cancer make decisions about the legitimacy of ideas, expertise, treatments, and regimens in the context of their cancer and to develop a conceptualization of therapeutic decision-making, using the notion of bricolage<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1FN2">*</xref> as a key point of departure</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All; intensive CAM users</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretive qualitative research</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom and Tovey<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine individual cancer patients' temporal experiences of CAM, including (1) the disciplining of the self demanded by certain CAM therapeutics and the impact of that on the experience of having cancer, (2) the role of CAM healing therapists in reconceptualizing disease and fi lling perceived gaps in biomedical cancer care, and (3) the complex interplay between CAM-derived notions, self-healing, and the state of nearing death</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All; intensive CAM users</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretive qualitative research</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom and Tovey<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine cancer patients' perspectives on the nature of evidence and the degree to which different understandings of evidence inform decision-making about CAM and biomedicine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social theory (postmodernity, reflexivity, technologies of the self, dialectic)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interpretive qualitative research</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brown et al.<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To elucidate common themes across 3 studies of women's decisionmaking and to examine the process that women undergo in making an important decision about their health and well-being, including where and how they acquire the necessary information to make a decision, the factors that influence their decision, who supports them in the decision-making process, and how they reconcile confusing or conflicting information</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergent, developed by authors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant comparison</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chiu et al.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore, in a sample of Chinese patients with cancer, (1) the general conceptualization of CAM use, (2) the meaning of CAM use in relation to cancer, (3) the patterns of CAM use before and after cancer diagnosis, (4) the reasons for CAM use, and (5) the sociocultural process in making decisions about CAM use</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergent, developed by authors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All types (stages I, II, and III); Chinese patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant comparison</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evans et al.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the processes shaping men's decision-making about CAM and the rationales they provide for their views and behaviour</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male cancer, any type</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant comparison</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evans et al.<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the use and evaluation of CAM-related information by male cancer patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male cancer, any type</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Kingdom</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not specific; thematic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gray et al.<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore cancer patients' motivations for seeking information about unconventional therapies, their decision-making processes, their experiences with such therapies, their attempts to communicate with conventional health care practitioners, and their perceptions of family members and friends' reactions to their interest in unconventional therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not specific; thematic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hlubocky et al.<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe the general usage rates of biologically based CAM among participants in phase I trials; secondary objectives were to explore social and demographic factors associated with CAM use, to describe potential differences in treatment decision-making preferences among CAM users and non-users, and to investigate associations of CAM use with awareness of prognosis and quality of life</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Advanced cancer; phase I trial participants</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jones et al.<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the beliefs and attitudes of African American survivors of prostate cancer regarding the use of CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate; African American patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey and phenomenology</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kakai et al.<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate ethnic differences in health information&#x02013;seeking behaviours among cancer patients of diverse ethnicity in Hawaii; also, to explore a possible association between patients' education and ethnicity and choice of health information</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All; various ethnic groups</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correspondence analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kimby et al.<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the relationships between user profiles (sociodemographic factors, treatment orientations, cancer status) and users' choice of various unconventional types of treatment (individualized versus standardized unconventional treatments)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Markovic et al.<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the impact of specific social and cultural factors influencing health care decision-making</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gynecologic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grounded theory</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Montbriand<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To recreate a model reflecting the health decision realities of patients with a diagnosis of cancer of the respiratory or digestive system</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naturalistic and rationalistic research; phenomenology; heuristics; Tversky's elimination-by-aspects theory; and emergent, developed by authors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory and digestive</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnography (following phenomenology)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oh and Park<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore how patients with cancer choose a therapy after the diagnosis has been made and the decision-making strategies used by these patients when they visit a doctor or when they use alternative therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive ethnographic decision tree model</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ohl&#x000e9;n et al.<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore how significant others were involved in cancer patients' decision-making processes related to CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast and prostate (early and advanced); significant others</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grounded theory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 with early cancer; 21 with advanced cancer; 31 significant others</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Owens<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe the self-help theoretical framework in relation to CAM and to delineate relationships in Braden's Self-Help Model of sideeffect burden to uncertainty, CAM self-care, and quality of life in Hispanic women undergoing treatment for breast cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braden's Self-Help Theory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast; Hispanic patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional survey</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ritvo et al.<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To apply a theoretical model, the Risk Adaptation Model, to further the clinical understanding of the motivations of cancer patients in seeking complementary therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Adaptation Model</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not original research</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not original research</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not original research</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shumay et al.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine cancer patients' reasons for declining all or part of recommended cancer treatment and choosing CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Montbriand's decisiontree model</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All; various ethnic groups; patients who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thematic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singh et al.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To compare the perceptions, beliefs, ideas, and experiences that contribute to the decision of patients with prostate cancer to use or not to use CAM</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate; various ethnic groups</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thematic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truant and Bottorff <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the decision-making process for complementary therapies from the perspective of women with breast cancer in the context of the cancer trajectory</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emergent, developed by authors</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grounded theory</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To describe the type of information about CAM that patients with cancer use in their decision-making, to understand why certain types of information about CAM are accepted as evidence by patients with cancer, and to explore the role of scientific evidence in treatment decision-making</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To summarize and review the reasons for CAM use, as well as the sociodemographic and disease characteristics associated with CAM use among patients with cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All (focus on breast and prostate)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States, Canada, Western Europe, Asia, Middle East, Australia, New Zealand</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic review</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 articles</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef and White<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore why and how patients with cancer decide to forgo conventional treatments in favour of alternative treatments, as well as which factors influence this decision</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All; patients who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore cancer patients' experiences with and expectations of the role of family physicians in discussing complementary therapies</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White et al.<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore why men decline conventional prostate cancer treatment and use CAM instead, to understand the role of holistic healing in their care, and to document their recommendations for health care providers</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate; patients who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White and Verhoef <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the role of spirituality in cancer management and decisionmaking for men with prostate cancer who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate; patients who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thematic</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White and Verhoef <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore in depth how sense of control was related to the decision to forgo conventional treatment for prostate cancer and to use CAM therapies for cancer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not stated</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate; patients who declined conventional treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content analysis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1FN1"><p>CAM = complementary and alternative medicine.</p></fn><fn id="T1FN2"><label>*</label><p>Bricolage was described in this paper as the active process in which people engage to construct their unique understanding of CAM, by piecing together ideas that fit with their needs and experiences from diverse practices and models of care.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2b"><title>Emerging concepts in the CAM and cancer decision-making
literature</title><p>Seven unique concepts related to CAM and cancer decision-making emerged through our analysis: decision- making phases, information-seeking and evaluation, decision-making roles, beliefs, contextual factors, decision-making outcomes, and the relationship between CAM and conventional medical decision-making. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> provides a guide to which articles included data relevant to each concept, and the results for each category are briefly synthesized below.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Concepts related to decision-making in the context of complementary and alternative medicine and cancer described in articles included in the review</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decision-making phases</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Information-seeking and evaluation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decision-making roles</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beliefs</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contextual factors</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decision-making outcomes</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relationship between CAM and conventional medical decision-making</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balneaves et al.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balneaves et al.<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bishop and Yardley<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boon et al.<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazier et al.<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom and Tovey<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broom and Tovey<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brown et al.<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chiu et al.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evans et al.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evans et al.<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gray et al.<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hlubocky et al.<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jones et al.<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kakai et al.<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kimby et al.<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Markovic et al.<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Montbriand<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oh and Park<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ohlen et al.<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Owens<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ritvo et al.<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shumay et al.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singh et al.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Truant and Bottorff <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef and White<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verhoef et al.<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White et al.<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White and Verhoef <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White and Verhoef <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2c"><title>Decision-making phases</title><p>The studies included in our review illustrate that CAM-related decision-making does not happen at any finite point in time but rather occurs as a nonlinear, complex, dynamic process, of which therapy choices are one outcome.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Although each person follows his or her own unique CAM decision-making process, we identified 3 specific phases (which we labelled early, mid, and late) that correspond to different events across the cancer trajectory, involving different aims and patterns of information- seeking and evaluation.<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></p><p>The early phase of CAM decision-making begins with the initial diagnosis or a recurrence of cancer.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> It is characterized by feelings of fear and a sense of loss of control.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> A wide range of CAM therapies are typically contemplated<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> during this phase, and the process involves seeking and evaluating information regarding the pros and cons of each therapy and reaching a decision regarding whether or not to use CAM, and if so, which type.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Some people seem to move through this phase quickly and to spend little time, if any, researching CAM options.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Those with past CAM experience seem to fall into this category, as they tend to be less overwhelmed with the amount of available and conflicting information.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Others spend more time consulting a range of information sources to help evaluate the potential of CAM use.<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p><p>The mid phase is best viewed as a maintenance phase, with the aim being to develop a personalized regimen of CAM therapies that fits within the individual's beliefs and needs. Patients seem to transition to this phase of decision-making when they encounter some sort of positive change in their personal context, for example, once they have adapted psychologically to their cancer diagnosis or completed their conventional cancer treatment. CAM therapies used during this phase are directed toward maintaining well-being, controlling the spread of cancer cells, managing the side effects of treatment, boosting the immune system, and preventing or delaying recurrence.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></p><p>The late phase of decision-making includes the same iterative information-gathering and evaluation apparent during the early phase, but there is less urgency, a stronger awareness of CAM, and more comfort with a variety of information sources.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> People seem to transition to this late phase when their conventional treatment ends and they move into survivorship or palliative care.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> During the late phase, patients consider CAM therapies that help to address a variety of aims, including overcoming a sense of loss and abandonment after discharge, maintaining health, prolonging life, or coming to terms with impending death.<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In palliative situations, the patient may re-evaluate CAM regimens that were previously perceived to require too much time, money, and effort.<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>Transitioning between phases seems to correspond to times of crisis or change within the cancer experience<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> that modify perceived consequences or expectations of CAM therapies within cancer treatment.<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Such changes seem to motivate people to revisit their original CAM-related decisions and to renew the process of gathering and evaluating information to help adapt to a new circumstance.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> This transitioning does not appear to represent desperation on the part of patients but, instead, a reasoned approach to critically examining their situation and available options.<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></p></sec><sec id="S2d"><title>Information-seeking and evaluation</title><p>Information-seeking and evaluation are integral components of decision-making, with distinct patterns during each phase. For some people, these activities form a process that begins at diagnosis and continues throughout their cancer journey. Other people begin to seek and evaluate information when they transition between decision-making phases and need to revisit their CAM decisions. People tend to rely on a wide range of information sources, including books, the Internet, mass media, CAM and conventional practitioners, friends and family, and other cancer patients.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Preferred information sources differ depending on the decisionmaking phase, with the broadest range of information sources used in early-phase decision-making, when individuals are exploring their treatment options and learning what types of CAM are available. In subsequent phases, individuals tend to rely on personal experience and the results of medical tests to evaluate whether CAM is helping them to achieve their treatment goals.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></p><p>The process of evaluating information has largely been studied by examining the meaning of evidence when cancer patients make CAM-related decisions. It is clear from our review of this literature that what constitutes high-quality evidence for the safety and effectiveness of CAM varies greatly among individuals<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> and also diverges from the standard applied within evidence-based medicine.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> The type and source of information that individuals accept as evidence seem to depend mostly on underlying beliefs and values, perceived credibility of information, experience with CAM, and stage of disease.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Anxiety, ethnicity, and social support may also play a role.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Within CAM decision-making, information evaluation will play a stronger or weaker role, depending on the level of attention that the individual affords to a given content area and his or her beliefs regarding the potential for use of CAM to modify his or her condition.<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> For example, if someone feels strongly that using herbal medicine can help mitigate the side effects of cancer treatment, and side effects are a great concern for that person, information evaluation becomes an important part of the decision-making process; however, if side effects are not as important an issue for the patient, then information evaluation in this situation is less important.</p></sec><sec id="S2e"><title>Decision-making roles</title><p>Individuals tend to take either an active or a passive role in decision-making, and the role they choose may differ at different points during the decision-making process.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> People who take an active role appear more self-motivated,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> have more self-confidence,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and are more likely to have used CAM before their cancer diagnosis<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> than those who take a passive role. The more active group also embraces a wider range of CAM therapies than the more passive group.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Taking an active or passive role is associated with cancer type and state of illness: those with rare forms of cancer, faster-growing tumours, or advanced disease are more likely to take an active role.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Regardless of whether their role is active or passive, patients with cancer appear to experience CAM decision-making as problematic. Taking an active role often requires going against the socially sanctioned expertise of medical doctors and assuming responsibility for one's own decisions, whereas taking a passive role conflicts with the ideal of individual responsibility for health.<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></p></sec><sec id="S2f"><title>Beliefs</title><p>A range of beliefs influence CAM and cancer decision-making, including beliefs about the causes of cancer,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> treatment mechanisms,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> risks and benefits of CAM use,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> risks and benefits of conventional care,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> available evidence,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> and disease status.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> A lthough it is possible to categorize beliefs in this way, it is more likely that an individual's entire belief system influences the CAM decisionmaking process, such that decisions are generally congruent with the complexity of the belief system. Depending on an individual's particular context at any given time, he or she will prioritize some beliefs over others when making decisions. For example, during active treatment, patients may prioritize their beliefs about treatment mechanisms and risks and benefits of care over their beliefs about the causes of their cancer.</p><p>It is clear, however, that not every person with cancer is explicitly aware of his or her beliefs; furthermore, these beliefs are not static. Current beliefs are informed by a range of factors, including past experiences of the individual<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> or his or her significant others,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> ethnocultural values,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> faith in God,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> and education.<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></p></sec><sec id="S2g"><title>Contextual factors</title><p>Several contextual factors influence the experience of making CAM decisions, including demographic and disease-related factors, social factors, and cultural norms. Relevant demographic and disease-related factors include age,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> geography,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> disease status and active treatment,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> experience with CAM use,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> and income and ability to pay.<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Social factors centre on an individual's interactions with others, including friends and family, health care practitioners, and other patients. Finding validation and support from others appears to be of great value to patients and seems to offer them the confidence to move forward with decisions that feel right for them.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> In some cases, however, support and recommendations from members of a support network can result in feelings of pressure and uncertainty.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Cultural norms have a strong influence on decision-making and appear to reflect a conflict between CAM and biomedicine,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> the limits of biomedicine,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> and perceived harmlessness of many CAM therapies.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p></sec><sec id="S2h"><title>Decision-making outcomes</title><p>The CAM decision-making process contributes to a range of outcomes, including the decision to use or not use CAM, but also several others. The process of making a decision has been documented to empower individuals through more active participation in their own care,<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> which can increase a person's sense of control and thus reduce anxiety and fear.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> CAM decision-making also introduces individuals to different philosophies of healing, healthy lifestyle behaviours, and personal development.<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> However, making decisions about CAM may also be associated with certain difficulties. For example, common outcomes of CAM decision-making include conflict and resistance from clinicians, both of which can contribute to feelings of frustration and anxiety about making the "right" decision.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Furthermore, individuals may describe feeling uncomfortable with the added responsibility and self-accountability that use of CAM can bring.<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p></sec><sec id="S2i"><title>Relationship between CAM and conventional medical
decision-making</title><p>Making decisions about CAM cannot be separated from making decisions about conventional medicine.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> These may seem to be similar processes that occur concurrently<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>; however, depending on the situation, one or the other will take priority.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Furthermore, the goals of both decision- making processes appear to be the same, but an individual's beliefs and values will lead to a choice of either CAM or conventional treatment (or both) to achieve his or her treatment goals.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Synthesis</title><p>An emergent conceptual framework illustrating the relationship among the 7 central concepts is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. In this framework, CAM decisionmaking begins with the diagnosis of cancer. The process encompasses 3 distinct phases, each marked by unique patterns of information-seeking and evaluation, specifically, early-, mid-, and late-phase decision-making. Transitions between phases correspond to changes in health status, a crisis, or other milestones within the cancer trajectory. All decision-making phases are influenced by a myriad of contextual factors, including demographic and disease-related factors, social factors, cultural norms, and personal beliefs about cancer, its causes, and its treatments. Outcomes of the decision-making process include one or possibly multiple CAM decisions over time, and also shifts in perceived sense of control, empowerment, anxiety, and fear, as well as conflict over whether the "right" decision has been made.</p><fig fig-type="Halftone" id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Conceptual framework of the decision-making process for complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) by patients with cancer. Conventional medical-decision making is included in this framework because making decisions about CAM cannot be separated from making decisions about conventional medicine. Social factors, cultural norms, and demographic and disease-related factors constitute the "contextual factors" discussed in the text. Transitions from one phase to another within the decision-making trajectory may occur at times of crisis or milestones, such as the end of conventional treatment and transition to survivorship or palliative care.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-08-54-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Interpretation</title><p>Through this integrative literature review, we have created a conceptual framework for CAM and cancer decision-making that can be used to guide the development of decision-support programs as well as future research in this field. The inclusion of diverse studies representing diverse populations ensures that the framework is comprehensive and therefore broadly applicable to cancer patients who are contemplating treatment options. It illustrates 3 distinct phases within CAM and cancer decision-making, each characterized by different patterns of information-seeking and evaluation. It is also clear that CAM decision-making should not be considered as a process separate from decision-making related to conventional medical care. Beliefs, values, and other social and cultural norms guide all treatment choices, and some patients will require support to articulate and prioritize these factors when making treatment decisions.</p><p>The inclusion of diverse study designs within integrative literature reviews means that such reviews are more susceptible to lack of rigour than are other types of reviews (such as systematic reviews).<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> For example, although our search was extensive, it is possible that we missed some primary studies, especially any published in languages other than English. However, given that we searched multiple databases and scanned reference lists of included articles for additional eligible studies, it is likely that we identified most of the published literature in this field. Furthermore, the reliability of our sampling strategy was enhanced by using pre- specified inclusion and exclusion criteria and by having 2 reviewers screen each potentially relevant article. Data extraction within integrative literature reviews can be especially problematic because of the wide range of variables, theories, and populations examined within diverse primary studies. To provide focus and delineate boundaries for the review, our team met frequently to formulate a clear research purpose and related data-extraction strategy, as well as to discuss the analysis as it was emerging.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Finally, our data analysis strategy was compatible with strategies used to combine diverse data within mixed-methods studies,<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> further supporting the rigour of our review.</p><p>We expect that the results of this review, including the conceptual framework and descriptions of relevant concepts within CAM and cancer decision-making, will be instructive for health care professionals who are supporting patients moving through this complex process. Decisions about CAM use are often characterized by conflict and anxiety,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> perhaps more so in the setting of cancer than other diseases, given the cultural significance of a cancer diagnosis.<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Decision-support programs are needed to promote open dialogue about the use of CAM in cancer care, to direct patients to high-quality information resources, and to support the safe integration of CAM within standard care.<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> This study has helped to identify some key characteristics required of such decision-support programs. Of note, these programs should encompass a variety of strategies to support patients within different decisionmaking phases. They must also acknowledge the variability and complexity of individuals' personal contexts, including beliefs, values, and social roles, which will influence when and how people make treatment decisions. Decision-support programs must also be flexible and adaptive, to account for both active and passive decision-making roles, diversity in preferred information sources, and changing needs and goals throughout the cancer experience. Finally, given that CAM-related decisions are intertwined with decision-making related to conventional medical treatments, it seems reasonable that CAM decision-support programs should be integrated with other programs offered within standard care.</p><p>To date, most of the research in the field of CAM and cancer decision-making has been conceptual and exploratory. This perspective has been crucial to gaining a better understanding of the complexity within CAM decision-making. The integrative review presented here provides a comprehensive understanding of the CAM and cancer decision-making process, including the distinct decision-making phases, roles, and contextual influences. It is now time to move forward with the development and evaluation of theory-based decision-support programs to provide evidenceinformed support for cancer patients in making decisions about CAM and conventional medical treatment. The proposed conceptual framework is a guide to ensure that decision-support programs are responsive to patients' beliefs and preferences and appropriate to their unique needs at different points throughout the cancer trajectory.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p>None declared.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Financial support for this study was provided entirely by a grant from the Lotte &#x00026; John Hecht Memorial Foundation, which had no role in designing the study, interpreting the data, or writing and publishing the report.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We are grateful for the assistance of Heidi Rasmussen, who updated the literature search before the analysis was complete.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottorff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hislop</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Levels of commitment:
exploring complementary therapy use by women with breast
cancer</article-title><source>J Altern Complement Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16813510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guns</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population-
based survey of complementary and alternative medicine
use in men recently diagnosed with prostate cancer</article-title><source>Integr Cancer
Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15035882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molassiotis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernadez-Ortega</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Panteli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of complementary and alternative medicine in cancer
patients: a European survey</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gansler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaw</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Crammer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population-based study of prevalence of complementary methods use by cancer survivors: a report from the American Cancer Society's studies of cancer survivors</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>113</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1048</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsterdam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary
and alternative medicine use among cancer survivors: a population-
based study</article-title><source>J Cancer Surviv</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20924711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maskarinec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumay</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the motivation
for conventional and complementary/alternative medicine use
among men with prostate cancer</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Easthope</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postmodern comsumption and alternative
medications</article-title><source>J Sociol</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell-Griner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McFann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary
and alternative medicine use among adults: United States, 2002</article-title><source>Adv Data</source><year>2004</year><issue>343</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15188733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative cancer care in a US academic cancer centre: the Memorial Sloan&#x02013;Kettering Experience</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl
2</issue><fpage>s108.es68</fpage><lpage>s108.es71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18769574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrative approach to addressing clinical issues in
complementary and alternative medicine in an outpatient oncology
center</article-title><source>Clin J Oncol Nurs</source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16482732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peace</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Manasse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Cavendish Centre for integrated cancer care: assessment of patients' needs and responses</article-title><source>Complement
Ther Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12442821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Truant</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bridging
the gap: decision-making processes of women with breast cancer
using complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)</article-title><source>Support Care
Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective communication about the use of complementary
and integrative medicine in cancer care</article-title><source>J Altern Complement
Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seely</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oneschuk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of natural health products with
biomedical cancer treatments</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>s109.
es81</fpage><lpage>s10.
es6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18769615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug interactions between herbal and prescription
medicines</article-title><source>Drug Saf</source><year>2003</year><volume>26</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14640772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juraskova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegedus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Butow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discussing
complementary therapy use with early-stage breast cancer patients:
exploring the communication gap</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20462858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manderson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary medicine
use by Australian women with gynaecological cancer</article-title><source>Psychooncology</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truant</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottorff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision making related to complementary
therapies: a process of regaining control</article-title><source>Patient Educ Counsel</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors in making the decision to forgo conventional
cancer treatment</article-title><source>Cancer Pract</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12100104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shumay</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maskarinec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotay</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer Research Center
of Hawaii. Why some cancer patients choose complementary
and alternative medicine instead of conventional treatment</article-title><source>J Fam
Pract</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A test of the self-help model and use of complementary
and alternative medicine among Hispanic women during treatment
for breast cancer</article-title><source>Oncol Nurs Forum</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>E42</fpage><lpage>E50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17723972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourguignon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Steeves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine modality use and
beliefs among African American prostate cancer survivors</article-title><source>Oncol
Nurs Forum</source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torraco</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Writing integrative literature reviews: guidelines and examples</article-title><source>Human Resour Dev Rev</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>367</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Knafl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The integrative review: updated methodology</article-title><source>J Adv Nurs</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16268861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristjanson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tataryn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond convention: describing
complementary therapy use by women living with breast cancer</article-title><source>Patient Educ Couns</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14528706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yardley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constructing agency in treatment decisions:
negotiating responsibility in cancer</article-title><source>Health (London)</source><year>2004</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15358899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Westlake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Deber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moineddin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Problem-solving and
decision-making preferences: no difference between complementary
and alternative medicine users and non-users</article-title><source>Complement Ther
Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16150376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Westlake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleshner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of complementary/alternative medicine by men diagnosed
with prostate cancer: prevalence and characteristics</article-title><source>Urology</source><year>2003</year><volume>62</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14624907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer survivors' perceptions of complementary/alternative medicine (CAM): making the decision to use or not to use</article-title><source>Qual Health Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10558372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brazier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moravan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using mixed methods for evaluating
an integrative approach to cancer care: a case study</article-title><source>Integr Cancer
Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intuition, subjectivity, and Le bricoleur: cancer patients' accounts of negotiating a plurality of therapeutic options</article-title><source>Qual
Health Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19638599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tovey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the temporal dimension in cancer patients' experiences of nonbiomedical therapeutics</article-title><source>Qual Health Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tovey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dialectical tension between individuation and depersonalization in cancer patients' mediation of complementary, alternative and biomedical cancer treatments</article-title><source>Sociology</source><year>2007</year><volume>41</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmoreo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Women's decision-making about their health care: views over the life cycle</article-title><source>Patient Educ Couns</source><year>2002</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12477607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barroetavena</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of complementary
and alternative medicine by Chinese individuals living
with cancer in British Columbia</article-title><source>J Complement Integr Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><comment>Article 2</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decisions to use complementary and alternative medicine (CAM)
by male cancer patients: information-seeking roles and types of evidence
used</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Men with cancer: is their use of complementary and alternative
medicine a response to needs unmet by conventional care?</article-title><source>Eur J
Cancer Care</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>525</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Labrecque</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives of cancer survivors interested in unconventional therapies</article-title><source>J Psychosoc Oncol</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3/4</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hlubocky</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratain</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary and
alternative medicine among advanced cancer patients enrolled on
phase I trials: a study of prognosis, quality of life, and preferences for
decision making</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maskarinec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumay</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnic
differences in choices of health information by cancer patients using
complementary and alternative medicine: an exploratory study
with correspondence analysis</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>56</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12560017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimby</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Launs&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Henningsen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Langgaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Choice of unconventional
treatment by patients with cancer</article-title><source>J Altern Complement
Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14499031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montbriand</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision tree model describing alternate health care
choices made by oncology patients</article-title><source>Cancer Nurs</source><year>1995</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7720049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision tree model of the treatment-seeking behaviors
among Korean cancer patients</article-title><source>Cancer Nurs</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottorff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brazier</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of significant
others in complementary and alternative medicine decisions
by cancer patients</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1625</fpage><lpage>1636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16725245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacamano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The patient's motivation in seeking complementary therapies</article-title><source>Patient Educ
Couns</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14560712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilsden</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kania</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the role of evidence in patients' evaluation of complementary therapies: a quality study</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vroegindewey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reasons for
and characteristics associated with complementary and alternative
medicine use among adult cancer patients: a systematic review</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16282504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer patients' expectations of the role of family physicians in communication about complementary therapies</article-title><source>Cancer Prev Control</source><year>1999</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10474765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seeking mind, body and spirit healing&#x02014;why some men with prostate cancer choose CAM (complementary and alternative medicine) over conventional cancer treatments</article-title><source>Integr Med Insights</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21614154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer as part of the journey: the role of spirituality
in the decision to decline conventional prostate cancer treatment
and to use complementary and alternative medicine</article-title><source>Integr
Cancer Ther</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16685076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision-making control: why men decline
treatment for prostate cancer</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15035883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Creswell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Research design: qualitative, quantitative, and mixed
methods</source><year>2009</year><edition>3rd ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks (CA)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receiving bad news: a phenomenological exploration
of the lived experience of receiving a cancer diagnosis</article-title><source>Cancer Nurs</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>E31</fpage><lpage>E39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balneaves</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Truant</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoef</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcino</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Complementary Medicine Education and Outcomes
(CAMEO) program: a foundation for patient and health professional
education and decision support programs</article-title><source>Patient Educ Couns</source><year>2012</year><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22305188</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>