<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">OpenMed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009680</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4085090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-8-e10-e13</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title xml:lang="en">The Sunshine Act: Commercial conflicts of interest and the limits of transparency</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><aff>Mark Wilson is a bioethicist living in Guelph, Ontario, Canada.</aff><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">Mark Wilson, 22 Princeton Place, Guelph ON N1G 3N4; <email xlink:href="markwilson1920@yahoo.com">markwilson1920@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn id="AFN1" fn-type="other"><p>We must create a world in which the best experts are those that are free from commercial influence. And Europe needs legislation along the lines of the US Sunshine Act to combat both real and perceived commercial influence in science and health care.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>Fiona Godlee, editor in chief, BMJ</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e10</fpage><lpage>e13</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Copyright by Societ&#x000e0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country. For more information, please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>Godlee is referring to the Physician Payment Sunshine Act, which became federal law in the United States in January 2012.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The Act requires drug and medical manufacturers who participate in federal programs to report annually on direct payments and other transfers of value made to physicians and teaching hospitals. As part of the disclosure mandated by the Act, information on amounts received by individual physicians will be made available on a publicly accessible website beginning in September 2014.</p><p>The aim of the legislation is to tackle the issue of commercial conflicts of interest (COIs), which has been a source of heated debate in the medical community for well over a decade. Media coverage of commercial conflicts within medicine focused greater public attention on the issue and raised concern about the integrity of medical information.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> In 2009, the US Institute of Medicine weighed in with a report that described commercial COIs within medical practice and education as widespread and often hidden from public view.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The report stressed that financial ties can exert undue influence on physicians' judgments, research, and practice, thus jeopardizing patient care, scientific integrity, and objectivity in education. It recommended that medical education should be free of industry sponsorship and that experts on panels who establish clinical guideline practices be prohibited from having commercial COIs. Both recommendations were intended to ensure greater public trust in medicine.</p><p>Another recommendation was for the implementation of policies that would make financial ties between industry and the medical community more transparent to the public. This particular recommendation was welcomed by Senator Chuck Grassley, co-author of the Sunshine Act and a champion of the view that metaphorical sunshine&#x02014;disclosure&#x02014;is a powerful aid to accountability. Grassley was instrumental in heightening public concern about commercial COIs and the need for greater accountability. He spearheaded investigations that brought financial ties out of the shadows and exposed egregious violations of federal conflict-of-interest reporting requirements by influential physicians in eminent academic institutions.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> These investigations reinforced the perception that commercial COIs were ubiquitous and poorly managed, and that they required better oversight to mitigate their effects.</p><p>Against this backdrop, the Sunshine Act gained political momentum and eventually became law as part of the Affordable Care Act of 2010. Through its requirements for disclosure of commercial COIs, the Act is seen as a tool to empower patients to decide whether physician prescribing patterns are influenced by financial interests in the pharmaceutical and medical device industries.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>There are no signs that any legislative measures along the lines of the Sunshine Act are imminent in Canada, although there have been calls for legislators in Australia,<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> the United Kingdom,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and the European Union to follow the United States' lead.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Despite this international interest in the Sunshine Act, psychological, institutional, and behavioural research suggests that this kind of legislation, with its stress on transparency, will not effectively combat commercial COIs. Indeed, there is good reason to believe that the Sunshine Act will only preserve the status quo.</p><p>Various researchers have examined the unconscious character of bias and the limits of disclosure as a standalone measure to address commercial COIs.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Even though the view that disclosure is a necessary but insufficient means of combatting commercial conflicts has gained a toehold in the medical literature,<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> it has never gained traction in public policy. The issue over mitigating the influence of commercial interests was framed primarily around disclosure:<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> whether to disclose a commercial COI; what kind and how much information should be disclosed; whether disclosure should be mandatory; and whether disclosure of a commercial COI was too intrusive.<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Public attention became fixed on ensuring commercial COIs did not remain hidden. Meanwhile, scant attention was paid to the unconscious nature of bias, the potential for bias to become institutionally embedded, and its ability to compromise the integrity of medical data. Ironically, the stress on disclosure hid the real problem: the existence of commercial conflicts and their consequences.<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> In short, a preoccupation with disclosure hijacked the debate and sidetracked the public interest. Jerome Kassirer, former chief editor of the <italic>New England Journal of Medicine</italic>, critiqued this fixation on "the wrong problem"<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> and expressed concern that the need to eliminate commercial conflicts, especially from oversight bodies that assess the integrity of medical data, was being excluded as a public policy option.<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p><p>This concern was shared by analysts in other sectors who examined the unconscious nature of bias and the ineffectiveness of disclosing commercial COIs.<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Decades of market scandals reveal a history of compromised auditor independence arising from consultancies with corporate clients.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Wall Street's attempt to manage the problem by disclosing these conflicts failed to prevent further scandals involving tainted accounting audits. Calls to eliminate commercial conflicts altogether<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> fell on deaf political ears, partly because of lobbying by powerful interest groups.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Then emerged a fear that more "predictable surprises" would ensue&#x02014;that is, situations in which the gravity of avoidable crises is underestimated in order to satisfy economic and social policies.<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> On Wall Street this fear was borne out by the 2008 global financial crisis, in which auditors with consulting relations with major banks signed off on overstated bank balance sheets and fictitious earning statements. Calls to end these commercial conflicts and for genuine auditor independence continue.<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p><p>The relevance of the Wall Street experience was not lost on members of the medical, business, and bioethics academic communities who examined the unconscious nature of bias in the context of commercial COI and institutional corruption; for instance, a public policy symposium held at Harvard University examined the cognitive mechanisms of bias and the sometimes paradoxical effects of disclosure.<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> However, such subleties were ignored by the framers of the Sunshine Act, despite the fact that disclosure has been demonstrated to be a flawed accountability tool on Wall Street.</p><p>What the Sunshine Act achieves is to shift the burden of managing the problem of commercial conflicts onto the shoulders of a powerless consumer public.<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> With respect to health care&#x02014;and the science that underpins it&#x02014;the public lacks the specialized training, practice, and knowledge required to effectively assess the integrity of medical data and the various contexts in which it is embedded. And simply disclosing a commercial COI to the public does not provide the necessary skills to assess its implications. There is a good reason why medical expertise is required to assess the integrity of medical information. The problem is that independence and objectivity can, and have been, compromised by commercial COIs.<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In short, the Sunshine Act fails to fix the problem;<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> instead, it mythologizes transparency.</p><p>This is not surprising, given the dominant political approach to the problem. Systemic commercial COIs continue to flourish on Wall Street, despite a near market collapse.<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> With this in mind, it is difficult to gauge what kind of tipping point will rally politicians to help turn the tide in medicine. Furthermore, it is not by chance that the Sunshine Act mirrors the way US politicians tackle the issue of financial campaign contributions from special interest groups. Public disclosure of campaign contributions plays a key role in managing the issue.<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> The Sunshine Act is symptomatic of a self-serving political culture that lacks the will to end commercial conflicts.</p><p>Until politicians end their own commercial COIs, the Sunshine Act will likely remain the governance order of the day. The public will have to shoulder the regulatory weight and negative consequences of an unresolved problem, just as it bailed out the banks during the financial crisis while lacking the power to curb commercial conflicts on Wall Street. As a political response to a systemic problem, the Sunshine Act echoes the marketing mantra that "consumers know best" and that the market is the best information medium and solution to public policy issues.<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> The result is a false sense of public empowerment and a pseudo accountability that sustains the status quo.</p><p>Greater transparency in medicine should be welcomed. A world in which the best experts in science and health care are free of commercial influence is surely desirable. But the Sunshine Act fails to disinfect a medical and political landscape awash in commercial conflicts. Consumers beware: the predictable surprises are becoming ever more common.</p></body><back><ack><p>I thank David Healy, John Hoey, and Andrew Lugg for their comments.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="gov"><comment>Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe. Excerpts of remarks by Fiona Godlee, Editor-in-Chief of the British Medical Journal, during an exchange of views in Paris with PACE's Health Committee on the handling of the H1N1 pandemic, 4 June 2010. PACE News. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://assembly.coe.int/asp/apfeaturesmanager/defaultArtView.asp?ID=918">http://assembly.coe.int/asp/apfeaturesmanager/defaultArtView.asp?ID=918</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="gov"><comment>Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010, HR 3590, 111th
Congress (2010).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How tightly do ties between doctor and drug company
bind?</article-title><source>New York Times</source><year>2004</year><month>7</month><day>24</day><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://psychrights.org/research/Digest/Science4Sale/NYTimesTiesBetween-DoctorandDrugCompany.htm">http://psychrights.org/research/Digest/Science4Sale/NYTimesTiesBetween-DoctorandDrugCompany.htm</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Institute of Medicine
</collab><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Conflict of interest in medical research, education,
and practice</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The National
Academies Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grassley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Disclosure of drug company payments to doctors</source><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.grassley.senate.gov/about/Disclosure-of-Drug-Company-Payments-to-Doctors.cfm">www.grassley.senate.gov/about/Disclosure-of-Drug-Company-Payments-to-Doctors.cfm</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>CMS implements the "Sunshine Act." COI SMART blog
[Internet]</source><year>2013</year><month>2</month><day>20</day><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coismart.com/blog/index.php/2013/02/cms-implements-the-sunshine-act/">www.coismart.com/blog/index.php/2013/02/cms-implements-the-sunshine-act/</ext-link> (accessed
2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Petition to ACCC on Medicine Australia Code authorisation.
GoPetition 2012 [Internet]</source><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gopetition.com/petitions/petition-to-accc-on-medicines-australia-code-authorisat.html">www.gopetition.com/petitions/petition-to-accc-on-medicines-australia-code-authorisat.html</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godlee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Sunshine Act for Europe</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2011</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>d6593</fpage><lpage>d6593</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Letting the sunshine in on doctor-pharma relationships</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2011</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>d6459</fpage><lpage>d6459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21990283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social psychology of ordinary unethical
behavior</article-title><source>Soc Justice Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>D M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coming clean but playing
dirtier: the shortcomings of disclosure as a solution to conflicts of
interest</article-title><source>Conflicts of interest: challenges and solutions in business, law,
medicine, and public policy</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chugh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bounded ethicality as a psychological
barrier to recognizing conflicts of interest</article-title><source>Conflicts of interest: challenges
and solutions in business, law, medicine, and public policy</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soule</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing ethical performance in organizations: insights
from the corporate world</article-title><source>Cleve Clin J Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>S73</fpage><lpage>S76</lpage><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccjm.org/content/74/Suppl_2/S73.full.pdf">www.ccjm.org/content/74/Suppl_2/S73.full.pdf</ext-link> (accessed
2013 Dec 10).</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17471621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vries</surname><given-names>R</given-names><prefix>De</prefix></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why disclosure?</article-title><source>J Gen Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1831613/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1831613/</ext-link> (accessed 2013).</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16918750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassirer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicine's obsession with disclosure of financial conflicts: fixing the wrong problem</article-title><source>Science and the media: Delgado's brave bulls and the ethics of scientific disclosure</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disclosure of physician incentives: do
practices satisfy purposes?</article-title><source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10916969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spevick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Should clinician-researchers disclose financial incentives
to patients?</article-title><source>Virtual Mentor [Internet]</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><issue>10</issue><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://virtualmentor.ama-assn.org/2002/10/jdsc1-0210.html">http://virtualmentor.ama-assn.org/2002/10/jdsc1-0210.html</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusinak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A trial of disclosing physicians' financial incentives to patients</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>166</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16567600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Resnik</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspective: disclosing hidden sources of funding</article-title><source>Acad
Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>84</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stossel</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Has the hunt for conflicts of interest gone too far? Yes</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2008</year><volume>336</volume><issue>7642</issue><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18309999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kassirer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commentary: disclosure's failings: what is the alternative?</article-title><source>Acad Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>84</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>1181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetlock</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanlu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reports of solving the
conflicts of interest in auditing are highly exaggerated</article-title><source>Acad Manage
Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetlock</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanlu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conflicts of interest
and the case of auditor independence: moral seduction and strategic
issue cycling</article-title><source>Acad Manage Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Predictable surprises</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harvard
Business School Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><source>The challenge of auditor independence
[hearing testimony]</source><comment>United States Securities and Exchange Commission, 2000 Jul 26. Sesson 8. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sec.gov/rules/proposed/s71300/testimony/loewen1a.htm">www.sec.gov/rules/proposed/s71300/testimony/loewen1a.htm</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Take on the street: what Wall Street and corporate America don't want you to know; what you can do to fight back</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Political strategies used by the
US public accounting profession during auditor liability reform: the
case of the Private Securities Litigation Reform Act of 1995</article-title><source>J Account
Public Pol</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>457</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>Predictable surprise</article-title><source>Wikipedia</source><year>2013</year><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Predictable_surprise">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Predictable_surprise</ext-link> (2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Financial crisis and the silence of the auditors</article-title><source>Account Org
Soc</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><issue>6&#x02013;7</issue><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>873</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is it time for auditor independence yet?</article-title><source>Account Org Soc</source><year>2011</year><volume>36</volume><issue>4&#x02013;5</issue><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>312</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>The scientific basis of conflicts of interest:
the role of implicit cognition</source><year>2011</year><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ethics.harvard.edu/component/content/article/40-general-content/166-korn-symposium">www.ethics.harvard.edu/component/content/article/40-general-content/166-korn-symposium</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economics behaving badly</article-title><source>New York Times</source><year>2010</year><month>7</month><day>14</day><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/07/15/opinion/15loewenstein.html?_r=0">www.nytimes.com/2010/07/15/opinion/15loewenstein.html?_r=0</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Healey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pharmagedon</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Berkely and Los Angeles</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of California
Press</publisher-name><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>159</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why we can't trust clinical guidelines</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2013</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>f3830</fpage><lpage>f3830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23771225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Deadly medicines and organised crime: how big pharma
has corrupted health care</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Radcliffe Publishing</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dark side of the sun</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2011</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>d7024</fpage><lpage>d7024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22046012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zweig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conflict of interest? Moi?</article-title><source>Wall Street J</source><year>2012</year><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10000872396390443493304578038811945287932.html">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10000872396390443493304578038811945287932.html</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Dec 10).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Briffault</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Campaign finance disclosure 2.0</article-title><source>Election Law J: Rules
Polit Policy</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>303</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Science-Mart: privatizing American science</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>