<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">OpenMed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25237405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4161500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-7-e94-e97</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title xml:lang="en">Prelude to a systematic review of activity-based funding of hospitals: potential effects on cost, quality, access, efficiency, and equity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>Karen S.</given-names></name><aff>Karen S. Palmer is an Adjunct Professor in the Faculty of Health Sciences and the Faculty of Science, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, British Columbia.</aff><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Danielle</given-names></name><aff>Danielle Martin is Vice-President of Medical Affairs and Health System Solutions at Women's College Hospital and an Assistant Professor in the Department of Family and Community Medicine and the Institute of Health Policy, Management and Evaluation, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario.</aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>Gordon</given-names></name><aff>Gordon Guyatt is a Professor in the Department of Clinical Epidemiology &#x00026; Biostatistics, McMaster University, Hamilton, Ontario.</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><email xlink:href="kpalmer@sfu.ca">kpalmer@sfu.ca</email></corresp><fn id="AFN1" fn-type="con"><p>Karen Palmer wrote the first draft. Karen Palmer, Danielle Martin, and Gordon Guyatt contributed to the article, revised it critically for important intellectual content, and gave final approval of the version submitted for publication. Karen Palmer and Gordon Guyatt will act as guarantors for the manuscript.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>10</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e94</fpage><lpage>e97</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Copyright by Societ&#x000e0; Italiana di Otorinolaringologia e Chirurgia Cervico-Facciale</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives License, which permits for noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any digital medium, provided the original work is properly cited and is not altered in any way. For details, please refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The Canadian approach to funding hospitals may be on the verge of a monumental change. Until recently, hospital funding has been based predominantly on global budgets, but health care system decision-makers throughout the country are now seriously considering&#x02014; and some are already adopting&#x02014;an alternative funding model referred to as activity-based funding (ABF).</p><p>In contrast with global budgeting, ABF pays hospitals per episode of care for each patient served. In simple terms, the money follows the patient. Under this system, hospital services are classified prospectively into clinically meaningful "bundles" of care that use similar levels of resources. These bundles take into account patient characteristics such as diagnosis and complexity, along with anticipated volume and intensity of care. Different jurisdictions use various terms to describe these bundles of services; for example, they might be called "diagnosis-related groups" in the United States and "health-resource groups" or "case-mix groups" in Canada.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Various costing methods are used to set a "price" for the bundle of services provided to each patient during a hospital stay.</p><p>The historical roots of ABF lie in the US health care system. In the late 1970s, rising health care costs in the United States coupled with economic stagnation forced policy-makers to investigate financing reforms for Medicare (the publicly funded program for patients aged 65 and older). Starting in 1983, the government implemented a prospective system of hospital payment based on DRGs; rather than simply paying hospitals whatever they charged to treat Medicare patients, the new model paid hospitals a predetermined, set rate based on the patient's diagnosis.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Since then, other countries have adopted, and adapted, this approach as the basis for all or part of their hospital funding systems.</p><p>In Canada, where reductions in government revenues are spurring a desire to "bend the cost curve" in health care, ministries of health are "focusing more on efficiency, value for money, and accountability"<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> while they simultaneously look for ways to increase access to hospital care and maintain quality of care.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> ABF has captured the imagination of some policy-makers and advocates as one potential component of hospital reform.</p><p>Opinion is divided within the Canadian health care policy community as to whether ABF would help us achieve any of the putative benefits originally achieved in the United States and in other nations that subsequently adopted variations on the ABF theme, or whether the risks would outweigh the benefits.</p><p>What are those alleged benefits? Enthusiasts point to evidence that ABF can reduce costs per episode of care or improve efficiency,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> reduce length of stay,<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> and reduce wait times;<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> they also claim that a culture change, by which patients are seen not as cost centres but as as revenue generators,<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> is needed in Canadian health care. To elaborate, by fostering competition for patients between hospitals, ABF theoretically provides hospitals with financial incentives to increase efficiency. Under ABF, hospitals retain any surplus in funding above their expenditures per case, but must absorb any losses if expenditures exceed reimbursement. The other potential benefits arising from these financial incentives include stimulating productivity<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> (i.e., increasing patient throughput, leading to improved access and reduced wait times), increasing transparency<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> and accountability in hospital spending, and moderating cost growth.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></p><p>But what about the potential adverse consequences of introducing ABF? The detractors of this funding method point to evidence that it leads to the rapid discharge of sick patients into community settings that may be unprepared to care for them,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> provides an incentive to "up-code" and thus "game" the system,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> creates a perverse focus on "profitable" over "unprofitable" patients and procedures, with negative implications for equitable access to care,<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> and increases overall costs to the health care system<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> in the absence of global caps on spending.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p>Under ABF, the incentive to spend less, on average, per patient could encourage the premature discharge of sick patients from hospital, which might increase rates of preventable readmissions<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> and of postdischarge mortality. Spending less per patient might also compromise the quality of care patients receive in hospital or lead hospitals to eliminate unprofitable services (such as trauma units<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) or, conversely, in order to "make a profit," to unnecessarily admit and potentially overtreat patients who could otherwise be cared for as outpatients.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> There is also a concern that a "cherrypicking" or "cream-skimming" effect could reduce equitable access to care if hospitals cater preferentially to profitable patients.<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Similarly, since more treatmentintensive case-mix groups warrant a higher reimbursement rate, there is an incentive to selectively code patients as being sicker than they really are.<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Any efficiencies gained through ABF may be undermined by the increased administrative spending required to cope with coding and monitoring demands, as well as by the transaction costs of implementing ABF. Another worry is that by breaking care into "saleable units"<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> ABF will facilitate the introduction of private, profit-driven delivery of care.</p><p>Both ABF enthusiasts and detractors can point to evidence to support their claims, and each line of reasoning follows a logical narrative that can be persuasive to policy-makers. However, in making their case, each group selects the international experiences that are consistent with their narrative, rather than attempting to understand the evidence as a whole.</p><p>British Columbia and Ontario are leading the Canadian movement toward ABF as an alternative to, or in combination with, global budgets. Results from a British Columbia study published early in 2013 indicated that one anticipated benefit, increasing patient through-put, had not been achieved: the researchers found "no intervention effect of the ABF reform on the changes in surgical volumes over time in all five health authorities."<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> Such findings raise questions about whether the supposed benefits of ABF play out when this model is implemented in the real world.</p><p>The international literature on ABF consists of research studies and non-systematic reviews<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> without, so far, a single systematic review. Health care researchers are convinced that "systematic reviews of research evidence constitute a more appropriate source of research evidence for decision-making than the latest or most heavily publicized research study."<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Policy- and decision-makers should rely on robust evidence to make well-informed decisions about how best to finance and deliver health care. "Evidence-informed" policy-making is characterized by the "systematic and transparent access to, and appraisal of, evidence as an input into the policy-making process."<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Yet, in the absence of a thorough and systematic approach to understanding the impact of ABF on cost, quality, access, efficiency, and equity across multiple health care systems and at different times, Canadian policy-makers continue to make decisions based upon only selected evidence. The limited reviews available may well reflect biased selections of the available evidence.</p><p>Having established the pressing need to review all the evidence available about ABF, in March 2012 our research team launched a systematic review to inform Canadian policy-makers about how this funding model affects health care systems around the world. Our systematic search of Canadian and international evidence has demonstrated that there is no shortage of published literature addressing ABF. Of the more than 16 000 potentially eligible titles and abstracts we have screened, 261 studies, representing 64 countries (either singly or in aggregate), provide data on at least one of the cost, quality, access, efficiency, and equity outcomes of interest to our research team. We are now in the process of analyzing data from the eligible studies most germane to the Canadian context.</p><p>This commentary is intended to alert decision-makers to the upcoming release of a series of papers based on our systematic review of ABF, in the hope that there will be an appetite for this knowledge at a time when they are being asked to make decisions in its absence.</p><p>It would be a shame if Canadian governments moved to ABF only to find later that, for instance, they obtain none of the putative benefits but instead observe premature hospital discharges to an unprepared posthospital care system and subsequent adverse health consequences to patients. It will be particularly regrettable if, armed with a systematic review of the evidence, they could have foreseen such an unfortunate outcome of their policy experiment. It would be similarly unfortunate for governments to abandon ABF only to learn that the benefits do in fact outweigh the harms. We simply don't know yet which way the evidence will lean.</p><p>Our systematic review will soon provide a more robust evidence base to better inform decision-makers. Until then, it would be imprudent to rush to judgment about the effects ABF may, or may not, have on Canada's health care system. We look forward to releasing our results in the near future and encourage governments to consider the implications of our review in their decisions about hospital funding reforms.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p>None declared.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This project is being funded by a Knowledge Synthesis Grant (priority area: evidence-informed health care renewal) from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We acknowledge the contribution to our research of all other team members: Arnav Agarwal (abstraction), Thomas Agoritsas (screening, abstraction, methodology), Neera Bhatnagar (literature search), Andrew Bresnahan (abstraction), Irfan Dhalla (initial study co-conception and co-design), Stephen Duckett (methodology), Bob Evans (economics), Afeez Hazzan (abstraction), Rebecca Jeffery (abstraction), John Lavis (knowledge transfer and exchange), Arnaud Merglen (abstraction), Ashley Miller (screening, abstraction), Sohail Mulla (screening, abstraction), Ahmed Negm (abstraction), Taryn Scott (research coordination, screening, abstraction), Reed Siemieniuk (abstraction), John You (methodology).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Canadian Doctors for Medicare
</collab><source>Activity-based funding in Canadian
hospitals and other surgical facilities</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Doctors for
Medicare</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.canadiandoctorsformedicare.ca/Issues/abf-bulletins.html">www.canadiandoctorsformedicare.ca/Issues/abf-bulletins.html</ext-link> (accessed 2012 Jul 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origins, development, and passage of Medicare's revolutionary prospective payment system</article-title><source>J Hist Med Allied Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Canadian Institute for Health Information
</collab><source>Health care in Canada
2009: a decade in review</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Institute</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://secure.cihi.ca/free_products/HCIC_2009_Web_e.pdf">https://secure.cihi.ca/free_products/HCIC_2009_Web_e.pdf</ext-link> 
(accessed 2013 Jul 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Canadian Institute for Health Information, Activity-Based Funding Unit
</collab><source>A primer on activity-based funding</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Institute</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/pdf/internet/primer_activity_based_fund_en">www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/pdf/internet/primer_activity_based_fund_en</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi&#x000f8;rn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnussen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How different are hospitals' responses to a financial reform? The impact on efficiency of activitybased financing</article-title><source>Health Care Manag Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>2010</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20402278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lur&#x000e5;s</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of activity-based financing
on hospital length of stay for elderly patients suffering from
heart diseases in Norway</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23651910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labrie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><source>Activity-based hospital funding: we've waited long enough</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Montreal (QC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Montreal Economic Institute</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iedm.org/files/note0612_en.pdf"> www.iedm.org/files/note0612_en.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Sep 16).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitikainen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorvatn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hvenegaard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introducing activity-
based financing: a review of experience in Australia, Denmark,
Norway and Sweden</article-title><source>Research Paper 30</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>York (UK)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Centre for Health
Economics</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.york.ac.uk/media/che/documents/papers/researchpapers/rp30_introducing_activity-based_financing.pdf">www.york.ac.uk/media/che/documents/papers/researchpapers/rp30_introducing_activity-based_financing.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Sep 15).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Geissler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quentin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Diagnosis-related
groups in Europe: moving towards transparency, efficiency and quality
in hospitals</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Berkshire (UK)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization on behalf of
European Observatory on Health Systems and Policies, Open University
Press, McGraw-Hill</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Canadian Institute for Health Information
</collab><source>Overview of activity-
based funding</source><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Institute</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/internet/EN/tabbedcontent/health+system+performance/health+fundingactivity+based+funding/cihi008054">www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/internet/EN/tabbedcontent/health+system+performance/health+fundingactivity+based+funding/cihi008054</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Below</surname><given-names>G</given-names><prefix>von</prefix></name></person-group><article-title>The implementation of DRG-based hospital
reimbursement in Switzerland: a population-based perspective</article-title><source>Health Res Policy Syst</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20950481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Canadians should beware of Americans bearing "activity-based funding."</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Toronto (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Healthcare Network</publisher-name><comment>Available 
from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.canadianhealthcarenetwork.ca/healthcaremanagers/discussions/opinion/beware-of-americans-bearing-activity-based-funding-19897">www.canadianhealthcarenetwork.ca/healthcaremanagers/discussions/opinion/beware-of-americans-bearing-activity-based-funding-19897</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Sep 15).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newhouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do unprofitable patients face access problems?</article-title><source>Health
Care Financ Rev</source><year>1989</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10313456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Repin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><source>Reviewing the potential roles of financial
incentives for funding healthcare in Canada</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian
Foundation for Healthcare Improvement</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cfhi-fcass.ca/publicationsandresources/researchreports/ArticleView/12-12-21/bec64e56-ce47-43c9-b05c-98186051731d.aspx">www.cfhi-fcass.ca/publicationsandresources/researchreports/ArticleView/12-12-21/bec64e56-ce47-43c9-b05c-98186051731d.aspx</ext-link> 
(accessed 2013 Sep 16).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno-Serra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>System-wide impacts of hospital payment
reforms: evidence from Central and Eastern Europe and Central Asia</article-title><source>Policy Research Working Paper 4987</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Washington (DC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The World
Bank</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incidence of adverse medical outcomes under prospective
payment</article-title><source>Econometrica</source><year>1995</year><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Civil</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Talucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DRG reimbursement for trauma: the demise of the trauma center
(the use of ISS grouping as an early predictor of total hospital cost)</article-title><source>J Trauma</source><year>1988</year><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3135419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do AR-DRGs adequately
describe the trauma patient episode in New South Wales,
Australia?</article-title><source>HIM J</source><year>2011</year><volume>40</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospective payment: The next big policy disappointment?</article-title><source>Health Aff</source><year>1984</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Callea</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vittadini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of upcoding,
cream skimming and readmissions on the Italian hospitals efficiency:
A population-based investigation</article-title><source>Econ Model</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>821</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stannigel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayatepek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoehn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of the
introduction of diagnosis related group systems on the distribution
of admission weights in very low birthweight infants</article-title><source>Arch Dis Child
Fetal Neonatal Ed</source><year>2011</year><volume>96</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>F186</fpage><lpage>F189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21037282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dafny</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do hospitals respond to price changes?</article-title><source>NBER Working
Paper Series no. 9972</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge (MA)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic
Research</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w9972.pdf?new_window=1">www.nber.org/papers/w9972.pdf?new_window=1</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Sep 16).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolhandler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Himmelstein</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competition in a publicly funded
healthcare system</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2007</year><volume>335</volume><issue>7630</issue><fpage>1126</fpage><lpage>1129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18048539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiping</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Repin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity based funding in
British Columbia: Changes in activity? [Abstract G3.4]</article-title><conf-name>Canadian Association
for Health Services and Policy Research Conference</conf-name><conf-date>2013 May 28&#x0fffd;30</conf-date><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cahspr.ca/web/uploads/conference/2013-05-28_Book_of_Abstracts_2013.pdf">www.cahspr.ca/web/uploads/conference/2013-05-28_Book_of_Abstracts_2013.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 2).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinkaid</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Beyond the hospital walls:
Activity-based funding versus integrated health care reform</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Vancouver
(BC)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives</publisher-name><comment>Available from: 
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.policyalternatives.ca/sites/default/files/uploads/publications/BCOffice/2012/01/CCPA-BC_ABF_2012.pdf">www.policyalternatives.ca/sites/default/files/uploads/publications/BC%20Office/2012/01/CCPA-BC_ABF_2012.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 2).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab collab-type="author">
Canadian Institute for Health Information
</collab><source>Evaluating the impact of
activity-based funding on health system performance</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Institute</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/pdf/internet/EVALUATING_IMPACT_ABF_EN">www.cihi.ca/CIHI-ext-portal/pdf/internet/EVALUATING_IMPACT_ABF_EN</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 11).</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospital payment mechanisms: An overview and options
for Canada</article-title><source>Series on Cost Drivers and Health System Efficiency:
Paper 4</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa (ON)</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Health Services Research Foundation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;kkinen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Or</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paying for hospital
care: The experience with implementing activity-based funding
in European countries</article-title><source>Health Econ Policy Law</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22221929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden-Biddle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards
systematic reviews that inform healthcare management and
policy-making</article-title><source>J Health Serv Res Policy</source><year>2005</year><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16053582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fretheim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Support tools for evidenceinformed
health policymaking (STP) I: What is evidence-informed
policymaking?</article-title><source>Health Res Policy Syst</source><year>2009</year><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S1</lpage><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health-policy-systems.com/content/pdf/1478-4505-7-S1-s1.pdf">www.health-policy-systems.com/content/pdf/1478-4505-7-S1-s1.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 2013 Jul 2).</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018099</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>