<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20101292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2801914</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-01-e52-54</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The media-medicine mix: quality concerns in medical reporting</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>Alan KE</given-names></name><bio><p>Alan Cassels is a researcher in the School of Health Information Sciences, University of Victoria, Victoria, BC.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Alan Cassels, 423 Stannard Avenue, Victoria BC V8S 3M6; (250) 361-3120; <email>cassels@uvic.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e52</fpage><lpage>e54</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/index.php/om/article/view/54"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Many people hear about medical discoveries for the first time through popular media. Newspapers, magazines, television and the Internet play an increasingly crucial role in communicating information about health issues and informing the public about research findings and new treatments.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Good medical journalism provides accurate, balanced reports and important contextual information, helps to set appropriate expectations on the part of consumers, informs the larger medical community, and thus arguably provides a vital public service. By the same token, poor medical journalism can exaggerate or oversimplify an issue, unnecessarily inflating expectations of patients and providers and putting increasing strain on the physician&#x02013;patient relationship.</p><p>The importance of the role played by health journalism is reflected in the findings of a 1999 survey of Canadian general practitioners; of the 250 physicians surveyed, 75% thought that health-related news reporting is beneficial because it prompts patients to ask important questions and otherwise learn more about their health.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> However, almost two thirds of survey respondents stated that journalists should do better job of reporting on health issues. This concern with the quality of medical reporting stemmed from many documented problems, such as stories that lacked complete information, especially concerning the quality of evidence, and that selectively reported benefits, harms and costs of treatment. Other problems are evident; for example, studies in several countries have found that media stories often do not mention the financial ties between study groups or experts and the manufacturers of the treatment in question, although this information provides vital context to a new study.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Such concerns have led to recent calls for more direct and honest reporting of trial results.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref></p><p>Quality and comprehensiveness of health technology coverage by the lay media are important for individual patients and society as a whole.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Preliminary reports can set the tone for subsequent news stories; because media coverage influences perceptions of both consumers and health care professionals, it can affect demand (positively or negatively) for particular health treatments, which in turn can have an impact on public decision-making, shaping public debate around access to new therapies through drug licensing, subsidized payments and other means.</p><p>For example, in 2005 new studies of trastuzumab (Herceptin) announced a breakthrough in treatment for women with breast cancers that expressed the HER2 gene.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> Initial reporting in Canada focused on perceived benefits of the treatment. This was soon followed by stories about patient access to the treatment, the cost of Herceptin (estimated at CDN$35,000 to CDN$45,000) and the dilemmas faced by physicians and patients who were not able to access it. Despite some media attention to the limited benefits offered by trastuzumab compared with existing treatment,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> dozens of media stories over the next 6 months created further controversy and put pressure on provincial health plans and cancer agencies to speed up access to the drug, without waiting for more robust scientific review. In July 2005 British Columbia relented, announcing that it would pay for trastuzumab therapy. Ironically, this occurred one month before the drug's maker, Genentech, issued a warning of significant cardiac toxicity related to its use.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></p><p>Some of the hype related to new treatments is driven by organizations, companies, universities and research groups promoting their research and attempting to get favourable coverage from major media outlets. This leads to a general tendency to over-promote new treatments. For example, a 2003 study analyzing the content of 1,203 American newspapers found that 20% of all examined newspaper articles about common neurologic conditions contained medical errors or exaggerated the treatment's effectiveness.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></p><p>This may also lead to reports giving inadequate attention to negative findings of studies. Some colleagues and I looked at the coverage in North American newspapers of the Antihypertensive and Lipid-Lowering Treatment to Prevent Heart Attack Trial (ALLHAT) trial and found that while 98% (47 of 48) accurately captured a single key message &#x02013; that diuretics, calcium-channel blockers and ACE inhibitors are equivalent in preventing death from heart failure and non-fatal heart attacks &#x02013; only half reported the increased risk of stroke with ACE-inhibitors, and only half conveyed the increased risk of heart failure with calcium-channel blockers (both compared to diuretics).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> The implications for public health and the health care system of failing to disclose these health outcomes is potentially very significant, given the widespread use of these drugs and the fact that ACE-inhibitors and calcium-channel blockers are up to 20 times more expensive than diuretics.</p><p>News coverage of drug treatments can also overemphasize negative aspects of a study's findings, at the risk of engendering further irrational drug use. A recent example was the reporting and subsequent market withdrawal of phenylpropanolamine, an additive in cough preparations and appetite suppressants. A news article in BMJ reported that the "risk of haemorrhagic stroke was found to be as much as 15 times higher in those who had taken appetite suppressants in the three days before the stroke."<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> What this article and subsequent media follow-up failed to report was that the absolute risk of stroke in those women remained extremely rare: between one in 3.26 million and 1 in 107,000.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></p><p>Many of those working within medical journalism are aware of these concerns. Andr&#x000e9; Picard, a leading medical reporter at the Toronto Globe and Mail, elucidates some key problems with quality medical reporting: a lack of reporter skepticism, weak evidence to support health claims, the influence of commercialism and the use of single sources. He also points to a factors such as the lack of full-time health journalists within news organizations, the failure to devote sufficient space to cover an issue properly and the use of untrained journalists.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></p><p>A major and sustained improvement in reporting standards needs to start with improving the education of journalists and the public on what qualities to look for in news reports about new treatments. Recent initiatives in researching, monitoring and evaluating medical coverage aim to start this education process. In the last 3 years <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediadoctor.org/">Media Doctor Australia</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediadoctor.ca/">Media Doctor Canada</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthnewsreview.org/">Health News Reviews</ext-link> in the United States have used teams of experts to scan, review and post ratings of hundreds of health treatment stories according to similar criteria for quality. Recognizing the need to build better capacity in science journalism and biomedical communications, the Canadian Institute for Health Research (CIHR), the leading government funder of health research in Canada, recently announced a Health Research Communications Award to support Canadian journalism or communications students who are pursuing a career in health research communications.</p><p>These initiatives can start none too soon. Consumer awareness of medical technologies and treatments is a significant policy concern for drug plan managers and provincial health ministries, as a (mis)informed public places pressure on government for the rapid uptake of often expensive and sometimes inadequately studied medical technologies and drugs. Although better medical journalism will no doubt also require changes to the culture of media companies and the behaviour of companies and researchers with a vested interest in generating positive coverage, the public, researchers, and health care professionals should welcome current efforts to improve the quality of health news reporting.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: Alan Cassels is the founder and project leader of Media Doctor Canada, which is funded through the Office of Consumer Affairs at Industry Canada. He is remunerated for coordinating reviewers and administering the project.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>E J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarczyk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tastad</surname><given-names>P L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of the lay press in the transmission of medical knowledge to the scientific community.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1991</year><month>10</month><day>17</day><volume>325</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1891034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Minozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass media interventions: effects on health services utilization.</article-title><source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source><year>2002</year><issue>1</issue><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane.org/reviews/en/ab000389.html">http://www.cochrane.org/reviews/en/ab000389.html</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Media coverage of health stories often inaccurate, MDs report.</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>1999</year><month>8</month><day>24</day><volume>161</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>361</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10478152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Merrilee A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintzes</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><name><surname>Lexchin</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>James P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drugs in the news: an analysis of Canadian newspaper coverage of new prescription drugs.</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2003</year><month>4</month><day>29</day><volume>168</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12719316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moynihan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross-Degnan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soumerai</surname><given-names>S B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coverage by the news media of the benefits and risks of medications.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><month>6</month><day>1</day><volume>342</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>1650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200006013422206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10833211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Lisa M</given-names></name><name><surname>Woloshin</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The media matter: a call for straightforward medical reporting.</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2004</year><month>2</month><day>3</day><volume>140</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shattuck lecture--medicine and the media</article-title><source>New England Journal of Medicine</source><year>1998</year><volume>339</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199807093390206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9654540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romond</surname><given-names>Edward H</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>Edith A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><name><surname>Suman</surname><given-names>Vera J</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>Charles E</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>Nancy E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan-Chiu</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>Silvana</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>Soonmyung</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>Peter A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>Sandra M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisansky</surname><given-names>Thomas M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehrenbacher</surname><given-names>Louis</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutteh</surname><given-names>Leila A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>Victor G</given-names></name><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>Daniel W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yothers</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>Robert B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Ann M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakhil</surname><given-names>Shaker R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamounas</surname><given-names>Eleftherios P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingle</surname><given-names>Wilma L</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Pamela M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingle</surname><given-names>James N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolmark</surname><given-names>Norman</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trastuzumab plus adjuvant chemotherapy for operable HER2-positive breast cancer.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><month>10</month><day>20</day><volume>353</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1673</fpage><lpage>1684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa052122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>Picard</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Second opinion: Be skeptical about the Herceptin hype</article-title><year>2005</year><month>8</month><day>4</day><fpage>A15</fpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v5/content/subscribe?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2FArticleNews%2FTPStory%2FLAC%2F20050804%2FHPICARD04&#x00026;ord=2039187">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v5/content/subscribe?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2FArticleNews%2FTPStory%2FLAC%2F20050804%2FHPICARD04&#x00026;ord=2039187</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Genentech Biotechnology</collab></person-group><article-title>Important drug warning. [Dear Healthcare Provider letter]</article-title><year>2005</year><month>8</month><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Jan 21</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gene.com/gene/products/information/pdf/herceptin-ddl.pdf">http://www.gene.com/gene/products/information/pdf/herceptin-ddl.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caspermeyer</surname><given-names>Joseph J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sylvester</surname><given-names>Edward J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drazkowski</surname><given-names>Joseph F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>George L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirven</surname><given-names>Joseph I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of stigmatizing language and medical errors in neurology coverage by US newspapers.</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>2006</year><month>3</month><volume>81</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ALLHAT in the news: How well did newspapers cover the world's most important antihypertensive trial? Toward a National Pharmaceutical Strategy [poster presentation]</article-title><conf-name>Centre for Health Services and Policy Research Conference</conf-name><conf-date>2006 Feb 9</conf-date><conf-loc>Vancouver</conf-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charatan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylpropanolamine in drugs could be a risk for stroke.</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2000</year><month>10</month><day>28</day><volume>321</volume><issue>7268</issue><fpage>1037</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.321.7268.1037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11053157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kernan</surname><given-names>W N</given-names></name><name><surname>Viscoli</surname><given-names>C M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brass</surname><given-names>L M</given-names></name><name><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>J P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>L B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilterdink</surname><given-names>J L</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>R I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylpropanolamine and the risk of hemorrhagic stroke.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><month>12</month><day>21</day><volume>343</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>1826</fpage><lpage>1832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200012213432501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11117973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>Andre</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How can we improve medical reporting? Let me count the ways.</article-title><source>Int J Health Serv</source><year>2005</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2190/MADK-XGU0-MY2M-QFJQ</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16119578</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>