<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673943</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3113222</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-01-e147-149</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Up close and personal: poverty and human development</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>Sally</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Sally Murray</bold>, </p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>James Brophy</bold>, </p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Claire Kendall</bold> and</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palepu</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Anita Palepu</bold> are members of the editorial team of <italic>Open Medicine</italic>. Their affiliations are listed <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/about/editorialTeam">here</ext-link>.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e147</fpage><lpage>e149</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country. For more information, please follow this link: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/ca/">Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.5 Canada License</ext-link>.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/171/80">http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/171/80</self-uri><abstract><sec><title/><p>Poverty and health are inextricably linked: poverty diminishes access to health care (whether through reduced ability to pay, a lack of knowledge about when to seek health care or a lack of adequate services within reach), increases exposure to disease and other illness (for example, through exposure to dangerous workplaces), and is related to reduced access to clean water, housing and sanitation.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>October 22 marks the launch of special issues related to global poverty and human development in more than 200 biomedical journals around the world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref> Although poverty contributes to poor health in more than 2 billion people worldwide, and despite an exponential increase in scientific research publication in recent years, little is published on interventions and analyses that target improved health in poor countries. <italic>Open Medicine</italic>&#x02019;s participation in this collaborative initiative is a small effort toward redressing this deficiency.</p><p>Poverty and health are inextricably linked: poverty diminishes access to health care (whether through reduced ability to pay, a lack of knowledge about when to seek health care or a lack of adequate services within reach), increases exposure to disease and other illness (for example, through exposure to dangerous workplaces), and is related to reduced access to clean water, housing and sanitation.</p><p>The need to address poverty as an underlying contributor to poor health is not a new concept: the 1978 Alma-Ata Declaration determined that achieving the highest possible level of health requires the response not only of the health sector but of many other social and economic sectors as well.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> Yet it is only in the last decade that agencies such as the World Health Organization have focused on poverty as a distinct determinant of health.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>Other initiatives such as the United Nations Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) similarly have poverty as a focus.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> The MDGs focus on reducing poverty and hunger as well as addressing specific health issues (<italic>e.g.</italic>, maternal health, child mortality, HIV/AIDS and malaria) and broader, interrelated issues such as education, gender equality and environmental sustainability. The initiative brings sharp focus to the problem of poverty as a determinant of health and of human development.</p><p>Arguably, some agencies may have pursued the link between poverty and health less out of an interest in health as a fundamental human right (as argued at Alma-Ata) than through the realization that improved health leads to economic gain and gross domestic product (GDP) growth. Importantly &#x02014; irrespective of the underlying reasons for addressing the problem &#x02014; this change in direction in multi-agency attention has focused much-needed resources on neglected health sectors and initiatives addressing poverty.</p><p>As we proceed to address poverty and human development we need to ensure that our work is done with care. The way we calculate, benchmark and monitor improvements (or deterioration) across countries and continents can hide as much as it reveals. Using aggregate statistics may in fact silence some underprivileged groups whose health (or other) outcomes are subsumed by the statistics generated by larger population groups. For example, small groups within countries may, as a result of poverty, lack opportunity for human development and not be adequately represented in national statistics.</p><p>The Indigenous people of Australia provide one example of the multifaceted impact of poverty on health. Australia is home to 21 million people, including 410,000 Indigenous Australians.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Although the incomes of Indigenous Australians&#x02019; do not meet the United Nation&#x02019;s criteria for absolute poverty (less than US$1 per day) the income gap in Australia means that the problems plaguing the world&#x02019;s poor are mirrored in these communities, in reduced life expectancy, low schooling rates, poor access to water and sanitation, and reduced access to health care.</p><p>The extent of the disparity between Australian national averages and those of Indigenous Australians can be highlighted using the UN Human Development Index (HDI). The HDI draws attention to three facets of human development &#x02014; life expectancy, education and standard of living &#x02014; and is used to make comparisons at the country level.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> Australia is ranked third in the index. If we examine these three indicators for Indigenous Australians we see that Australia&#x02019;s ranking hides the experiences of Indigenous Australians.</p><p>Consider life expectancy and education. Indigenous Australians can expect to live 17 years less than non-Indigenous Australians (59 years for Indigenous men), meaning that life expectancy in Nigeria, Nepal, India and Bangladesh is considerably greater.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> Schooling rates in Australian Indigenous communities are also considerably lower. Indigenous persons are only half as likely as non-Indigenous persons to have completed Year 12 (18% compared with 41%) and only one-quarter as likely if they are living in remote areas.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Saliently, a 2003 review of schooling in Indigenous communities found that poverty limits literacy and numeracy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></p><p>The third ingredient of the HDI&#x02014;standard of living&#x02014; is also clearly substandard. The HDI uses purchasing power parity (PPP) and income to measure standard of living. Although PPP data are not available for Indigenous Australians, raw income data show that for the period 2002 to 2004&#x02013;05 the median gross weekly household income for Indigenous Australians was A$340, almost half that of non-Indigenous population (A$618), and that 40% of Indigenous people had household incomes in the lowest quintile.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref></p><p>Receiving an income is, at least in part, dependent on participation in paid employment. In 2004&#x02013;05 over half of Indigenous people received their individual income from government pensions and allowances, and a further 10% received income from government work schemes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Today, fewer than half of Indigenous people aged 15 years or more report paid employment (42%), and Indigenous people are almost three times more likely than non-Indigenous people to be unemployed (20% compared with 7%).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></p><p>Indigenous Australians&#x02019; reduced income (and potential access to income) is compounded in other ways: up to 85% of income is spent on basic living costs in remote communities, with food accounting for almost one third of the total<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> (cited in Webb and Leeder).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> This compares with Australian population spending of less than 20% of income on food.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Access to health services is often limited, housing is unavailable or unaffordable, and basic services such as sanitation and water are still, astoundingly, unavailable in some communities.</p><p>The experience of Indigenous Australians is not dissimilar to that of Indigenous peoples around the world. In every instance, Indigenous peoples of the world have life expectancies lower than the national average.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Their levels of income, education and employment are also worse. In Canada life expectancy for First Nation peoples is 7.4 years (males) and 5.2 years (females) less than the national average.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Educational attainment indicators, including secondary school completion rates, postsecondary education admissions and completion of university degrees are lower for on-reserve Registered Indians<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> and, like Indigenous Australians, most Aboriginal people are at or below the poverty line. In major Western Canadian cities, four times as many Aboriginal people as other citizens live below the poverty line.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref></p><p>The Commission on Social Determinants of Health (CSDH), a World Health Organization-affiliated body, recognizes the unique problems facing Indigenous peoples across the globe and are committed to specifically examining the health of these populations. The Commission held a recent symposium on Indigenous health in Adelaide, Australia, for 74 representatives from Australia, Belize, Cambodia, Canada, Chile, China, Ecuador, Guatemala, New Zealand, the Philippines and the United Kingdom.</p><p>The report from the Symposium underlines the resolution of Indigenous poverty as &#x0201c;fundamental to improving health.&#x0201d; Income, education and employment are highlighted for their interdependent impact on health, each leading to &#x0201c;marginalisation [and] limiting access to education, employment, good housing and nutritious food.&#x0201d; Representatives also found that poverty has a direct impact on mental well-being by lowering self-esteem, increasing dependence and &#x0201c;vitiating one&#x02019;s ability to participate fully in society.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></p><p>The Symposium&#x02019;s report highlights investment in education, particularly of children, as one means of combating poverty. Given the impact of education on subsequent income, employment status and living conditions, this is a crucial part of action<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> and one also supported by the MDGs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>In Australia there are growing (but belated) efforts to do just this. A recent government report highlights several initiatives that are successfully encouraging Indigenous children&#x02019;s education. These include Deadly Vibe, a magazine for Indigenous students published by an Aboriginal media agency, non-government-sector sponsorship of scholarship programs for children to board at private schools, and a private foundation engaging and supporting young Indigenous men to complete Year 12 and to find employment.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> Unfortunately, such initiatives are unlikely to be replicated in poorer nations with few private benefactors.</p><p>Poverty is a complex phenomenon, no less in countries with Indigenous people, where poverty is tied to the limitation of opportunity through racism, geographical isolation and political inertia. As fraught and complex as the solutions may be, there is no doubt that broader global efforts must be cognisant of Indigenous poverty and opportunity. In the same way, we must consider that Indigenous poverty is just one example of poverty in the context of affluence. Many countries have broad income gradients and large gaps between the very rich and the very poor.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref> We must ensure that our efforts address all groups in need.</p><p>We hope that the research, commentary and analysis published this month in <italic>Open Medicine</italic> and the other many journals offer useful debate and information for policy-makers, health practitioners and program managers with an interest in global poverty and human development. The articles <italic>Open Medicine</italic> publishes are open access, freely accessible to all. We believe there is little point in publishing key information to influence health outcomes and debate if those who want to use the information are impeded from accessing it by expensive subscription fees. Indeed, open access publication of scientific and technical information is supported by the UN as part of building a people-centred, inclusive and development-oriented society.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">&#x02020;</xref> We also hope that research is used carefully and critically; ensuring that all are included in our poverty reduction mandate to support true human development.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.councilscienceeditors.org/globalthemeissue.cfm">a full list of participating journals</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>The WSIS principles and plan of action are endorsed by the UN General Assembly resolution 59/220.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><source>Declaration of Alma-Ata</source><year>1978</year><conf-name>International Conference on Primary Health Care</conf-name><conf-date>6-12 September, 1978</conf-date><conf-loc>Alma-Ata, USSR</conf-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Commission on Macroeconomics and Health</collab><source>Macroeconomics and Health: Investing in health for economic development</source><year>2001</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2001/924154550X.pdf">http://whqlibdoc.who.int/publications/2001/924154550X.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Commission on Social Determinants of Health</collab><source>Achieving Health Equity: from root causes to fair outcomes</source><year>2007</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phm-india.org/pdf/PHM_Global/CSDH%20interim%20statement.pdf">http://phm-india.org/pdf/PHM_Global/CSDH%20interim%20statement.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>United Nations</collab><source>The Millennium Development Goals Report</source><year>2006</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://unstats.un.org/unsd/mdg/Resources/Static/Products/Progress2006/MDGReport2006">http://unstats.un.org/unsd/mdg/Resources/Static/Products/Progress2006/MDGReport2006</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Steering Committee for the Review of Government Service Provision</collab><source>Overcoming Indigenous Disadvantage: Key Indicators 2007</source><year>2007</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pc.gov.au/gsp/reports/indigenous/keyindicators2007">http://www.pc.gov.au/gsp/reports/indigenous/keyindicators2007</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>United Nations Development Programme</collab><source>Human Development Report 2006. Beyond scarcity: power, poverty and the global water crisis</source><year>2006</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdr.undp.org/hdr2006">http://hdr.undp.org/hdr2006</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab><source>Population Characteristics, Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Australians, 2001</source><year>2003</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/ProductsbyCatalogue/2B3D3A062FF56BC1CA256DCE007FBFFA?OpenDocument">http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/ProductsbyCatalogue/2B3D3A062FF56BC1CA256DCE007FBFFA?OpenDocument</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Department of Education Science and Training</collab><source>Final Report of the National Evaluation of National Indigenous English Literacy and Numeracy Strategy (NIELNS)</source><year>2003</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dest.gov.au/sectors/indigenous_education/publications_resources/profiles/final_report_nielns.htm">http://www.dest.gov.au/sectors/indigenous_education/publications_resources/profiles/final_report_nielns.htm</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tregenza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tregenza</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Anangu Pitjantjatjara Services Resource Management Project: Budgeting household resources</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Alice Springs</publisher-loc><publisher-name>N Kutjara Consultants</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>Karen L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeder</surname><given-names>Stephen R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New Year's resolution: let's get rid of excessive food prices in remote Australia.</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2007</year><month>1</month><day>1</day><volume>186</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17229023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Australian Bureau of Statistics</collab><article-title>Household expenditure survey, Australia: summary of results, 2003&#x02013;04</article-title><year>2004</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/DetailsPage/6530.02003-04%20(Reissue)?OpenDocument">http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/DetailsPage/6530.02003-04%20(Reissue)?OpenDocument</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Health Canada</collab><source>A Statistical Profile on the Health of First Nations in Canada for the Year 2000</source><year>2005</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fnih-spni/pubs/gen/stats_profil_e.html">http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/fnih-spni/pubs/gen/stats_profil_e.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Indian and Northern Affairs Canada</collab><article-title>Social Development</article-title><year>2007</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ainc-inac.gc.ca/gs/soci_e.html">http://www.ainc-inac.gc.ca/gs/soci_e.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>World Health Organization (Commission on Social Determinants of Health)</collab><source>Social determinants and indigenous health: the international experience and its policy implications. Report on specially prepared documents, presentations and discussion., in International Symposium on the Social Determinants of Indigenous Health</source><year>2007</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/social_determinants/resources/indigenous_health_adelaide_report_07.pdf">http://www.who.int/social_determinants/resources/indigenous_health_adelaide_report_07.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>Steven A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shattuck Lecture. We can do better--improving the health of the American people.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2007</year><month>9</month><day>20</day><volume>357</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMsa073350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><source>Declaration of Principles: Building the Information Society: a global challenge in the new Millennium. in World Summit on the Information Society</source><year>2003</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/official/dop.html">http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/official/dop.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>