<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602940</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3090174</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-02-e45-48</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>How well do Canadian media outlets convey medical treatment information?</article-title><subtitle>Initial findings from a year and a half of media monitoring by Media Doctor Canada</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Alan Cassels</bold> is the project leader of Media Doctor Canada, Victoria, BC.</p></bio></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lexchin</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><bio><p><bold>Joel Lexchin</bold> is a professor in the School of Health Policy and Management, York University, Toronto, Ont.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp><email>cassels@uvic.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e45</fpage><lpage>e48</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/170/131">http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/170/131</self-uri></article-meta></front><body><p>The popular media play a crucial role in communicating information about health treatments. By informing the public about new research findings, they can affect how medical treatments are perceived<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> and, in so doing, influence their use.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> Although some medical reporting is driven by public interest, many stories are prompted by companies, universities and research groups who are promoting their work and hope to get favourable coverage of it from major media outlets.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> A recent analysis by public relations specialists argues that the shift from traditional advertising to public relations is one of the most dramatic changes in the marketing field in decades and has come about because of the perceived superiority of this approach.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></p><p>Most recent studies of media coverage of medical treatments have found that many stories about pharmaceuticals lack complete information, particularly details on the quality of evidence and on the reported benefits, harms and costs of treatments.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Research in this area in Canada has led to recent calls for more direct and honest reporting of the results of research.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> In the last three years, three different services &#x02014; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediadoctor.org.au/">Media Doctor Australia</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mediadoctor.ca/">Media Doctor Canada</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.healthnewsreview.org/">Health News Reviews</ext-link> in the United States &#x02014; have monitored hundreds of health treatment stories using similar criteria, posting results to their websites. </p><p>Media Doctor Australia, with input from medical media researchers in Canada and the United States, developed 10 criteria with which to analyze media stories about treatments.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> Our group, Media Doctor Canada, adapted these into a similar tool, dropping a criterion about the presence or absence of press releases and adding one about the quantification of harms from treatments. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="table1">Table 1</xref> shows the 10 criteria that we ultimately used.</p><fig id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Media Doctor Canada rating instrument for assessing the quality of news stories about medical treatments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-02-e45-g001"/></fig><p>We assembled a team of 12 reviewers with backgrounds in clinical epidemiology, clinical medicine, evidence-based medicine and media studies from personal contacts and people who had been involved in an earlier study of medical media reporting in Canada.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> Over an 18-month period between 31 May 2005 and 1 November 2006, Media Doctor Canada analyzed 87 unique stories dealing with treatments that appeared in 10 major English-language daily newspapers, a medical news service directed toward health professionals, and two web-based news services that are linked to two major broadcasters in Canada (CBC and CTV). Our method of evaluating stories followed the procedure used in Australia: Each story was rated Satisfactory or Not Satisfactory for each of the 10 criteria by two reviewers, and any disagreements were resolved by consensus. We felt that media coverage may be different for stories dealing with pharmaceuticals versus other forms of treatment, so we examined stories in these two categories separately.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="table2">Table 2</xref> shows the percentage of Satisfactory scores for each of the 10 different rating criteria for all 87 stories about pharmaceuticals and other forms of treatment. Nearly all stories dealing with pharmaceuticals and other treatments were rated Satisfactory on two criteria: Novelty of Treatment (93.8%) and Disease-Mongering (89.7%). This is to say that the stories did not exaggerate or misconstrue the novelty of the treatment (saying something was new when it was not) or misrepresent the natural history of the disease (disease-mongering). For all other criteria, fewer than half the stories in either category (pharmaceuticals or other therapies) were rated Satisfactory. The largest difference in the rate of Satisfactory scores between the two categories was for Harms of Treatment: 49.2% for pharmaceutical stories versus 30.4% for stories about other treatments.</p><fig id="table2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ranking and percentage of &#x0201c;Satisfactory&#x0201d; scores on assessment criteria</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-02-e45-g002"/></fig><p>Our results were consistent with those reported by Media Doctor Australia, which also found the highest percentage of Satisfactory scores for Novelty of Treatment and Disease-Mongering.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref> In addition, the lowest-scoring criterion in the Australian study was Costs of Treatment, which similarly ranked near the bottom in our study.</p><p>Despite the consistency between these two studies, there are a few possible weaknesses to our approach. Although we trained our reviewers to apply the different criteria consistently, we recognize that there may have been individual biases that affected the scoring. Furthermore, we may have missed stories during our daily screening and selection, particularly because we looked only at stories from the largest English-language Canadian newspapers and two broadcast news agencies. The quality of stories appearing in other media, especially small media outlets where there are no journalists trained in health reporting, may be different.</p><p>Some journalists may consider our 10-criteria rating system to be difficult to implement, but none who communicated to us about our evaluations of their stories raised this concern, and we have had many favourable reviews of our site.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref> We recognize that many elements that go into making a &#x0201c;good&#x0201d; story from the point of view of journalists may not have been considered, but do not believe that these preclude accurate and informed reporting. Similarly, there are arguments that short news stories cannot accommodate all of the criteria we measure. However, this assertion has not been supported by previous work in which we have shown that there are few significant differences in the overall quality between short news briefs and longer stories.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref></p><p>The quality and comprehensiveness of the coverage of health technologies by the lay media is an important topic to study.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>Although journalism outlets strive<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> to do a competent job while juggling competing interests, there are few mechanisms by which to provide them with feedback on the quality of their coverage. Since there is evidence that providing timely feedback of performance data can improve practice standards,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref> auditing or monitoring the quality of health reporting in the lay press and feeding reviews back to news outlets may improve the informative value of these stories.</p><p>An obvious question then to ask is, Has Media Doctor Canada made a difference in the quality of Canadian medical reporting? We have recorded more than 59,000 unique hits on our site, but because they are anonymous we have no concrete evidence as to whether we are in fact contributing to the education of journalists. In the future, we intend to continue to build our database of articles, to send scores back to the editors and journalists whose stories we assess, to broaden and refine the scoring instruments and to periodically systematically analyze the collected data to see if there have been any changes to the averages of the scoring criteria. One measure of success could be a finding of better reporting of the criteria where journalists are currently missing the mark, such as Quantification of Harms of Treatment. If this were coupled with focus-group interviews with journalists indicating that our site had a positive impact on their reporting, we could be confident that our endeavour was having a positive effect.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Funding source: This study was funded by a grant from the Office of Consumer Affairs at Industry Canada. The sponsor played no role in gathering or analyzing the data. The authors had full control over all contents of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We would like to thank the following people who reviewed stories for Media Doctor Canada: Donna Barker, Carol Cole, Merrilee Hughes, Fariba Jaffary, Peter Jewesson, Sarah Kreager, Peter Loewen, James McCormack, Vijaya Musini, Marco Perez, Avis Picton, Gwen Preston, Lori Puil, Aaron Tejani and Jennifer Thornhill.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>D P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanter</surname><given-names>E J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarczyk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tastad</surname><given-names>P L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of the lay press in the transmission of medical knowledge to the scientific community</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1991</year><volume>325</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1891034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Minozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass media interventions: effects on health services utilisation</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>CD000389</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11869574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>The fall of advertising and the rise of public relations</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper Collins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Publish and be pampered</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2003</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>348</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.327.7410.348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woloshin</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Lisa M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Press releases: translating research into news</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2002</year><volume>287</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>2856</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=12038933">http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=12038933</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12038933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Merrilee A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintzes</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><name><surname>Lexchin</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>James P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drugs in the news: an analysis of Canadian newspaper coverage of new prescription drugs</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2003</year><volume>168</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cmaj.ca/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=12719316">http://www.cmaj.ca/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=12719316</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12719316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moynihan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross-Degnan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soumerai</surname><given-names>S B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coverage by the news media of the benefits and risks of medications</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>342</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://content.nejm.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=short&#x00026;pmid=10833211&#x00026;promo=ONFLNS19">http://content.nejm.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=short&#x00026;pmid=10833211&#x00026;promo=ONFLNS19</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10833211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On medical news, is the reporting healthy?</article-title><source>The Globe and Mail</source><year>2005</year><month>12</month><day>29</day><comment>Sect: A17.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Lisa M</given-names></name><name><surname>Woloshin</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The media matter: a call for straightforward medical reporting</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>140</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.annals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=reprint&#x00026;pmid=14757622">http://www.annals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=reprint&#x00026;pmid=14757622</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>David E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Amanda J</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>David A</given-names></name></person-group><collab>Media Doctor Study Group</collab><article-title>Monitoring the quality of medical news reporting: early experience with media doctor</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2005</year><volume>183</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mja.com.au/public/issues/183_04_150805/smi10755_fm.html">http://www.mja.com.au/public/issues/183_04_150805/smi10755_fm.html</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16097916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassels</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintzes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lexchin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Drugs in the news: how well do Canadian newspapers report the good, the bad and the ugly of new prescription drugs?</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.policyalternatives.ca/index.cfm?act=news&#x00026;do=Article&#x00026;call=154&#x00026;pA=19933261&#x00026;type=2,3,4,5,6,7">http://www.policyalternatives.ca/index.cfm?act=news&#x00026;do=Article&#x00026;call=154&#x00026;pA=19933261&#x00026;type=2,3,4,5,6,7</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shattuck lecture--medicine and the media</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>339</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9654540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassirer</surname><given-names>J P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical research--what should the public believe?</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>331</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8008033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An uneasy relationship: the tensions between medicine and the media</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1996</year><volume>347</volume><issue>9015</issue><fpage>1600</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8667872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson O'Brien</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Freemantle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Audit and feedback: effects on professional practice and health care outcomes</article-title><source>The Cochrane Library</source><year>1999</year><issue>4</issue></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>