<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602943</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3090181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-02-e54-59</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Email security in clinical practice: ensuring patient confidentiality </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kreindler</surname><given-names>David M</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><degrees>MD</degrees><degrees>FRCP(C)</degrees><bio><p><bold>David M. Kreindler</bold>, BSc, MD, FRCP(C), is with the Division of Youth Psychiatry, Department of Psychiatry, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, and the Mood and Anxiety Program, Department of Psychiatry, University of Toronto.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Dr. David Kreindler, Department of Psychiatry, Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, 2075 Bayview Avenue, Room FG-62, Toronto ON M4N 3M5; <email>david.kreindler@utoronto.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e54</fpage><lpage>e59</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/56/144">http://www.openmedicine.ca/article/view/56/144</self-uri></article-meta></front><body><p><italic>Note:</italic> Elements of this article were presented as a part of a workshop at the annual meeting of the Canadian Psychiatric Association (CPA) in Vancouver in November 2005 and at a CPA continuing medical education online forum in 2006.</p><sec sec-type=""><title/><p>Electronic mail (email) enjoys wide acceptance among the general public<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref> but has more limited acceptance among physicians.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> A 2005 survey found that 46% of Canadian physicians used email to communicate with colleagues for clinical purposes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref> Although email can be extremely useful, physicians need to appreciate the potential hazards of using email in clinical practice.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref> The College of Physicians and Surgeons of Ontario (CPSO) has noted that &#x0201c;e-mailing or faxing unencrypted patient health information is really no more secure than sending that information on a postcard,&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref> and that &#x0201c;those physicians who wish to send personal health information by email should use an encrypted or otherwise secure system.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> The American Medical Informatics Association has offered similar guidance.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref></p><p>This article outlines how email works, introduces the basics of encryption, and highlights the important role that encryption has to play in the clinical use of email. It does not recommend specific pieces of commercial software, since both software and encryption technology are constantly evolving. </p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Clinical vignette</title><p>A specialist visits a clinic in a remote city to provide consultations. While there, the physician dictates consultation notes that are transcribed by the clinic staff. The transcribed notes are sent at a later time by email to the consultant for review and editing; they are then returned to the remote clinic by email for distribution and inclusion in the patient record.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Question 1: Does the use of email in this scenario result in risks to confidentiality?</title><p>Yes, there are definite potential risks. To understand why, it is essential to first understand how email works.</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>How email works</title><sec><title>Email is not sent; it is copied</title><p>In contrast to a regular letter sent via the postal service, an email message is not carried from one computer to another; rather, the original message is copied to the remote location, while the original copy remains at the sending location, in a manner similar to what happens in the transmission of a facsimile (fax).</p></sec><sec><title>Copies of email are generated on multiple computers</title><p>Email is relayed via a network of <italic>client</italic> and <italic>server</italic> computers, such that one copy is generated at each computer participating along the way (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure1">Fig. 1</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref> This process is documented in the <italic>header</italic> of each email message and can be inspected if the header is viewed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure2">Fig. 2</xref>).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref> In principle, a copy of the original message could be accessed by anyone with computer expertise, physical or network access to any one of these computers, and the necessary passwords. Typically, servers retain copies of emails that they relay only temporarily, in order to conserve storage space; however, these copies are not necessarily deleted immediately. Moreover, servers are typically backed up from time to time, so there is no guarantee that copies of email in temporary storage on a server will not be preserved indefinitely as part of a backup.</p></sec><sec><title>Can you be sure that the sender&#x02019;s and receiver&#x02019;s computers are secure?</title><p>Many personal computers (PCs) are used by more than one person &#x02014; for example, by family members at home or colleagues at work. Moreover, some operating systems &#x02014; notably, most versions of Windows &#x02014; are not configured by default to restrict one user&#x02019;s ability to access other users&#x02019; files.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref> Thus, it is possible that persons other than the sender or the intended recipient may be able to access email messages not intended for them on the sender&#x02019;s or recipient&#x02019;s computer. Also, it is possible for unauthorized users to impersonate physicians if the computer is not properly configured.</p></sec><sec><title>Summary</title><p>In this vignette, email is sent from clinic to consultant via mail servers on the Internet; the owners and operators of the servers are unknown. There are three loci at which someone could intercept and potentially read the clinic notes: the sender&#x02019;s computer; any of the mail servers that relayed the email; and the recipient&#x02019;s computer. Even if one demands that the sender and the recipient be responsible for securing access to their computers, copies of the email are generated at each of the servers; confidentiality could be breached at any one of them.</p><fig id="figure1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Email transmission</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-02-e54-g001"/></fig><fig id="figure2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A sample email message, including the header, body, and the initial portion of an attachment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-02-e54-g002"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Question 2: What reasonable steps could be taken to decrease the risk to patient confidentiality?</title><p>In practice, there are two straightforward solutions.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Strip the consultation note of all identifying patient information.</bold> However, this is typically inconvenient and time-consuming. </p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Encrypt the email.</bold> If an email is the Internet equivalent of a postcard, the encryption process acts as an envelope.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>How encryption works </title><sec><title>Cryptography, encryption and decryption</title><p><italic>Cryptography</italic> refers to processes for converting text from a readable to an unreadable format (&#x0201c;encryption&#x0201d;) and back again (&#x0201c;decryption&#x0201d;). Modern cryptographic systems generate a set of random digits that are then protected using a <italic>password</italic> or <italic>passphrase</italic> selected by the user, creating the key. The key is used to scramble (i.e., encrypt) the text. If viewed while encrypted, the text appears to be a string of random incomprehensible characters. Only when provided with the proper key can the original text be unscrambled (i.e., decrypted) into the original text.</p><p>Modern cryptographic systems can be divided into two broad classes,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref> based on how keys are handled: <italic>secret key</italic> (or <italic>symmetric key</italic>) systems, and <italic>public key</italic> systems. These are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref></p></sec><sec><title>How secure is an encrypted document?</title><p>An encrypted document&#x02019;s security &#x02014; its ability to resist being read by unauthorized third parties &#x02014; depends on (i) the strength of the encryption system that is being used, and (ii) the strength and confidentiality of the key. If a password protecting either the sender&#x02019;s or the recipient&#x02019;s key is intercepted by a third party (e.g., by being overheard, stolen, inadvertently disclosed, etc.) or the key is discovered, the document is no longer secure. Broadly speaking, there are three ways by which an unauthorized third party can decrypt and read (&#x0201c;crack&#x0201d;) an encrypted message when the sender&#x02019;s or recipient&#x02019;s computer is secure:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Guessing the password.</bold> A thorough discussion of password selection is beyond the scope of this article.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> Briefly, if a cryptosystem&#x02019;s key is protected by a user-supplied password, the key is vulnerable to anyone with access to the system. The degree of vulnerability depends on the strength of the user-supplied password. Words found in a dictionary are poor (&#x0201c;weak&#x0201d;) choices, since they are relatively easy to guess, as are birth dates, phone numbers, maiden names, etc., or any minor variations of these. Unusual combinations of letters, numbers, and punctuation are better choices, as are long multi-word combinations with interspersed numbers or punctuation. Long random character sequences are &#x0201c;strongest,&#x0201d; i.e., hardest to guess, but these can be difficult to remember.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Guessing the key.</bold> It is theoretically possible to decrypt an encrypted message by guessing the key that was used to encrypt it. The advantage of this method is that it does not depend on access to the sender&#x02019;s or receiver&#x02019;s computer. The disadvantage is that the attack &#x02014; referred to as a <italic>brute force attack</italic> &#x02014; is extremely resource- and time-consuming. One example of successful brute force attacks is against the widely available but poorly implemented RC-4 encryption system<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> included with Microsoft Word 2000.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> In principal, RC-4 is a good encryption system<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>; however, to comply with United States export laws,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref> the implementation of RC-4 in Word 2000 is limited to 2<sup>40</sup> or 1&#x02009;099&#x02009;511&#x02009;627&#x02009;776 possible passwords (technically, a &#x0201c;40 bit key&#x0201d;).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>  Although this may seem like a huge number, a modern computer capable of testing 100 million potential passwords per minute can exhaust all possible alternatives in approximately 10 days. Many inexpensive software tools and services for doing exactly this are available for purchase, e.g., by searching the Internet via www.google.com using keywords, &#x0201c;Word password decryption crack.&#x0201d; In contrast, one study estimated that, on average, it would take a dedicated 2001-vintage $10 million computer longer than the lifetime of the universe to break a document encrypted using symmetric encryption and a random 128-bit key.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">&#x02020;</xref></p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>&#x0201c;Breaking&#x0201d; the encryption system</bold>, by finding a flaw in the math underlying the encryption system&#x02019;s algorithm that can be exploited to decrypt the message. One may think of this type of attack as using an unplanned &#x0201c;shortcut&#x0201d; to a cryptosystem&#x02019;s complex math problem. These kinds of shortcuts can appear in any cryptosystem, but have historically been found in cryptosystems that have been deployed with little or no peer review. One such example is the wireless encryption system used in many commercial and consumer wireless routers.</p></list-item></list><fig id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cryptosystem characteristics</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-02-e54-g003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Any document encrypted with a weak key is vulnerable to guessing attacks</title><p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> To defend against the possibility of poor key choice, some encryption systems (such as PGP, described below) automatically generate random keys. In general, if a strong key is paired with a robust encryption system &#x02014; that is, one based on Triple-DES,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> AES/Rijndael,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref> Blowfish,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>, ECC,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref> RSA,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> or one of the others that have survived peer review and/or public contests<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref> and thus can be considered reliable &#x02014; the chance of unauthorized decryption is very small. </p><sec><title>Getting started with encrypted email</title><p>In general, by default, most email programs transmit email <italic>without</italic> encryption. Although encryption is increasingly being incorporated into widely available software, no single standard for encrypted email presently exists. The closest to a single standard for public-key encrypted email, S/MIME,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref> has been incorporated into many but not all popular email software packages, although it requires some infrastructure to work. Another popular implementation is PGP (&#x0201c;Pretty Good Privacy&#x0201d;).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref> The following steps are key for those wishing to start using encrypted email with colleagues, patients, or others:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Select cryptographic software compatible with that of your correspondents.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Become proficient with your email and encryption software.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ensure that you are using strong passwords and keys, and keep them confidential.</p></list-item><list-item><p>For <italic>secret key</italic> cryptosystems, decide on a shared password and communicate it to your correspondent securely.</p></list-item><list-item><p>For <italic>public key</italic> cryptosystems, each correspondent will need to publish his or her public key. How this happens depends on the specific implementation chosen. S/MIME users require a <italic>digital certificate</italic> (also known as a <italic>public key certificate</italic>) from a <italic>certificate authority</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref> A certificate authority is deemed to be implicitly trustworthy; it verifies an applicant&#x02019;s identity, then issues a digital certificate. The digital certificate specifies the applicant&#x02019;s email and certifies that the public key, which is included in the certificate, belongs to the applicant. Anyone wishing to send email to a user looks up the user&#x02019;s public key in the certificate authority&#x02019;s database online. In contrast, every PGP user generates and distributes his or her own public key. Rather than relying on the certificate authority to verify identities, PGP uses other users to vouch for the validity of each others&#x02019; public keys, thereby creating an interconnected &#x0201c;web of trust.&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref> Keys and trust signatures can be hosted on PGP key servers, further simplifying this process.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The author thanks Deborah Fenichel, PhD, and Dr. Tarek Loubani, MD, for their careful reading and detailed critique during the preparation of this manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>One way to remember multiple passwords is to use <italic>password management software</italic>. Password management software lets you record all your passwords in a single database, which is then encrypted with a single master password using high-grade encryption. This permits safe storage and easy access to all your passwords. Obviously, it is critical to choose a strong master password and keep it confidential.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Note that the strength of a key of a given length depends on <italic>the class of encryption system</italic>. For example, while a 128-bit key is sufficient at present for symmetric key systems, the key length that would provide equivalent security in a public key system would need to be 1620 bits in length.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></p></fn></fn-group><app-group><app><title>Further reading</title><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Email Security [web page on the Internet]. Toronto: Computing and Networking Services, University of Toronto; c2004 [cited 2006 May 30]. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.utoronto.ca/security/UTORprotect/email.htm">Full Text</ext-link>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>RSA Laboratories&#x02019; Frequently Asked Questions About Today&#x02019;s Cryptography, Version 4.1 [monograph on the Internet]. Bedford, MA (USA): RSA Security Inc.; c2000 [cited 2006 May 30] [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/faq/files/rsalabs_faq41.pdf">Full Text</ext-link>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Bruce Schneier: Crypto-Gram [newsletter on the Internet]. A free monthly newsletter commenting on security issues and security technology. Available from: [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.schneier.com/crypto-gram.html">Full Text</ext-link>]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Bruce Schneier: <italic>Applied Cryptography: Protocols, Algorithms, and Source Code in C</italic>. 2nd ed. New York: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons; 1996. An introductory text for anyone interested in the details of modern applied cryptography. Technical yet very readable.</p></list-item></list></app></app-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dryburgh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>Changing our ways: Why and how Canadians use the Internet.</source><year>2000</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Statistics Canada</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.statcan.ca/english/research/56F0006XIE/56F0006XIE.pdf"/></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab><article-title>Purpose of computer use at home for people 18 years and over using a computer at home, by selected characteristics</article-title><source>Current Population Survey, October 2003</source><year>2003</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United States Census Bureau</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/population/socdemo/computer/2003/tab08B.csv">http://www.census.gov/population/socdemo/computer/2003/tab08B.csv</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sands</surname><given-names>Daniel Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Help for physicians contemplating use of e-mail with patients.</article-title><source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedid=15252925">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedid=15252925</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15252925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Canadian Medical Association and Canada Health Infoway</collab><source>Physician Technology Usage and Attitudes Survey</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Medical Association</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cma.ca/multimedia/CMA/Content_Images/Inside_cma/HIT/10country/Release_slides_v2.ppt">http://www.cma.ca/multimedia/CMA/Content_Images/Inside_cma/HIT/10country/Release_slides_v2.ppt</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>K D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohane</surname><given-names>I S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>A M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic patient-physician communication: problems and promise.</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>129</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.annals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=9735088">http://www.annals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&#x00026;pmid=9735088</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9735088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>College of Physicians and Surgeons of Ontario</collab><article-title>Privacy Legislation</article-title><source>Members' Dialogue</source><year>2004</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The College</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>College of Physicians and Surgeons of Ontario</collab><source>Medical Records Policy #5-05-2. Overview and Organization of Medical Records</source><year>2005</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><issue>5</issue><publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The College</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cpso.on.ca/policies/medical%20records/medicalrec3.htm"/></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sands</surname><given-names>D Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guidelines for the clinical use of electronic mail with patients. The AMIA Internet Working Group, Task Force on Guidelines for the Use of Clinic-Patient Electronic Mail.</article-title><source>J Am Med Inform Assoc</source><year>1998</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedid=9452989">http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?tool=pubmed&#x00026;pubmedid=9452989</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9452989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klensin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>RFC 2821 - Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</source><year>2001</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Nov 20</date-in-citation><publisher-name>AT&#x00026;T Laboratories</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2821">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2821</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Borenstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base64 content-transfer-encoding. Network Working Group Request for Comments: 2045 - Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet Message Bodies</article-title><year>1996</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><publisher-name>First Virtual</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2045.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2045.txt</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugend</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kleinrock</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UCLA to be first station in nationwide computer network</article-title><source>From Gutenberg to the Internet: A Sourcebook on the History of Information Technology</source><year>2005</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2008 June 16</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Novato, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>HistoryofScience.com</publisher-name><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.engineer.ucla.edu/stories/2004/internet1969.htm">http://www.engineer.ucla.edu/stories/2004/internet1969.htm</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Desktop Google finds holes</article-title><source>EWeek</source><year>2004</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Feb 12</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1730748,00.asp">http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1730748,00.asp</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>RSA Laboratories</collab></person-group><article-title>RSA Laboratories&#x02019; frequently asked questions about today&#x02019;s cryptography, version 4.1</article-title><year>2004</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 30</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Bedford, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>RSA Security, Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/faq/files/rsalabs_faq41.pdf">http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/faq/files/rsalabs_faq41.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MySpace passwords aren&#x02019;t so dumb</article-title><year>2006</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Dec 14</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wired.com/news/columns/0,72300-0.html">http://www.wired.com/news/columns/0,72300-0.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Choosing Secure Passwords</article-title><year>2007</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Feb 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/01/choosing_secure.html">http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2007/01/choosing_secure.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Microsoft Corporation</collab></person-group><article-title>Strong passwords: How to create and use them</article-title><year>2006</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Feb 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/athome/security/privacy/password.mspx">http://www.microsoft.com/athome/security/privacy/password.mspx</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Applied cryptography: protocols, algorithms, and source code in C</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Mississauga, ON</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Microsoft Corporation</collab></person-group><source>Word 2000 9.0.6926 SP-3</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Redmond, WA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Microsoft Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsoft RC4 Flaw</article-title><year>2005</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Feb 14</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2005/01/microsoft_rc4_f.html">http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2005/01/microsoft_rc4_f.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Crypto.</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Wikipedia contributors</collab></person-group><article-title>Export of cryptography</article-title><source>Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia</source><year>2006</year><month>11</month><day>7</day><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Nov 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Export_of_cryptography&#x00026;oldid=86191563">http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Export_of_cryptography&#x00026;oldid=86191563</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Microsoft Support</collab></person-group><article-title>Changes in encryption file properties in Office 2003 and Office 2002</article-title><year>2006</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Aug 16</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Redmond, WA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Microsoft Corporation</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;EN-US;q290112">http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;EN-US;q290112</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>RSA Laboratories</collab></person-group><article-title>Bulletin 13: A cost-based security analysis of symmetric and asymmetric key lengths</article-title><year>2001</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 30</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Bedford, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>RSA Security Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/node.asp?id=2088">http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/node.asp?id=2088</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>RSA Laboratories</collab><source>Cryptographic Challenges</source><year>2004</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 30</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Bedford, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>RSA Security Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/node.asp?id=2091">http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/node.asp?id=2091</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Technology Administration, US Department of Commerce</collab><source>AES&#x02013;FIPS&#x02013;197</source><year>2001</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 21</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csrc.nist.gov/CryptoToolkit/aes">http://csrc.nist.gov/CryptoToolkit/aes</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Blowfish encryption algorithm</article-title><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 30</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.schneier.com/blowfish.html">http://www.schneier.com/blowfish.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Certicom</collab><article-title>Introduction to ECC</article-title><year>2006</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 May 30</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Mississauga, ON</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Certicom Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.certicom.com/index.php?action=ecc,home">http://www.certicom.com/index.php?action=ecc,home</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsdell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Network working group request for comments: 2633: S/MIME version 3 message specification</source><year>1999</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2006 Nov 20</date-in-citation><publisher-name>Worldtalk</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2633.txt">http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2633.txt</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Network Associates, Inc</collab><source>An Introduction to Cryptography</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Santa Clara, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Network Associates Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.pgpi.org/pub/pgp/6.5/docs/english/IntroToCrypto.pdf">ftp://ftp.pgpi.org/pub/pgp/6.5/docs/english/IntroToCrypto.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Netscape Communications Corp</collab><article-title>Glossary: Certificate Authority (CA)</article-title><year>2001</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2007 Feb 23</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/security/pki/psm/help_21/glossary.html#1020903">http://www.mozilla.org/projects/security/pki/psm/help_21/glossary.html#1020903</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>