<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">Open Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1911-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Open Medicine Publications, Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22567079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3329116</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenMed-06-e24-27</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Analysis and Comment</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rare diseases: Canada&#x02019;s &#x0201c;research orphans&#x0201d;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Samir</given-names></name><bio><p>
<bold>Samir Gupta</bold> is Assistant Professor in the Department of Medicine and the Division of Respirology at the University of Toronto and Adjunct Scientist at the Keenan Research Centre in the Li Ka Shing Knowledge Institute of St. Michael&#x02019;s Hospital, Toronto, Ontario. He is the Director of the Rare Lung Disease Research Program at St. Michael&#x02019;s Hospital.</p></bio></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Dr. Samir Gupta, Suite 6045, Bond Wing, 30 Bond St., Toronto ON M5B 1W8; <email>guptas@smh.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e24</fpage><lpage>e27</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/2.5/ca/"><license-p>Open Medicine applies the Creative Commons Attribution Share Alike License, which means that anyone is able to freely copy, download, reprint, reuse, distribute, display or perform this work and that authors retain copyright of their work. Any derivative use of this work must be distributed only under a license identical to this one and must be attributed to the authors. Any of these conditions can be waived with permission from the copyright holder. These conditions do not negate or supersede Fair Use laws in any country.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple"/></article-meta></front><body><p>Although definitions vary by jurisdiction, diseases that affect approximately 1 in 2000 people are considered rare.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref> Canada is one of only a few developed countries without a national &#x0201c;orphan drug&#x0201d; program to protect patients with rare diseases from exorbitant drug costs. Public debate concerning government funding for these drugs is periodically stimulated by stories of patients who are deprived of life-sustaining therapies because of cost. However, most Canadians remain unaware of another important disparity between common and rare disease care in this country: namely, the availability of research funding. Above and beyond worrying about expensive therapies, patients diagnosed with a rare disease are often surprised to learn that there is limited scientific knowledge about the causes and natural history of their condition and little or no ongoing research.</p><p>The reasons for this research gap are many. Public funding agencies have a mandate to improve public health, and so naturally favour grants that address common conditions. As a result, researchers with an interest in a rare disease who enter open grant competitions may be disadvantaged by the limited population-level impact of their potential findings.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Furthermore, the relatively small numbers of people affected by a given rare disease make it difficult for researchers to recruit and study an adequate number of patients to reach scientifically valid conclusions. As a result, even basic knowledge about the diagnosis, causes, and consequences of many of these diseases is lacking.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref> Even when these aspects are well understood and drug development can be considered, the pharmaceutical industry often opts out on the grounds that development costs are difficult to recoup from the small number of potential users of a new drug for a rare disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></p><p>In most developed nations, governments have sought to target this inequity through legislation. Since the establishment of the Office of Orphan Products Development by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 1982, various national rare disease laws, policies, and programs have been established successfully in many countries around the world.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref> Some of the most notable of these are outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="table1">Table 1</xref>. The impact of these programs has been significant. Since the US Orphan Drug Act was passed in the United States in 1983, over 300 rare disease products, affecting over 14 million Americans, have come to market, as compared with fewer than 10 products in the previous decade.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> Between 2006 and 2007, the National Institutes of Health Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network produced 25 publications, posters, and abstracts, launched 24 new studies with active recruitment, and enrolled 2357 rare disease subjects.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref> The first French National Plan for Rare Diseases (2005&#x02013;08) enabled the establishment of 132 &#x0201c;reference centres&#x0201d; (specialized national rare disease centres), 500 &#x0201c;centres of competence&#x0201d; (regional rare disease care providers), new best-practice guidelines for 17 rare diseases (with 24 more in preparatory stages at the time of the evaluation), and a compassionate-use system to enable orphan-drug coverage for patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref> The success of the European Union&#x02019;s rare disease research funding initiative is exemplified by the EuroBioBank. Originally funded by a seed grant of &#x020ac;1.22 million by the EU&#x02019;s fifth Framework Programme, this 10-country network of rare disease DNA, cell and tissue banks now contains 440&#x02009;000 rare disease samples, among which 7000 are sent annually to researchers around the world.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></p><p>Patient advocacy groups have also played an important role in advancing the rare disease research agenda, both by lobbying for government action and by funding research directly. In the United States, the National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarediseases.org">http://www.rarediseases.org</ext-link>) is a non-profit federation of over 100 volunteer organizations and 5000 patients and providers dedicated to helping people with rare diseases. The NORD website posts information about active studies along with researcher contact information for patients and their physicians (at no cost),<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref> and invites applications for seed funding for the study of new treatments and diagnostic tests for rare diseases.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref> Also, it was as a result of sustained lobbying by NORD that the US Congress passed the Rare Diseases Act in 2002. In Europe, The European Organization for Rare Disorders (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurordis.org">EURORDIS</ext-link>) represents more than 260 rare disease organizations in more than 30 European countries and plays a role similar to NORD&#x02019;s.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref> In Canada, advocacy is provided by the Canadian Organization for Rare Disorders (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.raredisorders.ca">CORD</ext-link>).</p><p>In contrast to the comprehensive and proven effective approaches developed by nations around the world, Canada remains one of few countries without policies to address research into rare diseases (including drug development incentives) and drug access for patients. Since it came into existence in 2000, the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) have seen an increase in their annual budget from around $350 million to nearly $1 billion in 2009&#x02013;10.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref> Yet it was not until 2011 that the first funding competition specific to rare diseases was announced, allocating a maximum of $14.5 million between 2012 and 2017, including commitments from partner organizations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref></p><p>Logically, a comprehensive strategy to address orphan disease research should be developed and legislated at the federal level, building and improving on processes in other developed nations. For example, a caveat to the US Orphan Drug Act is that it eliminates short-term market competition by guaranteeing drug developers 7 years of market exclusivity.&#x000a0;Although this policy has successfully driven rare disease drug development, it has also been criticized for facilitating prohibitive drug costs.&#x000a0;In Canada, it is possible to envision a federally sponsored, single-payer system to fund pharmaceuticals for rare diseases that includes a policy mechanism that would control costs through advance negotiations with drug developers while still maintaining market incentives.&#x000a0;Furthermore, provisions of the US Orphan Drug Act have resulted in drug development being carried out predominantly in the private sector in the United States, as opposed to government labs or universities. &#x000a0;This should also be addressed in a future Canadian policy through specific incentives to encourage drug development in the non-profit sector.</p><p>The first step toward a Canadian policy was a Private Member&#x02019;s motion brought before the House of Commons in 2008 by Don Bell, then Member of Parliament for North Vancouver.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref> This motion called on the federal government to examine the feasibility of creating a Canadian Rare Disease Strategy that would emulate the principal components of the EU&#x02019;s strategy. Measures proposed by the motion included creating a fund for nation-wide drug coverage for rare disease sufferers, developing Canadian Centres of Reference for rare diseases, and providing public and private organizations with incentives to undertake rare disease research, including drug development. Although the motion was passed,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref> no sustained debate, feasibility assessment, or measurable government action has since materialized.</p><fig id="table1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>International initiatives to promote research and development related to rare diseases</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OpenMed-06-e24-g001"/></fig><sec><title>A call to action</title><p>The imminent renewal of the federal-provincial Health Accord, which expires in 2014, presents an opportunity for provisions for a federally designed rare disease strategy to be tied to provincial funding, with an accountability structure to measure progress. Although the current federal government has delineated the financial terms of the future Accord, at the time of writing, discussions around national standards and provincial accountability have yet to occur.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref> To this end, the Canadian medical and scientific communities should lobby both the federal government and the CIHR directly for action. This can be achieved through free advocacy programs offered by the Canadian Medical Association (CMA), such as the MD-MP Contact Program, which matches CMA members with their local Member of Parliament. Furthermore, the CMA should prioritize this issue, presenting a unified front to the federal government. These efforts should be made in conjunction and consultation with CORD, which represents a large number of rare disease groups&#x02014;a strategy that has proven to be effective in driving political change in other jurisdictions. Individual stories of rare disease sufferers being denied expensive drug coverage also routinely ignite fierce public calls for government to institute more compassionate policies. Increasing public awareness of the overarching need for a centralized rare disease policy could also stimulate an effective grassroots movement. Strategies to educate and engage the public include direct discussions with affected patients, their families, and their friends (who should be encouraged to contact their MPs), promoting activities by rare disease advocacy groups (e.g., &#x0201c;Rare Disease Day in Canada 2011,&#x0201d; organized by CORD), and participating in awareness campaigns in mass-media publications and in social media (e.g., a 2011 Globe and Mail article highlighting the plight of Canadian rare disease sufferers).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></p><p>In the interim, or failing a federal solution, those who suffer from rare diseases and their advocates might turn to provincial governments to lead the development of rare disease programs. However, given our geographically dispersed population and the need for multicentre participation to recruit sufficient numbers of participants to rare disease studies, interprovincial partnerships for rare disease research funding, recruitment, and resource and expertise sharing will be required. Challenges include the wide range of political parties represented across provinces, their correspondingly eclectic health care priorities, and their various fiscal positions. However, these disparities would seem to pale in comparison with those between the 30 countries that have successfully instituted and currently uphold the many binding EU-wide legislative requirements and programs related to rare diseases. This suggests that a lack of political will may be the only barrier to success.</p><p>In this era of limited health care resources, a utilitarian approach to wealth distribution would argue that substantial resource investment in rare diseases fails to maximize the benefit to society by bringing the greatest good to the greatest number. However, the &#x0201c;paradox of rarity&#x0201d; is that, given the existence of over 6000 known rare diseases and the fact that 6% to 8% of the population is affected by a rare disease, even though each disease is rare, patients with rare diseases are many.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref></p><p>Based on a belief that our society&#x02019;s moral obligation is to protect each individual&#x02019;s rights, the Canada Health Act upholds the principle of &#x0201c;non-abandonment,&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref> whereby all Canadians should have &#x0201c;timely access to health services on the basis of need, not ability to pay &#x0201d; and &#x0201c;the health care services available to Canadians are of high quality, effective, patient-centred and safe.&#x0201d; Far beyond the simple question of access to drugs, a right to effective and high-quality care can not be fulfilled without addressing the fundamental gap in access to scientific advancement and research in rare diseases.</p><p>It is our duty to advocate for these patients by calling on our political leaders to join the rest of the developed world in legislating a comprehensive strategy to improve Canadian orphan disease care and research.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Competing interests: None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Funding source: None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Weely</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leufkens</surname><given-names>H G M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Background paper: orphan diseases</article-title><source>Priority medicines for Europe and the World&#x02014;a public health approach to innovation</source><year>2004</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Apr 11</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pharmaceuticalpolicy.nl/Publications/Reports/7.5%20Orphan%20diseases.pdf">http://www.pharmaceuticalpolicy.nl/Publications/Reports/7.5%20Orphan%20diseases.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hampton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rare disease research gets boost</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2006</year><month>6</month><day>28</day><volume>295</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>2836</fpage><lpage>2838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.295.24.2836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16804140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavandeira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orphan drugs: legal aspects, current situation</article-title><source>Haemophilia</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.wiley.com/10.1046/j.1365-2516.2002.00643.x">http://doi.wiley.com/10.1046/j.1365-2516.2002.00643.x</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2516.2002.00643.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12010410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haffner</surname><given-names>M E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adopting orphan drugs&#x02014;two dozen years of treating rare diseases</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2006</year><month>2</month><day>2</day><volume>354</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMp058317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>European Organisation for Rare Diseases</collab><source>Rare diseases in Australia: a piecemeal approach</source><year>2009</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2010 Aug 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurordis.org/content/rare-diseases-australia-piecemeal-approach">http://www.eurordis.org/content/rare-diseases-australia-piecemeal-approach</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panju</surname><given-names>Abbas H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>Chaim M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Policy alternatives for treatments for rare diseases</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><year>2010</year><month>7</month><day>12</day><volume>182</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20624867">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20624867</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1503/cmaj.081429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gericke</surname><given-names>C A</given-names></name><name><surname>Riesberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethical issues in funding orphan drug research and development</article-title><source>J Med Ethics</source><year>2005</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/15738438">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/15738438</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jme.2003.007138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15738438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taruscio</surname><given-names>Domenica</given-names></name><name><surname>Vittozzi</surname><given-names>Luciano</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanov</surname><given-names>Rumen</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>National plans and strategies on rare diseases in Europe</article-title><source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>686</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-90-481-9485-8_26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20824461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EU-US plans for joint funding of rare disease research unveiled to industry</article-title><source>Science Business</source><year>2011</year><month>7</month><day>18</day><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencebusiness.net/news/75276/EU-US-plans-for-joint-funding-of-rare-diseases-research-unveiled-to-industry">http://www.sciencebusiness.net/news/75276/EU-US-plans-for-joint-funding-of-rare-diseases-research-unveiled-to-industry</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>European Commission</collab><source>National plans or strategies for rare diseases</source><date-in-citation>accessed 2012 Jan 23</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/health/rare_diseases/national_plans/detailed/index_en.htm">http://ec.europa.eu/health/rare_diseases/national_plans/detailed/index_en.htm</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graf von der Schulenburg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The German plan for rare diseases: a development in progress</article-title><source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20964875">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/pmid/20964875</ext-link></comment><comment>Abstracts of the 5th European Conference on Rare Diseases (ECRD 2010). Krakow, Poland. May 13-15, 2010.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20964875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Orphanet</collab><source>Orphan drugs in Singapore</source><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 20</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/Education_AboutOrphanDrugs.php?lng=EN&#x00026;stapage=ST_EDUCATION_EDUCATION_ABOUTORPHANDRUGS_SIN">http://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/Education_AboutOrphanDrugs.php?lng=EN&#x00026;stapage=ST_EDUCATION_EDUCATION_ABOUTORPHANDRUGS_SIN</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Ministry of Health and Social Policy</collab><source>Rare diseases strategy of the Spanish National Health System</source><year>2009</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_threats/non_com/docs/rare_strategy_spain_en.pdf">http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_threats/non_com/docs/rare_strategy_spain_en.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>FDA Office of Orphan Products Development</collab><source>Developing products for rare diseases &#x00026; conditions</source><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/orphan/">http://www.fda.gov/orphan/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rados</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orphan products: hope for people with rare diseases</article-title><source>FDA Consum</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14986582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network</collab><source>Who are we?</source><date-in-citation>2011 Jul 30</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rarediseasesnetwork.epi.usf.edu/">http://rarediseasesnetwork.epi.usf.edu/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Europlan</collab><source>EUROPLAN: European Project for Rare Diseases National Plans Development</source><date-in-citation>2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.europlanproject.eu/Home.aspx">http://www.europlanproject.eu/Home.aspx</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>NIH Centers of Excellence</collab><source>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network. Overview</source><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Apr 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://report.nih.gov/biennialreportfy0607/pdf/NIH_BR_Ch4_rare.pdf">http://report.nih.gov/biennialreportfy0607/pdf/NIH_BR_Ch4_rare.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>European Organisation for Rare Diseases</collab><source>1st French National Plan for Rare Diseases, 2004&#x02013;2008, Evaluation After 4 Years</source><year>2009</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurordis.org/IMG/pdf/amm_09/1-4National_Plans_France_nourissier_may09.pdf">http://www.eurordis.org/IMG/pdf/amm_09/1-4National_Plans_France_nourissier_may09.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>EuroBioBank</collab><source>About EuroBioBank</source><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurobiobank.org/en/information/info_institut.htm">http://www.eurobiobank.org/en/information/info_institut.htm</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Organization for Rare Disorders</collab><source>About NORD</source><year>2011</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarediseases.org/about">http://www.rarediseases.org/about</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Organization for Rare Disorders</collab><source>Research grants</source><year>2011</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rarediseases.org/medical-professionals/research-grants">http://www.rarediseases.org/medical-professionals/research-grants</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>European Organisation for Rare Diseases</collab><source>Rare Diseases: understanding this public health priority</source><year>2005</year><month>1</month><day>6</day><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Apr 10</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://archive.eurordis.org/article.php3?id_article=918">http://archive.eurordis.org/article.php3?id_article=918</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Government of Canada</collab><source>Budget 2000&#x02013;2001 estimates. Parts 1 and II: the government expenditure plan and the main estimates</source><year>2000</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/webarchives/20060116224833/http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/est-pre/20002001/e_me00.pdf">http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/webarchives/20060116224833/http://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/est-pre/20002001/e_me00.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</collab><source>Annual report 2009&#x02013;2010. Knowledge to action: CIHR-supported health research at work for Canada and Canadians</source><year>2010</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/42205.html">http://www.cihr-irsc.gc.ca/e/42205.html</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Government of Canada</collab><source>ResearchNet. Canadian Institutes of Health Research emerging team grant: rare diseases</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.researchnet-recherchenet.ca/rnr16/viewOpportunityDetails.do?prog=1149&#x00026;view=currentOpps&#x00026;org=CIHR&#x00026;type=AND&#x00026;resultCount=25&#x00026;sort=program&#x00026;all=1&#x00026;masterList=true">http://www.researchnet-recherchenet.ca/rnr16/viewOpportunityDetails.do?prog=1149&#x00026;view=currentOpps&#x00026;org=CIHR&#x00026;type=AND&#x00026;resultCount=25&#x00026;sort=program&#x00026;all=1&#x00026;masterList=true</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><source>Canada. House of Commons. Debates. Vol. 142, no. 078. 2nd Session, 39th Parliament</source><year>2008</year><month>4</month><day>14</day><fpage>4847</fpage><lpage>4849</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>The Canadian PKU and Allied Disorders</collab><source>Motion M-426: A call for a rare disease plan in Canada passes in House of Commons</source><year>2011</year><date-in-citation>accessed 2011 Aug 11</date-in-citation><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.canpku.org/pku-news/24-motion-m-426">http://www.canpku.org/pku-news/24-motion-m-426</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><source>Canada. House of Commons. Debates. Vol. 142, no. 078. 2nd Session, 39th Parliament</source><year>2008</year><month>5</month><day>7</day><fpage>5573</fpage><lpage>5574</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In surprise move, Flaherty lays out health-spending plans til 2024</article-title><source>Globe and Mail (Toronto)</source><year>2011</year><month>12</month><day>19</day><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/in-surprise-move-flaherty-lays-out-health-spending-plans-til-2024/article2276354/">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/in-surprise-move-flaherty-lays-out-health-spending-plans-til-2024/article2276354/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>National drug policy for rare diseases has fallen between the cracks</article-title><source>Globe and Mail (Toronto)</source><year>2011</year><month>4</month><day>4</day><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/time-to-lead/national-drug-policy-for-rare-diseases-has-fallen-between-the-cracks/article1970960/">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/time-to-lead/national-drug-policy-for-rare-diseases-has-fallen-between-the-cracks/article1970960/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>